TST1-MUC3-0001

GUATEMALA CITY, 4 FEB 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE GUATEMALA ARMY DENIED TODAY THAT GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE "SANTO TOMAS" PRESIDENTIAL FARM, LOCATED ON THE PACIFIC SIDE, WHERE PRESIDENT CEREZO HAS BEEN STAYING SINCE 2 FEBRUARY.

A REPORT PUBLISHED BY THE "CERIGUA" NEWS AGENCY -- MOUTHPIECE OF THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY (URNG) -- WHOSE MAIN OFFICES ARE IN MEXICO, SAYS THAT A GUERRILLA COLUMN ATTACKED THE FARM 2 DAYS AGO.

HOWEVER, ARMED FORCES SPOKESMAN COLONEL LUIS ARTURO ISAACS SAID THAT THE ATTACK, WHICH RESULTED IN THE DEATH OF A CIVILIAN WHO WAS PASSING BY AT THE TIME OF THE SKIRMISH, WAS NOT AGAINST THE FARM, AND THAT PRESIDENT CEREZO IS SAFE AND SOUND.

HE ADDED THAT ON 3 FEBRUARY PRESIDENT CEREZO MET WITH THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS ACCREDITED IN GUATEMALA.

THE GOVERNMENT ALSO ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE DESCRIBING THE REBEL REPORT AS "FALSE AND INCORRECT," AND STRESSING THAT THE PRESIDENT WAS NEVER IN DANGER.

COL ISAACS SAID THAT THE GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE "LA EMINENCIA" FARM LOCATED NEAR THE "SANTO TOMAS" FARM, WHERE THEY BURNED THE FACILITIES AND STOLE FOOD.

A MILITARY PATROL CLASHED WITH A REBEL COLUMN AND INFLICTED THREE CASUALTIES, WHICH WERE TAKEN AWAY BY THE GUERRILLAS WHO FLED TO THE MOUNTAINS, ISAACS NOTED.

HE ALSO REPORTED THAT GUERRILLAS KILLED A PEASANT IN THE CITY OF FLORES, IN THE NORTHERN EL PETEN DEPARTMENT, AND BURNED A TANK TRUCK.

TST1-MUC3-0003

SAN SALVADOR, 4 APR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] EL SALVADOR'S SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE HAS RELIEVED JUDGE HECTOR LARIOS OF HIS DUTIES AS JUDGE AND NOTARY BECAUSE HE ORDERED THE RELEASE OF A BAND OF ALLEGED KIDNAPPERS.

THE NEW JUDGE, RICARDO MEJIA, OVERTURNED THE RULING TO RELEASE THE EIGHT PEOPLE ACCUSED OF KIDAPPING AT LEAST SIX WEALTHY SALVADORANS IN THE EARLY 1980'S.

SUPREME COURT CHIEF JUSTICE FRANCISCO JOSE GUERRERO ANNOUNCED LARIOS' DISMISSAL AND SUSPENDED HIS LICENSE TO PRACTICE LAW. "BASED ON A REVIEW OF LARIOS' IRREGULAR RULING, ONE CAN CONCLUDE THAT HIS BEHAVIOR IS UNBECOMING AN OFFICIAL WORTHY OF THE SUPREME COURT'S TRUST. WE ARE DISMAYED BY THAT JUDGE'S CONDUCT," HE NOTED.

MOREOVER, MEJIA OVERTURNED THE RULING ORDERING THE RELEASE OF ORLANDO LLOVERA BALLET, LIEUTENANT ISIDRO LOPEZ, MAJOR ALFREDO JIMENEZ, AND OTHER MEMBERS OF THE KIDNAPPING RING.

LARIOS DECIDED ON FRIDAY TO RELEASE THE MEMBERS OF THE KIDNAPPING RING, WHICH INCLUDED SOME ARMY OFFICERS AND SYMPATHIZERS OF THE RIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA), WHICH WON THE 19 MARCH PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS.

"THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THE SUPREME COURT HAS LEVIED THIS KIND OF SANCTION IN A CASE SETTING A PRECEDENT IN JUDICIAL CORRUPTION," A COURT OFFICIAL ASSERTED, REFERRING TO LARIOS' DISMISSAL. LARIOS IS ALSO ACCUSED OF RELEASING MEMBERS OF A DRUG TRAFFICKING RING SOME YEARS AGO.

BECAUSE THE RULING ON THE KIDNAPPERS WAS OVERTURNED, "THE CASE GOES BACK TO THE LOWER COURTS," THE NEW JUDGE SAID.

THE KIDNAPPERS, SOME OF WHOM HAVE BEEN UNDER ARREST SINCE APRIL 1986, WERE ACCUSED OF KIDNAPPING SEVERAL BUSINESSMEN FOR HIGH SUMS OF MONEY.

LARIOS'S RULING IN FAVOR OF THE KIDNAPPERS PROMPTED A BITTER REACTION FROM GOVERNMENT, POLITICAL, AND PROFESSIONAL SECTORS. THE NATIONAL AD COUNCIL, REPRESENTING NEWS MEDIA ANNOUNCERS, HAS URGED THAT THE KIDNAPPERS BE PROSECUTED TO THE FULL EXTENT OF THE LAW "SO THAT THOSE WHO PROFIT FROM THE SUFFERING OF OTHERS ARE PUNISHED."

TST1-MUC3-0004

BOGOTA, 30 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] LAST NIGHT'S TERRORIST TARGET WAS THE ANTIOQUIA LIQUEUR PLANT. FOUR POWERFUL ROCKETS WERE GOING TO EXPLODE VERY CLOSE TO THE TANKS WHERE 300,000 GALLONS OF THE SO-CALLED CASTILLE CRUDE, USED TO OPERATE THE BOILERS, IS STORED. THE WATCHMEN ON DUTY REPORTED THAT AT 2030 THEY SAW A MAN AND A WOMAN LEAVING A SMALL SUITCASE NEAR THE FENCE THAT SURROUNDS THE PLANT. THE WATCHMEN EXCHANGED FIRE WITH THE TERRORISTS WHO FLED LEAVING BEHIND THE EXPLOSIVE MATERIAL THAT ALSO INCLUDED DYNAMITE AND GRENADE ROCKET LAUNCHERS. METROPOLITAN POLICE PERSONNEL SPECIALIZING IN EXPLOSIVES, DEFUSED THE ROCKETS. SOME 100 PEOPLE WERE WORKING INSIDE THE PLANT.

THE DAMAGE THE ROCKETS WOULD HAVE CAUSED HAD THEY BEEN ACTIVATED CANNOT BE ESTIMATED BECAUSE THE CARIBE SODA FACTORY AND THE GUAYABAL RESIDENTIAL AREA WOULD HAVE ALSO BEEN AFFECTED.

THE ANTIOQUIA LIQUEUR PLANT HAS RECEIVED THREATS IN THE PAST AND MAXIMUM SECURITY HAS ALWAYS BEEN PRACTICED IN THE AREA. SECURITY WAS STEPPED UP LAST NIGHT AFTER THE INCIDENT. THE LIQUEUR INDUSTRY IS THE LARGEST FOREIGN EXCHANGE PRODUCER FOR THE DEPARTMENT.

TST1-MUC3-0005

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 11 DEC 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH LIEUTENANT COLONEL RICARDO WHEELOCK, CHIEF OF THE NICARAGUAN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE DIRECTORATE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] HOW ABOUT THE SANDINIST SOLDIERS THAT ALLEGEDLY [WORDS INDISTINCT]. NO SANDINIST SOLDIERS ARE BEING HELD BY THE CREW OF THAT BOAT?

[WHEELOCK] THAT IS WHAT I SAID. FURTHERMORE, ONE OF THE BOATS WITH 50 CREW MEMBERS HAS SHOWN UP IN HONDURAS AND IT IS WHAT IS CAUSING THIS PROBLEM.

[REPORTER] THERE ARE SOME PROBLEMS WITH SOME COLOMBIANS CONCERNING CONTRABAND, RIGHT?

[WHEELOCK] WE ARE THERE TO PROTECT THE FISHING RESOURCES AND TO PREVENT ANY TYPE OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, GUN RUNNING OR ANY MERCHANDISE CONTRABAND.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] HOW DID THE MUTINY OCCUR?

[WHEELOCK] FROM THE TIME THEY WERE CAPTURED AND ON THE WAY TO CORN ISLAND, ONE OF THE OFFICERS ON BOARD WAS CARELESS. THEN, THE COOK AND THE CAPTAIN DISARMED ONE OF THE SOLDIERS, TOOK AWAY HIS RIFLE, AND THEY KILLED HIM. THE CREW THEN AVAILED ITSELF OF THIS INCIDENT TO RISE UP IN MUTINY. THE CAPTAIN WAS STRANGLING ONE OF THE OFFICERS WHEN ANOTHER OFFICER PULLED UP GUN ON HIM. HE IS THE CAPTAIN WHO RAN THE SHIP AGROUND IN A CORAL REEF. [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE SHIPOWNERS WILL HAVE TO PAY A FINE AND AFTER THE FINE IS PAID, THEY MUST COMPLY WITH ALL LEGAL REQUIREMENTS SO THAT THE BOAT AND CREW ARE RETURNED TO THEM.

TST1-MUC3-0006

BOGOTA, 18 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [EXCERPTS] THE EXTRADITABLES TODAY CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER OF ANTIOQUIA POLICE COMMANDER COLONEL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO, WHICH OCCURRED THIS MORNING IN MEDELLIN. THE CRIMINAL ATTACK ON THE OFFICER OCCURED A SCANT 1 MONTH AFTER THE MURDER OF ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT GOVERNOR ANTONIO ROLDAN BETANCUR.

A POLICEMAN WAS KILLED AND ANOTHER POLICEMAN WOUNDED DURING THE TERRORIST ATTACK. COL QUINTERO DID NOT HAVE A POLICE ESCORT BY HIS OWN BEHEST. COL QUINTERO WAS DIRECTING OPERATIONS AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING AND CONSEQUENTLY HAD BEEN THE OBJECT OF DEATH THREATS. HERE IS A REPORT BY GLADYS VARGAS FROM MEDELLIN.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] THIS MORNING ANTIOQUIA POLICE COMMANDER COL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO LEFT HIS RESIDENCE TO BEGIN HIS DAILY TASKS AT ANTIOQUIA POLICE HEADQUARTERS. AS THE VEHICLE DROVE THROUGH THE AMERICA NEIGHBORHOOD, SEVEN BLOCKS FROM WHERE ANTIOQUIA GOVERNOR ANTONIO ROLDAN WAS KILLED, THE VEHICLE THAT COL QUINTERO WAS IN -- A WHITE NISSAN PATROL VEHICLE WITH LICENSE PLATES ME-7847 -- DREW TO A STOP IN FRONT OF A RED LIGHT AT THE CARRERA 80 CROSSING. SEVERAL INDIVIDUALS IN A GRAY MAZDA 626 VEHICLE, WITH LICENSE PLATES MI-1630, TOOK ADVANTAGE OF THIS CIRCUMSTANCE TO FIRE VOLLEYS OF SUBMACHINEGUN FIRE AGAINST COL QUINTERO, WHO DIED INSTANTLY. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

COL QUINTERO DID NOT HAVE A POLICE ESCORT. JUST 8 DAYS AGO HE DECIDED TO DISMISS THE ESCORT, BECAUSE HE DID NOT WANT ANYONE ELSE TO BE KILLED IF THERE WERE AN ATTACK ON HIM. ONLY COL QUINTERO AND A POLICE DRIVER WERE IN THE VEHICLE.

THE JUDGE OF THE 76TH DISTRICT COURT, WHO DIRECTED THE REMOVAL OF THE BODY, SAID THAT SEVERAL TYPES OF WEAPONS WERE USED IN THE ATTACK AND MORE THAN 100 SHOTS WERE FIRED. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

TST1-MUC3-0008

BOGOTA, 14 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] DIEGO BIAFARA, ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY [DAS] AND DRUG ENFORCEMENT AGENCY INFORMANT, WHO APPEARED BEFORE A U.S. SENATE COMMITTEE ON 13 SEPTEMBER, REVEALED UNKNOWN LINKS BETWEEN THE ISRAELI AND BRITISH MERCENARIES, WHO HAVE TRAINED PARAMILITARY GROUPS IN OUR COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BIAFARA] THAT IS YAIR KLEIN IN FRONT. HE IS THE COLONEL WEARING THE DARK BLUE SHIRT. THE THIN PERSON BEHIND HIM WEARING THE LIGHT BLUE SHIRT IS TEDDY, WHO WAS THE TRANSLATOR. THERE WERE FIVE ISRAELI INSTRUCTORS. I REMEMBER THE NAMES: SADAKA, AMANCIA, YAIR, AND TEDDY. I CANNOT REMEMBER THE NAME OF THE FIFTH ONE. THERE WERE 11 BRITISH INSTRUCTORS. WE USED TO CALL THAT ONE DAVID. THIS MAN WAS AN EXPERT IN EXPLOSIVES. HE INSTRUCTED US ON HOW TO USE EXPLOSIVES. [END RECORDING]

THESE WERE STATEMENTS MADE BY BIAFARA TO THE U.S. SENATE IN WHICH WE LEARNED OF A CLEAR LINK BETWEEN THE ISRAELI MERCENARIES, WHO WERE TRAINING PARAMILITARY GROUPS IN THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA REGION, AND THE BRITISH MERCENARIES WHO CAME TO THE COUNTRY ALLEGEDLY TO ASSASSINATE PABLO ESCOBAR.

BIAFARA KNEW BOTH GROUPS OF MERCENARIES. ACCORDING TO HIS STATEMENTS GIVEN TO DAS LAST MARCH, NOT ONLY DID ISRAELI MERCENARIES TRAIN ASSASSINS IN MIDDLE MAGDALENA, THERE WAS ALSO A GROUP OF 11 BRITISH MERCENARIES, WHO GAVE LESSONS TO 50 STUDENTS. AMONG THE INSTRUCTORS THERE WAS PETER MCLISE, THE NAME OF ONE OF THE LEADERS OF THE OPERATION AGAINST PABLO ESCOBAR, AND DAVID, WHO BIAFARA CLEARLY IDENTIFIED. HE WAS DAVID TOMKINS, THE MAN IN CHARGE OF THE PLOT AGAINST ESCOBAR. ACCORDING TO BIAFARA, MOST BRITISH INSTRUCTORS HAD TATOOS ON THEIR BREASTS, ARMS, AND SHOULDERS, JUST AS WE CAN SEE ON THE VIDEO TAPED BY THE BRITISH MEN WHO PREPARED THE OPERATION AGAINST ESCOBAR.

IN CONCLUSION, THE MERCENARIES WHO WERE PREPARING TO ASSASSINATE ONE OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL LEADERS WERE THE SAME ONES WHO TRAINED THE ASSASSINS PAID BY THE CARTEL ITSELF.

TST1-MUC3-0010

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] ESTEEMED MEMBERS OF THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION:

TODAY, 9 MARCH, WE HAVE RECEIVED A MESSAGE SIGNED BY THE MEMBERS OF YOUR COMMISSION ASKING US TO BEGIN THE PEACE TALKS. WE HAVE ALREADY ADDRESSED THIS ISSUE ON NUMEROUS OCCASIONS, EXPRESSING OUR WILLINGNESS TO HOLD A MEETING. THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION'S LETTER MAKES NO MENTION OF ANY MOVE TO POSTPONE THE ELECTIONS. IT DOES NOT EVEN CONSIDER INCLUDING THIS TOPIC ON THE MEETING'S AGENDA. ON THE CONTRARY, IT IS CLEAR THAT THE COMMISSION HAS ALREADY DECIDED TO HOLD THE ELECTIONS ON 19 MARCH.

CONSEQUENTLY, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HEREBY INFORMS THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE OF THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION MUST CLEARLY AND PUBLICLY ANNOUNCE THAT IT IS WILLING TO REACH AN AGREEMENT ON CONFINING THE ARMY TO ITS BARRACKS ON THE DAY OF THE ELECTIONS, ESTABLISHING AN ELECTORAL CODE BY CONSENSUS, PROVIDING ABSENTEE VOTING FOR SALVADORANS LIVING ABROAD, RESTRUCTURING THE CENTRAL ELECTIONS COUNCIL, AND FORMING A COUNCIL FOR VERIFICATION.

MORE IMPORTANTLY, IT MUST EXPRESS THE STATE POWERS' WILLINGNESS TO POSTPONE THE ELECTIONS FOR 5 MONTHS, ONCE A CEASE-FIRE HAS BEEN AGREED UPON. WE ALSO BELIEVE THAT THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION MUST PUBLICLY ANNOUNCE THAT IT IS WILLING TO BRING MILITARY COMMANDERS AND OFFICERS RESPONSIBLE FOR POLITICAL MURDERS AND CRIMES TO TRIAL, TO REDUCE THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES TO THE NUMBER OF TROOPS IT HAD IN 1968, AND TO DISBAND THE SECURITY FORCES TO FORM A NEW CIVIL POLICE. WE REITERATE OUR WILLINGNESS TO DISCUSS PERMANENTLY CEASING THE ARMED STRUGGLE.

2. IF THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION AGREES TO THE ABOVE REQUESTS, THE FMLN WILL AGREE TO A MEETING AND IS WILLING TO IMMEDIATELY DECIDE ON A DATE AND A TIME FOR THE MEETING. THE FMLN IS EVEN WILLING TO HOLD THE MEETING OUTSIDE EL SALVADOR. AS A PART OF THIS MEETING, WE ARE WILLING TO NEGOTIATE AND COME TO AN AGREEMENT WITH THE ARMED FORCES STAFF ON A CEASE-FIRE THAT WILL BRING ABOUT A PERMANENT AND NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT.

3. IF NO SUCH AGREEMENT IS REACHED, THEN THERE IS NO POINT IN HOLDING THE MEETING PRIOR TO 19 MARCH, BECAUSE IT WILL SIMPLY BE USED BY BOTH THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] AND THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] IN THEIR ELECTION DISPUTE. THE ELECTIONS PLAY NO ROLE IN ACHIEVING PEACE; THEY ONLY SERVE TO PROVIDE A FALSE JUSTIFICATION FOR CONTINUING THE WAR.

4. WE AWAIT A RESPONSE FROM THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION.

EL SALVADOR, 9 MARCH 1989

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[SIGNED] COMMANDER SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN

COMMANDER FRANCISCO JOVEL

COMMANDER JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL

COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO

COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS

TST1-MUC3-0011

SANTIAGO, 18 MAY 90 (RADIO COOPERATIVA NETWORK) -- [REPORT] [JUAN ARAYA] [TEXT] EDMUNDO VARGAS CARRENO, CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTRY UNDER SECRETARY, HAS STATED THAT THE BRYANT TREATY WITH THE UNITED STATES WILL BE APPLIED IN THE LETELIER CASE ONLY TO COMPENSATE THE RELATIVES OF THE FORMER CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTER MURDERED IN WASHINGTON AND THE RELATIVES OF HIS U.S. SECRETARY, RONNIE MOFFIT. THE CHILEAN FOREIGN UNDER SECRETARY MADE THIS STATEMENT IN REPLY TO U.S. NEWSPAPER REPORTS STATING THAT THE TREATY WOULD BE PARTIALLY RESPECTED.

FOLLOWING ARE VARGAS CARRENO'S STATEMENTS AT A NEWS CONFERENCE HE HELD IN BUENOS AIRES BEFORE CONCLUDING HIS OFFICIAL VISIT TO ARGENTINA:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] THIS TREATY [WORDS INDISTINCT] USED BY THE UNITED STATES IN 1989, DURING THE PAST ADMINISTRATION, TO SOLVE TWO PROBLEMS CONNECTED WITH THE LETELIER CASE: THE PROBLEM OF COMPENSATION AND THE PROBLEM OF THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE DEATH OF ORLANDO LETELIER AND HIS [WORDS INDISTINCT] ASSISTANT.

IT HAS BEEN AGREED IN PRINCIPLE TO USE THE TREATY EXCLUSIVELY TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM OF COMPENSATION; THAT IS THE OBJECTIVE WHEN WE REFER TO ITS PARTIAL USE. [WORDS INDISTINCT] SO AS FOR THE COMPENSATION SUBJECT, IT WILL BE USED. WE ARE USING THE MECHANISM CREATED BY THE FIVE-MEMBER COMMISSION ESTABLISHED BY THE TREATY. THE LANGUAGE OF THIS TREATY WAS PERTINENT FOR THE EARLY DECADES OF THIS CENTURY BUT IS NO LONGER IN KEEPING WITH CURRENT INTERNATIONAL PRACTICES. [END RECORDING]

DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE WITH ARGENTINE AND FOREIGN JOURNALISTS, VARGAS CARRENO ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM WILL VISIT CHILE IN AUGUST IN RESPONSE TO AN INVITATION FROM CHILEAN PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN, WHO WILL ALSO VISIT ARGENTINA AT AN AS YET UNDETERMINED DATE.

VARGAS CARRENO NOTED HIS SATISFACTION WITH HIS MEETINGS IN BUENOS AIRES WITH FOREIGN MINISTER DOMINGO CAVALLO AND RAUL CARIGNANO, UNDER SECRETARY FOR LATIN AMERICAN AFFAIRS. VARGAS CARRENO SAID THAT AS A RESULT OF THIS INITIAL CONTACT THE BINATIONAL COMMISSION ESTABLISHED BY THE CHILEAN-ARGENTINE PEACE AND FRIENDSHIP TREATY, WHICH WAS SIGNED IN 1984, WILL MEET NEXT JULY. HE SAID THAT THE TWO COUNTRIES WILL CONTINUE TO HOLD FORMAL AND INFORMAL TALKS TO DISCUSS PROBLEMS OF COMMON INTEREST, SPEED UP THE INTEGRATION PROCESS, AND INCREASE MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING AND COOPERATION.

REGARDING THE SITUATION OF HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF CHILEAN CITIZENS LIVING IN ARGENTINA -- A TOTAL HE ESTIMATED AT 800,000 -- VARGAS CARRENO SAID THAT PRESIDENT AYLWIN'S GOVERNMENT HAS ESTABLISHED AN OFFICE TO HELP THOSE CITIZENS LIVING ABROAD FOR VARIOUS REASONS TO RETURN TO CHILE, ESPECIALLY THOSE LIVING IN ARGENTINA'S PATAGONIA REGION WHO ARE BEING TREATED INHUMANELY, ESPECIALLY BY BUSINESSMEN IN THE BORDER AREA, AS REPORTED BY AN ARGENTINE JOURNALIST.

TST1-MUC3-0013

LIMA, 20 DEC 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [EXCERPT] THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH HAS CALLED A SPECIAL SESSION OF CONGRESS FOR TOMORROW AND THE NEXT DAY TO CONSIDER THE SERIOUS SITUATION OF PANAMA AND TO DENOUNCE THE INTER-AMERICAN RECIPROCAL ASSISTANCE TREATY, TIAR, FOR ITS INEFFECTIVENESS. THIS WAS ANNOUNCED BY PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AT THE CONCLUSION OF A COUNCIL OF MINISTERS MEETING AT GOVERNMENT HOUSE TODAY. THE PRESIDENT ALSO EXPRESSED HIS SURPRISE OVER THE MILDNESS WITH WHICH THE REST OF THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES HAVE REACTED TO THE U.S. AGGRESSION AGAINST PANAMA. PRESIDENT GARCIA ALSO SAID THAT THE FUEL PRICE INCREASE WILL ALLOW PETROPERU [STATE PETROLEUM AGENCY] TO OPERATE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] WHAT IMPORTANT SUBJECTS WERE DISCUSSED IN THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS MEETING TODAY?

[GARCIA] THE MAIN SUBJECT WAS THE DECISION TO CALL A SPECIAL CONGRESSIONAL SESSION ON 22 AND 23 DECEMBER TO CONSIDER THE SERIOUS SITUATION CREATED BY THE U.S. INVASION IN PANAMA. THE SECOND IMPORTANT SUBJECT WAS THE DECISION TO DENOUNCE THE TIAR, A MILITARY ORGANIZATION THAT GROUPS ALL THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES AND THE UNITED STATES AND WHICH, ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS, HAS PROVED TO BE ABSOLUTELY INEFFECTIVE AND PARTIAL.

THE MALVINAS ISLANDS SITUATION IS A GOOD EXAMPLE. ACCORDING TO THE TIAR, THE UNITED STATES SHOULD HAVE SUPPORTED ARGENTINA, BUT IT DID EXACTLY THE CONTRARY, SUPPORTING THE UNITED KINGDOM.

NOW, IN THIS CASE WITH PANAMA, THE TIAR HAS NOT SERVED ANY PURPOSE. RATHER, IT HAS SERVED TO MASK THE U.S. INVASION OF PANAMA. THEREFORE, SINCE WE CONSIDER THE TIAR TO BE INEFFECTIVE AND SENSELESS, WE, AS A REPUBLIC, MUST DENOUNCE IT. WE MUST WITHDRAW OUR SIGNATURE FROM THE TIAR. THIS MUST BE DONE THROUGH CONGRESS, AND THAT IS WHY WE HAVE CALLED A SPECIAL SESSION.

[REPORTER] SEVERAL SECTORS HAVE DESCRIBED THE DECISION TO WITHDRAW THE PERUVIAN AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED STATES AS A HASTY DECISION. WHAT DO YOU THINK OF THAT?

[GARCIA] I THINK THAT THOSE MUST BE SECTORS COMMITTED TO THE INVASION. THEY MUST SUPPORT A RIGHTIST CONCEPT BY WHICH THE UNITED STATES HAS THE HEGEMONIC RIGHT TO SAFEGUARD OUR DESTINY AND TO DECIDE WHO CAN GOVERN US AND WHO CANNOT.

AS PERUVIANS AND LATIN AMERICANS, WE FEEL THAT THE AGGRESSIVE AND BLOODY ACTION BY U.S. TROOPS TO OCCUPY A SMALL COUNTRY IS A VIOLATION. THERE ARE CURRENTLY NEARLY 30,000 U.S. SOLDIERS IN PANAMANIAN TERRITORY. THEY HAVE KILLED MANY PEOPLE AND THEY WANT TO IMPOSE A NEW GOVERNMENT. THUS, AS LONG AS THOSE TROOPS REMAIN THERE, AS LONG AS THIS VIOLATION TO LATIN AMERICA IS MAINTAINED, OUR AMBASSADOR WILL NOT STAY IN THAT COUNTRY. THIS DOES NOT IMPLY A BREAK IN RELATIONS; IT REPRESENTS A CLEAR GESTURE OF CONDEMNATION AND DISLIKE.

AS LONG AS A U.S. SOLDIER VIOLATES THE REPUBLIC OF PANAMA, WE WILL KEEP OUR AMBASSADOR HERE. AS LONG AS THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT WITHDRAW THEIR TROOPS AND PANAMA REMAINS OCCUPIED, THE PANAMANIAN AND PERUVIAN FLAGS WILL REMAIN TOGETHER.

[REPORTER] DON'T YOU THINK THAT THIS ATTITUDE COULD HARM CERTAIN RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES; THAT IS, COULDN'T IT JEOPARDIZE THE IMF LOAN?

[GARCIA] NOT AT ALL. THESE ARE TWO ABSOLUTELY DIFFERENT THINGS. THE NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE IMF ARE ONE THING; THE INTERNATIONAL POLITICAL ATTITUDE OF A GOVERNMENT THAT ABUSES ITS ECONOMIC AND MILITARY POWER WITH OTHER COUNTRIES IS SOMETHING ELSE.

BESIDES, WE SHOULD MENTION SOMETHING VERY IMPORTANT. AS FOR PANAMANIAN-U.S. RELATIONS, THE AMERICANS HAVE BEEN THE MAIN ACCOMPLICES IN DEPRIVING PANAMA OF DEMOCRACY. WHEN ELECTIONS TOOK PLACE IN 1984, WHEN ARNULFO ARIAS SHOULD HAVE WON, THE UNITED STATES DECIDED THAT IT WAS NOT CONVENIENT THAT ARIAS SHOULD WIN, SO A LARGE FRAUD -- AS IT WAS DECLARED AT THE TIME -- WAS CARRIED OUT TO PLACE NICOLAS ARDITO BARLETTA IN POWER. THE FIRST ONES TO RECOGNIZE ARDITO WERE THE AMERICANS. ARDITO WAS PLACED IN THE PRESIDENCY BY NORIEGA.

IN 1985 NORIEGA REMOVED ARDITO AND PUT ERIC ARTURO DEL VALLE IN HIS PLACE. THE AMERICANS IMMEDIATELY RECOGNIZED DEL VALLE AS PRESIDENT. THEREFORE, THE UNITED STATES HAS BEEN NORIEGA'S ACCOMPLICE IN DEPRIVING PANAMA OF DEMOCRACY. WE DENOUNCED THIS. NORIEGA IS A CREATION OF THE UNITED STATES. IT HAS REPEATEDLY BEEN SAID THAT NORIEGA WORKED WITH THE UNITED STATES AND WITH THE U.S. CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY, WHERE PRESIDENT BUSH WAS ONCE CHIEF.

THEREFORE, NOW THAT THE MAID IS ANSWERING BACK, MAKING CLAIMS TO THE PANAMA CANAL AND WANTING TO BECOME INDEPENDENT FROM THE UNITED STATES, THE UNITED STATES SUDDENLY DISCOVERS THAT SHE IS A DRUG TRAFFICKER AND THAT SHE DOES NOT SERVE ITS INTERESTS, SO THEY SEND 30,000 U.S. SOLDIERS TO PANAMA. THIS IS AN ABUSE. IT IS A VIOLATION OF THE SOVEREIGNTY OF ANOTHER STATE.

NO HONORABLE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY SHOULD TOLERATE THIS INVASION WITHOUT ACTIVELY AND OPENLY CONDEMNING IT. ONE WAY TO CONDEMN IT AND EXPRESS DISAPPROVAL OF IT IS TO SAY THAT AS LONG AS THE TROOPS INVADING LATIN AMERICA REMAIN, WE DO NOT NEED TO MAINTAIN OUR AMBASSADOR THERE. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0016

CLANDESTINE, 23 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE OFFICERS AND EVERYONE ELSE IN THE ARMY MUST THINK THIS OVER. THEY CANNOT CONTINUE CLOSING THEIR EYES TO THE BOMBINGS, TO THE THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE LEFT THE POOR NEIGHBORHOODS OF SAN SALVADOR, TO THE MOTHERS WHO APPEAR CRYING ON TELEVISION. IT IS GOOD THAT THE NETWORK PRESENTS THESE PICTURES OF PEOPLE CRYING, MANIPULATING THEIR EMOTIONS. THOSE TEARS WERE SHED OVER 50 YEARS OF OPPRESSION AND MISERY, AND OVER THE BOMBINGS THAT HAVE DESTROYED ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. OFFICERS, THE BOMBS HAVE CAUSED ALL THAT SORROW AND THE DESTRUCTION OF 500 HOUSES IN ZACAMIL.

AS WE WERE SAYING, OFFICERS, YOU MUST ASK YOURSELVES: WHO ARE YOU DYING FOR? FOR COLONEL PONCE'S MANSIONS IN MIAMI? FOR GENERAL BUSTILLO'S MANSIONS? WHY ARE THE ARMED FORCES MEMBERS DYING HERE? WHY ARE THE LIEUTENANTS, THE CAPITAINS DYING, WHILE THE MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES HIERARCHY ARE CONFORTABLY SITTING IN THEIR AIR-CONDITIONED OFFICES BEING GUARDED WHILE THEY ARE AT EASE, BUT NOT REALLY AT EASE AS COMBAT IS TAKING PLACE JUST A FEW BLOCKS FROM THEIR OFFICE.

OFFICERS, LIEUTENANTS, CAPTAINS, THIS IS THE APPEAL THE FMLN WANTS MAKE TO YOU TODAY, AT A TIME WHEN THE FUTURE OF THE FATHERLAND IS AT STAKE? YOU MUST THINK THIS OVER, YOU MUST MAKE A DECISION, AND YOU MUST DO THIS SOON. HISTORY IS MOVING FAST, AND THE TIME IS RIPE. SO WHEN YOU ARE TOLD THAT YOU ARE DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION, THINK ABOUT WHAT WE ARE TELLING YOU. IF YOU ARE DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION, THINK ABOUT WHAT WE ARE SAYING. IF WE ARE DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION HERE, WHY IS THIS CONSTITUTION BEING VIOLATED BY THOSE RAMBOS SENT BY PRESIDENT BUSH TO EL SALVADOR? YOU ALL KNOW THIS LITTLE GROUP OF RAMBOS IS GOOD FOR NOTHING, AS THEY ARE COWARDS. THEY DID NOT WANT TO LEAVE THE SHERATON HOTEL, BECAUSE THE GUERRILLAS WERE THERE. THEY ARE COWARDS, JUST LIKE THEIR SYSTEM. THEY ARE TINHORN RAMBOS, WHO ARE ABSOLUTELY NO GOOD.

AS WE SAID YESTERDAY, IF THOSE MEN WHO LEFT THE SHERATON LIKE COMMON CRIMINALS COVERING THEIR FACES FROM THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS ARE THE ONES WHO ARE TRAINING THE ARMED FORCES, WE CAN UNDERSTAND BETTER WHY THE FMLN IS DEFEATING THE TACTICS TAUGHT BY THEM. THEY ARE NO GOOD, BECAUSE THEY DO NOT UNDERSTAND OUR PEOPLE, THEY UNDERESTIMATE OUR PEOPLE. OFFICERS, YOU KNOW THOSE U.S. ADVISERS UNDERESTIMATE YOU, THEY LOOK DOWN ON YOU, AS LITTLE INDIANS, AS DONKEYS. YOU KNOW HOW THEY THINK OF YOU. YOU KOW THEY MOCK THE SALVADORAN OFFICERS. OFFICERS, YOU KNOW VERY WELL HOW THESE U.S. ADVISERS TREAT OUR SOLDIERS. THEY ARE HAUGHTY, ARROGANT, AND COWARDS. YOU SAW THEM AT THE SHERATON HOTEL, PISSING IN THEIR PANTS, THEY DID NOT WANT TO LEAVE THE HOTEL. A COMMISSION WENT THERE, THE RED CROSS WENT THERE, BUT THEY DID NOT WANT TO LEAVE, BECAUSE THEY WERE NOT SURE OF THEMSELVES DURING THE TRUCE, SIMPLY BECAUSE THEY ARE COWARDS.

WE WANT THE CIN [NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER], THAT FASCIST NETWORK THAT IS SILENCING OUR PEOPLE, TO PRESENT THE FILMS OF THE ADVISORS LEAVING THE HOTEL. WE CHALLENGE THE NETWORK TO PRESENT THOSE FILMS OF THE ADVISORS LEAVING THE SHERATON, WITH THEIR FACES COVERED AS IF THEY WERE CAR THIEVES. THAT IS THE WAY THE U.S. ADVISERS -- THE RAMBOS, THE SUPERMEN -- LEFT THE SHERATON. THESE RAMBOS ARE NOT GOING TO SAVE ANYONE, AS THEY CANNOT EVEN SAVE THEMSELVES.

TST1-MUC3-0017

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND REPORTS:

1. ON SATURDAY 11 NOVEMBER WE BEGAN THE NATIONAL MILITARY CAMPAIGN CALLED " OUT WITH THE FASCISTS! FEBE ELIZABETH LIVES!" THIS CAMPAIGN IMMERSED THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND AND THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION IN CONFUSION AND INSECURITY SINCE THE BEGINNING; AND IT SUCCESSFULLY CONTINUES IN ITS SECOND DAY OF FIGHTING.

2. THE FMLN FIGHTERS ARE USING ALL THEIR INTELLIGENCE, ENERGY, UNSELFISHNESS, AND PATRIOTISM SO THAT A JUST PEACE IS ACHIEVED IN THE COUNTRY BASED ON AN AUTHENTIC DEMOCRACY DESIGNED TO COUNTER THE GENOCIDAL REPLY THAT THE MILITARY DICTATORSHIP HAS RESPONDED WITH.

3. SALVADORANS WHO HAVE WITHSTOOD A BLOODY MILITARY DICTATORSHIP FOR ALMOST 60 YEARS SEE MORE CLEARLY TODAY THE NEED TO DEVELOP THEIR LEGITIMATE DEFENSE AGAINST THE REPRESSION WHICH HAS BEEN STEPPED UP BY THE POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND MILITARY HOSTILITY OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S ADMINISTRATION; AND THEY UNDERSTAND THE NEED TO SUPPORT AND JOIN THE STRUGGLE FOR OUR COUNTRY'S LIBERTY.

4. WE URGE THE HONEST AND PATRIOTIC MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES TO SERIOUSLY REFLECT ON THE FACT THAT THEY ARE NOT ONLY FACING THE GUERRILLA ARMY OF THE FMLN, BUT A WHOLE SECTOR WHICH CLAIMS ITS RIGHT TO REBEL. WE SPECIFICALLY URGE THE SOLDIERS AND OFFICERS IN THE BATTLEFIELD TO UNDERSTAND THAT OUR STRUGGLE IS NOT BEING PERSONALLY WAGED AGAINST YOU, BUT RATHER AGAINST THE ANTIPOPULAR INTERESTS WHICH ARE BEING DEFENDED BY THE ARMED FORCES UPON ORDERS FROM THE FASCISTS.

5. THE GOVERNMENTS AND PEOPLES OF THE WORLD ARE CLOSELY FOLLOWING THE LATEST EVENTS IN EL SALVADOR AND THEIR CONTRIBUTION WILL BE VALUABLE IN ACHIEVING A NATIONAL CONSENSUS BASED ON DEMOCRACY, A SOLUTION AMONG SALVADORANS, AND NO FOREIGN INTERVENTION. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST HELP ACHIEVE A JUST AND DURABLE PEACE, THUS AVOIDING MORE BLOODSHED.

6. THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND WANTS TO REPORT THE ATROCITIES BEING PERPETRATED AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION BY THE ARMED FORCES WHO ARE INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBING DENSELY POPULATED AREAS IN SAN SALVADOR, AND ISSUING DEATH THREATS AGAINST ALL THE POLITICAL AND SOCIAL GROUPS, THUS PROVING THE REGIME'S WEAKNESS AND SHOWING ITS ANTIPOPULAR AND ANTIPATRIOTIC ESSENCE.

7. WE ALSO URGE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO HELP CREATE SPECIAL ZONES WHERE CHILDREN, THE ELDERLY, AND WOUNDED PEOPLE FROM THE BATTLE ZONES CAN BE EVACUATED.

OUT WITH THE FASCISTS! FEBE ELIZABETH LIVES!

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, COMMANDER FRANCISCO JOVEL, COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, COMMANDER SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO.

EL SALVADOR, 12 NOVEMBER 1989.

TST1-MUC3-0019

SAN SALVADOR, 26 JAN 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [MAURICIO FUNES] [TEXT] AFTER NEARLY A 2-MONTH ABSENCE FROM THE NATIONAL PRESS, MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON HOLDS THE VIEW THAT THE ARMED FORCES SHOULD NOT BE CRITICIZED FOR THE ISOLATED BEHAVIOR OF SOME OF ITS MEMBERS. THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] LEADER IS OF THE OPINION THAT THE ARMED FORCES THEMSELVES WERE THE ONES THAT EXERTED PRESSURE SO THAT THE JESUITS' MURDER CASE COULD BE CLEARED-UP.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON] IT WAS NOT THE INSTITUTION [ARMED FORCES] THAT WAS INVOLVED IN THE PROBLEM. REGRETTABLY SOME OF ITS MEMBERS DID IT AND NOW THE ENTIRE ARMED FORCES ARE UNDER PRESSURE FOR POLITICAL REASONS. HOWEVER, WE MUST REALIZE THAT IT IS THANKS TO THE ARMED FORCES THAT WE HAVE THIS DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, WITH A HOPE THAT OUR COUNTRY DEVELOPS AND RECOVERS. IT IS VERY UNFAIR THAT SOME PEOPLE PASS JUDGMENT OR CRITICIZE WITHOUT REALLY KNOWING HOW HARD IT HAS BEEN ON ALL THE OFFICERS, NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS, AND TROOPS WHO HAVE HAD TO PUT UP WITH THESE ATTACKS IN ADDITION TO THE INTENSE WORK THEY HAVE HAD FOR THE PAST FEW MONTHS. [END RECORDING]

D'AUBUISSON SAID THAT ONCE THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUITS HAS BEEN CLEARED UP, U.S. AUTHORITIES HAVE NO REASON TO QUESTION THE CONTINUATION OF U.S. ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE TO THE COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON] THE JESUITS' CASE WAS A DETERMINING FACTOR. BUT NOW THAT THE CASE HAS BEEN FULLY SOLVED WITH THE HELP OF THE FBI, SCOTLAND YARD, AND INVESTIGATORS FROM OTHER COUNTRIES, THIS IS NO LONGER A PROBLEM, ALTHOUGH PREVIOUSLY IT WAS SERIOUS. I DO NOT BELIEVE THERE CAN BE ANY DOUBT NOW ABOUT RECEIVING THE AID, ESPECIALLY AFTER THE TREMENDOUS OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. FOR ARGUMENT'S SAKE, IF THE SITUATION DID ARISE [WHEREBY AID WAS SUSPENDED], THIS WOULD ONLY FAVOR THE FMLN. I KNOW THE FMLN HAS A WHOLE RANGE OF SUPPORT GROUPS THAT HANDLE DISINFORMATION AND MAKE IT APPEAR AS IF THINGS HERE WERE DISASTROUS. FOR EXAMPLE, INFORMATION ABROAD IS THAT THE AIR FORCE LEVELED ALL THE NEIGHBORHOODS. WE SALVADORANS KNOW THAT THE AIR FORCE WAS EXCESSIVELY CAUTIOUS AND DID AN EXCELLENT JOB REPELLING THIS ATTACK WITH A MINIMUM OF CIVILIANS WOUNDED. FOR THAT MATTER, IF WE ARE GOING TO COMPARE THINGS, U.S. MILITARY OPERATIONS IN PANAMA WERE MORE CLUMSY -- THERE THEY SET A WHOLE NEIGHBORHOOD ON FIRE. [END RECORDING]

THE ARENA LEADER ALSO DENIED THAT THERE WERE DIFFERENCES BETWEEN PRESIDENT CRISTIANI AND HIMSELF. ACCORDING TO INTERNATIONAL PRESS AGENCIES, THE DECISION OF THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT TO PROSECUTE THE MILITARY MEN INVOLVED IN THE JESUITS' MURDER CAUSED DIVISION WITHIN THE PARTY. D'AUBUISSON DENIED THIS WAS TRUE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON] NOT IN THE LEAST. THERE HAVE NEVER BEEN ANY DIFFERENCES WITH PRESIDENT CRISTIANI. ON THE CONTRARY, WE ARE VERY CLOSE AND GRATEFUL FOR THE GREAT EFFORT, WORK, AND THE MAGNIFICENT JOB PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IS DOING. THIS IS REASON FOR PRIDE NOT ONLY AMONG FRIENDS OF PRESIDENT CRISTIANI BUT FOR THE PARTY AND FRIENDS OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. [END RECORDING]

IN COMMENTING ON THE DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN, D'AUBUISSON SUPPORTED PRESIDENT CRITIANI'S INITIATIVE OF ENGAGING THE ASSISTANCE OF THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON] I DO NOT THINK HE HAS THE TIME TO ACT AS MEDIATOR; HOWEVER, HE COULD ACT AS A GUARANTOR, RECEIVING RESULTS OF THESE TALKS AND ENSURING COMPLIANCE WITH THE COMMITMENTS MADE. [END RECORDING]

MAJ ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON, CURRENTLY AN ARENA DEPUTY, SAID THAT THIS YEAR HE WILL DEDICATE HIS TIME TO EXPAND AND REORGANIZE THE PARTY TO GET READY FOR THE 1991 MUNICIPAL AND PARLIAMENTARY ELECTIONS. HE WILL MOST LIKELY NOT BE AN ARENA DEPUTY IN THE NEXT LEGISLATIVE PERIOD, BECAUSE HE, ALONG WITH OTHER FORMER LEGISLATORS, WILL CONCENTRATE THEIR POLITICAL ACTIVITIES ON THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT.

TST1-MUC3-0020

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES HAVE EVERYTHING UNDER CONTROL. WE HAVE TOURED THE ENTIRE AREA; SOME HAVE ELECTRICITY, AND OTHERS DO NOT. THE REBELS HAVE TRIED TO CREATE A SITUATION. HOWEVER, NOTHING HAS HAPPENED BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES CONTROL EVERYTHING.

THIS IS A REPORT FROM THE ENTIRE AREA WHERE THERE HAS BEEN AN ATTEMPT TO CREATE A SITUATION OF HARASSMENT, AND THAT IS WHAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE REPORTING TONIGHT. IN A CERTAIN SECTOR, IN THE VICINITY OF SANTA TECLA OR, [CHANGES THOUGHT] THE ENTIRE SITUATION THAT IS BEING EXPERIENCED TONIGHT. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE CAN REST ASSURED THAT THE ARMED FORCES CONTROL EVERYTHING; THERE ARE ONLY SOME BOMBINGS AND SHOOTINGS THAT WILL NOT LEAD TO ANYTHING. THIS IS ONLY BEING DONE TO MAKE THE PEOPLE FEEL AS IF THERE WERE SITUATIONS THAT ARE NOT DIFFERENT AT ALL, BECAUSE THEY WILL NOT LEAD TO ANYTHING, THE SITUATION, RIGHT? [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

THAT IS THE REPORT WE CAN GIVE YOU NOW, WHILE WE ARE EXPERIENCING THE POWER OUTTAGE, AND THE REBLS ARE BRINGING EVERYTHING TO A STANDSTILL, BUT THIS WILL NOT LEAD TO ANYTHING THAT WOULD MAKE THE PEOPLE FEEL THAT THERE IS AN ALARMING SITUATION.

I AM REPORTING LIVE FROM THE AREA OF THE CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY AND JARDINES LA SULTANA, WHERE THERE IS NO ELECTRICITY AT PRESENT. WE HAVE MADE A GREAT EFFORT TO CONTACT YOU BY TELEPHONE AS WE KNOW THIS IS THE STATION THAT IS HEARD THROUGHOUT EL SALVADOR AND OUTSIDE OUR COUNTRY.

THAT IS THE SITUATION AT PRESENT. EVERYTHING IS UNDER CONTROL. THERE ARE NO PROBLEMS. IT IS JUST A HARASSMENT BY THE REBELS WHO ARE TRYING TO SCARE PEOPLE. EVERYTHING IS UNDER CONTROL.

TST1-MUC3-0021

SAN SALVADOR, 8 AUG 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] FMLN COMMUNIQUE TO ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE: CONCERNING THE TELA AGREEMENTS, THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND HEREBY STATES THE FOLLOWING:

1. THESE AGREEMENTS ARE A VICTORY FOR THE REVOLUTIONARY, PROGRESSIVE, INDEPENDENT, AND DEMOCRATIC FORCES OF THE REGION, AND AS SUCH, WE STRONGLY PRAISE THEM.

2. THESE AGREEMENTS SEAL THE POLITICAL DEATH OF THE CONTRAS AND DECLARE TO THE WORLD THE FAILURE OF THE POLICY OF AGGRESSION THAT THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION INITIATED AND CARRIED OUT AGAINST THE PEOPLE OF CENTRAL AMERICA.

3. ALTHOUGH THE GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES WERE PREPARED TO PUT FORWARD A THEORY OF PARALLELS, ALL OF THEIR ALLEGED EVIDENCE WAS DERIDED AND DISCARDED.

4. CRISTIANI HAS SIGNED OFF ON THE CONTRAS' DEATH AND ACKNOWLEDGED BEFORE THE ENTIRE WORLD THAT THE FMLN IS A FORCE WITH WHICH IT MUST TALK AND NEGOTIATE. HE WENT TO TELA WITH A DIALOGUE PLAN TO COVER UP THE WAR, BUT HE WAS FORCED, UNDER THE AGREEMENTS, TO NEGOTIATE FOR PEACE WITH THE FMLN. CRISTIANI'S DIALOGUE COMMISSION, IN FACT, HAS BEEN DEMOBILIZED.

5. CRISTIANI WAS FORCED TO SIGN A PLEDGE FOR DEMOCRATIZATION WHEN HIS PLANS WAS TO FASCISTIZE EL SALVADOR.

6. THE FMLN REAFFIRMS ITS RESOLVE TO CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THE EFFORTS OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES, THE SAN SALVADOR ARCHBISHOPRIC, AND OTHER SOCIAL FORCES TO ESTABLISH A DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE GOVERNMENT. IT IS CLEAR THAT THE CONTRAS WERE A MERCENARY FORCE MAINTAINED BY THE UNITED STATES, WHICH ATTACKED NICARAGUA FROM HONDURAS, AND WHICH SHOULD AND COULD BE DEMOBILIZED. IT IS CLEAR THAT THE FMLN IS A NATIONAL FORCE THAT HAS REASONS FOR BEING AT WAR, AND WITH WHICH PEACE MUST BE NEGOTIATED. NO ONE CAN DEMOBILIZE THE FMLN BECAUSE IT IS WITHIN THE COUNTRY AND IS A LEGITIMATE NATIONAL FORCE.

THE FMLN CALLS ON ALL FELLOW PATRIOTS WHO HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE IN HONDURAS, NICARAGUA, COSTA RICA, GUATEMALA, AND THE REST OF THE WORLD TO RETURN TO THE FATHERLAND. THEY ARE PROTECTED BY THE TELA AGREEMENTS. WE ASK ALL SALVADORANS TO DEMAND OF CRISTIANI THAT, WITHOUT FURTHER STRATAGEMS, HE CARRY OUT A SERIOUS NEGOTIATION; FULFILL HIS PLEDGE TO DEMOCRATIZE THE COUNTRY; STOP THE REPRESSION, KIDNAPPING, AND TORTURE; RELEASE ALL POLITICAL PRISONERS; GUARANTEE FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION; RESPECT REFORM; AND ABOLISH THE ECONOMIC MEASURES THAT ARE DEEPENING THE WAR.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[DATED] 7 AUGUST 1989

TST1-MUC3-0023

BOGOTA, 27 APR 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE MEDIA CAN MAKE A SIGNIFICANT CONTRIBUTION TOWARD PEACE AND DEMOCRACY IF, ON THEIR OWN INITIATIVE, THEY LAUNCH A GREAT CIVIC CAMPAIGN TO VIGOROUSLY STIMULATE THE CITIZENS TO PARTICIPATE IN THE COMING ELECTIONS.

FELLOW CITIZENS, I KNOW THAT YOU ARE ASKING YOURSELVES WHAT CAN BE DONE UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES. ABOVE ALL, DO NOT PLAY UP TO TERRORISM. THE INTERESTS OF THE FATHERLAND ARE ABOVE ALL INDIVIDUAL OR GROUP INTERESTS, AS IS THE DEFENSE OF OUR DEMOCRACY, WHICH WE HAVE ALL BEEN BUILDING TOGETHER FOR MORE THAN A CENTURY. THIS CANNOT BE THE TIME OF OPPORTUNISM. THIS IS THE HOUR OF SOLIDARITY WITH THE COUNTRY, ITS PEOPLE, AND ITS INSTITUTIONS. THE EFFECTIVENESS OF THESE MEASURES AND THE ACTIONS OF THE PUBLIC FORCE DEPEND, FIRST OF ALL, ON THE SOLIDARITY OF THE CITIZENS. THE RESULTS WILL BE AS ENCOURAGING AND AS FAVORABLE AS THE COOPERATION OF THE CITIZENS. TO REGAIN TRANQUILITY IS NOT THE EXCLUSIVE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE ARMED FORCES OR THE STATE. IT IS A TASK IN WHICH EACH OF US HAS SOMETHING TO CONTRIBUTE.

COLOMBIA HAS SUCCESSFULLY OVERCOME EVEN MORE DIFFICULT MOMENTS. IT HAS FACED DECISIVELY AND EMERGED VICTORIOUSLY FROM EVEN MORE UNCERTAIN SITUATIONS. THAT PAST HAS CREATED SOLID INSTITUTIONS. FOR THIS REASON, I AM SURE THAT DEMOCRACY WILL TRIUMPH AND THAT THOSE WHO COMMIT VIOLENCE, REGARDLESS OF WHO THEY MAY BE, WILL BE PUNISHED. I AM SURE THAT WE WILL CONTINUE TO PROGRESS ALONG THE PATH OF PEACE, TOLERANCE, AND RESPECT FOR LIFE AND HUMAN DIGNITY. GOOD NIGHT.

TST1-MUC3-0024

BOGOTA, 8 DEC 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE CAR BOMB ATTACK ON 6 DECEMBER WHICH DESTROYED THE BUILDING THAT HOUSES THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS, SECRET POLICE) HAD BEEN PLANNED SINCE LAST SEPTEMBER, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL DISCLOSURES.

A POLICE SPOKESPERSON CONFIRMED TODAY THAT THE BUS USED IN THE TERRORIST ACTION WAS BOUGHT BY A MAN WHO IS A NATIVE OF MEDELLIN. HE USED FALSE DOCUMENTS TO BUY THE CAR FROM A SCHOOL PROPRIETOR IN BOGOTA.

ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES, THE BUYER, WHO IS A MEMBER OF THE SINISTER MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS INSTRUCTED BY TERRORISTS ABROAD TO EXPLODE 500 KG OF DYNAMITE GEL IN FRONT OF THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE COUNTRY'S PRINCIPAL SECURITY ORGANIZATION.

DAS DIRECTOR BRIGADIER GENERAL MIGUEL MAZA MARQUEZ SAID ON 7 DECEMBER THAT A MEMBER OF THE SEPARATIST ETA [BASQUE FATHERLAND AND LIBERTY] GROUP DIRECTED THE OPERATION.

MAZA MARQUEZ ALSO SAID THAT PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE WORLD'S BIGGEST DRUG TRAFFICKERS, "ARE BEHIND THIS CRIMINAL ATTACK."

"THE MEDELLIN CARTEL PLANNED THE ATTACK SINCE SEPTEMBER, AFTER ANOTHER CAR BOMB ATTEMPT TO ASSASSINATE MAZA MARQUEZ WAS FOILED LAST MAY," THE POLICE SPOKESPERSON STATED.

MEANWHILE, THREE PERSONS SUSPECTED OF PARTICIPATING IN THE ATTACK WERE RELEASED ON 7 DECEMBER, AFTER BEING FOUND INNOCENT. TWO OTHER PERSONS ARE BEING HELD BY THE POLICE AND ARE UNDERGOING INTENSE QUESTIONING.

THE AUTHORITIES ALSO CONFIRMED THAT THE NUMBER OF VICTIMS IS 59 AND NOT 62, AS WAS REPORTED OFFICIALLY ON 7 DECEMBER.

CIVIL DEFENSE AND RED CROSS CREWS, AS WELL AS ARMED FORCES UNITS, ARE REMOVING THE RUBBLE FROM A 2-KM-PERIMETER, FEARING THAT PEOPLE MAY BE PERSONS TRAPPED BENEATH TONS OF IRON AND CEMENT.

TST1-MUC3-0026

BOGOTA, 24 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PRESENCE OF BRITISH AND ISRAELI MERCENARIES, PAID BY COLOMBIAN EXTREME RIGHT-WING GROUPS AND DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WAS CONFIRMED TODAY BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS), COLOMBIA'S SECRET POLICE.

THE DAS SENT A CONFIDENTIAL REPORT TO COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO WHICH WAS PUBLISHED TODAY BY THE LIBERAL NEWSPAPER EL TIEMPO. THE REPORT CONFIRMS THAT THERE IS A COLLABERATION BETWEEN DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND EXTREME RIGHT-WING GROUPS, AND THE PRESENCE OF FOREIGN MERCENARIES IN COLOMBIA -- HIRED BY THE EXTREME RIGHT-WING DRUG-TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS.

THE OFFICIAL ORGANIZATION ASSERTS THAT THE RECENTLY CREATED EXTREME RIGHTIST MOVEMENT OF NATIONAL RESTORATION (MORENA) "MUST BE IDENTIFIED AS THE CULMINATION OF A SYMBIOSIS BETWEEN DRUG TRAFFICKERS, SELF-DEFENSE GROUPS, GROUPS OF HIRED GUNMEN TRAINED BY FOREIGN MERCENARIES, AND AGRARIAN BUSINESSMEN WHO ARE TIRED OF THE GUERRILLA GROUPS' CONSTANT HARASSMENT."

THE REPORT INDICATES THAT BRITISH AND ISRAELI MERCENARIES IDENTIFIED AS JOHN OWEN, DAVE TOMKINS, R. PAXTON, P. GLASGOW, A. DEWER, AND P. ATHERTON ENTERED COLOMBIA THROUGH ELDORADO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT IN JULY, BUT THE INFORMATION DOES NOT GIVE THEIR INDIVIDUAL NATIONALITIES.

THE DAS ADDS THAT DEAN SHELLEY, PETER MCALEESE, ALEX LENOX, AND ANDRES GIBSON ENTERED THE COUNTRY IN PREVIOUSLY AND SETTLED IN THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS EXTREME RIGHT-WING GROUPS' MILITARY TRAINING CAMPS IN PUERTO BOYACA, MIDDLE MAGDALENA REGION (CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY), LA AZULITA (SOUTHERN PUTUMAYO), PUERTO LOPEZ (META DEPARTMENT), AND EL RECREO (CAQUETA DEPARTMENT) ON THE NORTHEASTERN FLATLANDS.

RADIO STATIONS' REPORTS ADDED THAT COLONEL YAIR KLEIN HAS BEEN IDENTIFIED AMONG THE ISRAELI MERCENARIES BY THE SECRET SERVICES OF HIS COUNTRY. KLEIN WAS COMMANDER OF A PARATROOPERS' UNIT IN 1983 AND APPARENTLY HAS A PRIVATE SECURITY AGENCY IN ISRAEL.

ABRAHAM TZADAKA AND JACOBO BRINE WERE ALSO IDENTIFIED BY THEIR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN.

ON A NATIONAL NEWSCAST BROADCAST SEVERAL WEEKS AGO A VIDEO WHICH SHOWS THE ISRAELI MERCENARIES WEARING BLUE UNIFORMS DURING WAR MANEUVERS WITH THE DRUG-TRAFFICKERS FAR RIGHT-WING GROUPS' PRIVATE ARMY. THE SCENES WERE REPRODUCED BY THE NBC TELEVISION NETWORK IN THE UNITED STATES.

PREVIOUS REPORTS FROM THE DAS, REVEALED IN COLOMBIA, INDICATE THAT THE COLOMBIANS TRAINED BY THE MERCENARIES INCLUDE PERSONS LINKED WITH THE SELF-DEFENSE GROUPS IN THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA REGION AND THE RECENTLY CREATED MORENA.

THE FIRST PERSONS TO NOTIFY THE PROSECUTOR GENERAL OF THE NATION, THE HIGHEST AUTHORITY, ABOUT THE PRESENCE OF FOREIGN MERCENARIES AMONG THE DRUG-TRAFFICKERS FAR RIGHT-WING ARMED GROUPS WERE DESERTERS FROM THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA SELF-DEFENSE GROUPS -- IDENTIFIED AS JESUS ALBERTO MOLINA URREA, RICAURTE DUQUE ARBOLEDA, AND VICTOR ARBOLEDA DUQUE.

ACCORDING TO THE DESERTERS' DECLARATIONS, THE ISRAELI MERCENARIES CANNOT SPEAK SPANISH AND THEY FREQUENTLY MET WITH GONZALO DE JESUS PEREZ, HENRY PEREZ, AND MARCELO PEREZ.

ACCORDING TO THE DAS REPORT REVEALED TODAY, "THE PEREZES," ARE IMPORTANT MEMBERS OF THE ASSOCIATION OF MIDDLE MAGDALENA CATTLEMEN (ACDEGAM), THE SELF-DEFENSE GROUPS, AND MORENA; AND THE AUTHORITIES CHARGE THEM WITH THE MASS MURDERS OF PEASANTS IN URABA, LOCATED IN THE COUNTRY'S NORTHWESTERN AREA.

TST1-MUC3-0029

BEIJING (PRC), 30 NOV 89 (XINHUA DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ON 30 NOVEMBER WHEN U.S. PRESIDENT BUSH SET FORTH TO MALTA TO MEET WITH SOVIET LEADER GORBACHEV, A REPORT FROM ANGOLA SAID THAT A CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY [CIA] AIRPLANE ON A CLANDESTINE MISSION OF DELIVERING WEAPONS TO THE ANTIGOVERNMENT NATIONAL UNION FOR THE TOTAL INDEPENDENCE OF ANGOLA (UNITA) CRASHED IN SOUTHERN ANGOLA ON 27 NOVEMBER AND THAT THE FOUR AMERICANS ON THE PLANE WERE KILLED. TODAY BOTH THE U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT AND THE DEFENSE DEPARTMENT CONFIRMED THE CRASH, BUT THEY REFUSED TO COMMENT ON WHETHER THE AMERICANS WHO WERE KILLED WERE CIA OFFICIALS, OR ON THE NATURE OF THE PLANE'S MISSION. THIS IS IN SHARP CONTRAST TO THE RESPONSE THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT MADE A FEW DAYS AGO IN CONNECTION WITH A PLANE CRASH IN EL SALVADOR.

AFTER A PLANE CARRYING WEAPONS TO THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS CRASHED ON 25 NOVEMBER, U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE BAKER PROMPTLY INSTRUCTED THE UNDERSECRETARY OF STATE ON THAT SAME EVENING TO SUMMON THE SOVIET AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED STATES TO PROTEST TO THE SOVIET UNION FOR UNDERMINING PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA AND "FAILING TO EXERCISE ITS INFLUENCE" TO STOP CUBA AND NICARAGUA FROM DELIVERING WEAPONS TO THE GUERRILLAS IN EL SALVADOR. IN THIS CONNECTION, A U.S. GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL POINTED OUT THAT PRESIDENT BUSH WOULD PRESENT THE CENTRAL AMERICA ISSUE AS AN IMPORTANT ISSUE WHILE DISCUSSING PROBLEMS OF REGIONAL CONFLICTS WITH SOVIET LEADERS DURING THEIR MEDITERRANEAN MEETING. SOME OFFICIALS EVEN SAID THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICA ISSUE IS THE "PRINCIPAL OBSTACLE" TO THE IMPROVEMENT OF U.S.-SOVIET RELATIONS, AND THAT ONLY WHEN THE USSR MAKES FURTHER CONCESSIONS ON THE CENTRAL AMERICA ISSUE WILL IT BE POSSIBLE FOR THE UNITED STATES TO PROVIDE ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE TO THE SOVIET UNION.

IN A CEASEFIRE ACCORD SIGNED ON 24 JUNE THIS YEAR, UNITA AND THE ANGOLAN GOVERNMENT AGREED TO SEEK WAYS AND MEANS TO CONCLUDE THE CIVIL WAR THAT HAD GONE ON FOR 14 YEARS. HOWEVER, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT KEEPS SUPPLYING WEAPONS TO UNITA. ACCORDING TO U.S. NEWSPAPERS, EVER SINCE THE SOUTH AFRICAN AUTHORITIES STOPPED SUPPLYING WEAPONS TO UNITA LAST APRIL, THE UNITED STATES HAS BECOME UNITA'S MAIN WEAPON SUPPLIER. THE SECRET THAT THE UNITED STATES' MILITARY ASSISTANCE TO UNITA INCREASED FROM $15 MILLION TO $50 MILLION THIS YEAR WAS REVEALED AFTER THE CRASH OF THE CIA'S WEAPON CARRIER. NOW, EVEN THE U.S. PRESS HAS ASKED THIS QUESTION: COULD IT PREVENT PRESIDENT BUSH FROM PRESENTING HIS CRITICISM WHEN PROBLEMS OF REGIONAL CONFLICTS ARE DISCUSSED WHEN HE MEETS THE SOVIET LEADER? A U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT OFFICIAL SAID: "NOT AT ALL," "WE WILL NOT PLACE (THE TWO) ON A PAR." A STATE DEPARTMENT OFFICIAL ALSO SAID THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WILL CONTINUE TO PROVIDE "APPROPRIATE AND EFFECTIVE ASSISTANCE" TO UNITA IN THE FUTURE.

TST1-MUC3-0030

NO CITY (PERU), 16 SEP 89 -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [GARCIA] AS A LATIN AMERICAN PRESIDENT, I FEEL A LITTLE BIT UNCOMFORTABLE OVER THE STATEMENT THAT THE NORTH AMERICANS ARE VICTIMS OF THE DRUGS PRODUCED IN LATIN AMERICA AND THAT COLOMBIA, PERU, AND BOLIVIA ARE TO BLAME FOR PRODUCING THE DRUGS; LET'S CALL THOSE COUNTRIES TO TALK WITH THEM. THAT SEEMS TO ME A VERY ETHNOCENTRIC VISION; IT LOOKS AT THIS MATTER FROM ONLY ONE SIDE. OUR PEASANTS ARE POOR PEOPLE WHO PRODUCE WHATEVER IS MOST PROFITABLE, AND COCA CULTIVATION HAPPENS TO BE MOST PROFITABLE FOR THEM. THIS IS SO, SPEAKING COLDLY, HONESTLY, AND SINCERELY. AS PRESIDENT OF PERU I HAVE TO POINT OUT THAT MY PEOPLE, THE HUALLAGE REGION PEASANTS, CANNOT BE CONSIDERED AS CRIMINALS OR AS PEOPLE WHO MUST BE JAILED FOR PRODUCING COCA LEAVES.

WE HAVE EXCHANGED THESE VIEWS WITH PRESIDENT BARCO, AND WE REACHED THESE CONCLUSIONS. WE MUST ALSO NOTE THAT THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HANDLED WITH A GREAT DEAL OF PUBLICITY. AFTER THE DEATH OF CARLOS GALAN, A GREAT COLOMBIAN LEADER, THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT LAUNCHED AN OFFENSIVE INTENDED TO FIND OUT WHETHER THE DRUG TRAFFICKING BANDS WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR HIS ASSASSINATION, AND THE U.S. GOVERNMENT THEN EXTENDED SOME ASSISTANCE. THIS ASSISTANCE HAS BEEN PRESENT TO THE WORLD AS THOUGH THE UNITED STATES HAD SENT AN ENORMOUS QUANTITY OF AIRCRAFT, HUNDREDS OF HELICOPTERS, AND THOUSANDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS TO COLOMBIA. AS I WAS ABLE TO SEE IN BOGOTA, ONLY HELICOPTERS, SOME OF WHICH HAD BEEN PURCHASED EARLIER BY THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT, WERE SENT. I WAS ALSO INFORMED THAT SOME OF THOSE HELICOPTERS HAD BEEN USED PREVIOUSLY IN PERU.

I HAVE SAID THAT, IF THERE IS THAT MUCH CONVICTION, I SUPPORT PRESIDENT BUSH FOR DEFENDING U.S. SOCIETY. IF HE HAS THAT MUCH CONVICTION, IT IS HARD TO BELIEVE THAT LESS THAN ONE THOUSANDTH OF WHAT IS SPENT IN ARMS AND MILITARY EXPENDITURES SHOULD BE ALLOCATED TO REPLACE COCA PLANTATIONS AND TO IMPROVE THE GENERAL SITUATION IN LATIN AMERICA. WE HAVE TALKED WITH PRESIDENT BARCO, AND I WILL TALK WITH PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA TO SEE HOW WE CAN EXCHANGE OPINIONS. THEN, AS PRESIDENT BUSH SAID, A MEETING OF PRESIDENTS WILL BE WELCOME. BUT THE MEETING SHOULD ALSO BE ATTENDED BY EUROPE, WHICH HAS A FUNDAMENTAL INTEREST IN THE FUTURE.

[CORRESPONDENT] WOULD THE IDEA BE TO HOLD A MEETING IN THE NEAR FUTURE OF PERU, COLOMBIA, AND BOLIVIA WITH PRESIDENT BUSH AND A REPRESENTATIVE OF THE EEC?

[GARCIA] YES, BECAUSE DRUG TRAFFICKING IS A GROWING PROBLEM. CARTELS HAVE SPROUTED IN COLOMBIA -- MONOPOLIES THAT TRY TO ELECT DEPUTIES AND SENATORS TO INFLUENCE THE GOVERNMENT. THOSE MONOPOLIES MIGHT EXTEND THEIR OPERATIONS TO OUR COUNTRIES IF WE DO NOT STOP THIS GROWING PROBLEM. THE SITUATION CAN BECOME WORSE IN BOLIVIA, WHERE IT WAS SAID THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAD AN INFLUENCE ON A DICTATORIAL MILITARY REGIME. IT IS NOT JUST A MATTER OF PROTECTING THE MORALITY OF HUMANITY; IT IS NOT JUST A MATTER OF DEFENDING THE UNITED STATES, WHICH HAS A PRIMARY ROLE IN WORLD LEADERSHIP; IT IS ESSENTIALLY A MATTER OF DEFENDING OUR DEMOCRACY -- THE LEGITIMACY AND CLEANLINESS OF OUR SOCIAL LIFE. I HOPE THAT WE CAN HAVE A MEETING OF THE THREE PRESIDENTS FIRST, SO THAT WE CAN LET THE U.S. PRESIDENT KNOW OUR VIEWS ON THE OVERALL PROBLEM.

[CORRESPONDENT] WILL YOU PROPOSE THAT MEETING, MR PRESIDENT?

[GARCIA] I DON'T WANT TO ASSUME A LEADING ROLE. THE IDEA EMERGED IN A CONVERSATION WITH PRESIDENT BARCO, AND I WILL TALK LATER WITH PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA.

[CORRESPONDENT] A MEETING BETWEEN YOU AND PRESIDENT BUSH LATE THIS MONTH HAS BEEN MENTIONED. IS THIS TRUE, MR PRESIDENT?

[GARCIA] NO, I BELIEVE THAT HAS BEEN MERE SPECULATION IN THE PRESS. FOR THE TIME BEING I HAVE DISCARDED THE IDEA OF MAKING ANOTHER TRIP ABROAD. I DO NOT SEE THE CONCRETE POSSIBILITY OF MEETING WITH PRESIDENT BUSH, ALTHOUGH I HOPE WE CAN MEET SOMETIME BEFORE 28 JULY 1990.

[CORRESPONDENT] CHANGING THE SUBJECT, MR PRESIDENT -- MUCH HAS BEEN SAID IN RECENT DAYS ABOUT THE POSSIBLE OR PROBABLE EXPULSION OF PERU FROM THE IMF. WHAT IS THE TRUTH ABOUT THIS, AND WHAT WOULD EXPULSION MEAN?

[GARCIA] WELL, FIRST, IT IS POLITICALLY IMPOSSIBLE FOR PERU TO BE EXPELLED FROM THE IMF. SECOND, THERE IS MISINFORMATION AND ALARMISM REGARDING THE MATTER. WHAT IS THE IMF? IT IS SOME SORT OF CREDITOR BANK CREATED IN 1946 THAT LENDS MONEY TO COUNTRIES WITH BALANCE-OF-PAYMENTS PROBLEMS; THAT IS, WITH PROBLEMS WITH THEIR FOREIGN RESERVES LEVELS. WHEN A COUNTRY HAS NO RESERVES OR ONLY $100 MILLION IN RESERVES, IT CAN APPLY FOR A CREDIT FROM THE IMF TO PAY FOR IMPORTS OR OVERDUE DEBTS. THIS IS THE IMF, AN ORGANIZATION CREATED TO FACILITATE THE FLOW OF INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL RESOURCES. AN IMF CREDIT IS DEPENDENT ON SIGNING A LETTER OF INTENT OR AN ADJUSTMENT PROGRAM. ADJUSTMENT MEANS REDUCING THE COUNTRY'S INTERNAL CONSUMPTION SO AS TO SPARE THE COUNTRY'S RESERVES IN ORDER TO MEET DEBT OBLIGATIONS. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0032

BUENOS AIRES, 18 MAY 90 (NA) -- [TEXT] NEXT JUNE AN ENTIRE U.S. ARMY COMPANY WILL CARRY OUT JOINT MANEUVERS WITH ARGENTINE TROOPS IN A PROVINCE OF THE LITTORAL REGION. THE MANEUVERS, DESIGNED TO TEACH THE ARGENTINE OFFICERS THE LATEST TECHNIQUES AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, FALL WITHIN THE COMPREHENSIVE MILITARY EXCHANGE PLAN. GENERAL MAXWELL THURMAN'S VISIT IS ALSO PART OF THE AFOREMENTIONED PLAN.

ACCORDING TO RELIABLE SOURCES, THE RECENT VISIT FROM THE UNITED STATES OF 10 LIEUTENANT COLONELS, THREE COLONELS, AND EIGHT CIVILIAN EXPERTS IN DEFENSE STRATEGY, REPRESENT AN IMPORTANT STEP IN THE RENEWED U.S.-ARGENTINE MILITARY RELATIONSHIP.

THE SAME SOURCES HAVE STATED THAT THE GRADUAL AND RESTRICTED PARTICIPATION OF THE ARMY IN MANEUVERS DESIGNED TO PRACTICE FIGHTING AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING HAS BEEN AUTHORIZED BY THE DEFENSE MINISTRY AND EVEN BY THE PRESIDENT.

THE MILITARY GROUP THAT ARRIVED IN ARGENTINA ON 6 MAY CARRIED OUT WAR GAMES AT THE WAR SCHOOL AND THE CAMPO DE MAYO MILITARY SCHOOL AND, LATER ON, CARRIED OUT FIELD MANEUVERS. OTHER FORCES PARTICIPATED IN THE THREE-DAY MANEUVERS THAT WERE CARRIED OUT ON AN ISLAND IN THE RIVER PLATE DELTA. ACCORDING TO A WITNESS, THE MANEUVERS CONSISTED OF "RAIDS" INCLUDING "SURPRISE" SITUATIONS THAT FORCED THE U.S. TROOPS TO ENDURE BAD WEATHER AND BAD TERRAIN.

ACCORDING TO THE FINAL EVALUATION, THE MANEUVERS WERE REGARDED AS "SATISFACTORY AND SUCCESSFUL". ACCORDING TO THE PROGRAM, A COMPLETE U.S. COMPANY THAT WILL TRAIN WITH ARGENTINE TROOPS IN A PROVINCE OF THE LITTORAL REGION IS SCHEDULED TO ARRIVE IN JUNE.

FOREIGN MINISTRY SOURCES CONFIRMED THE EXISTENCE OF EXCHANGE PLANS BUT STATED THAT GENERAL THURMAN HAD PROPOSED TO THE CHIEFS OF STAFF THE POSSIBILITY OF CARRYING OUT JOINT MANEUVERS TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING DURING A LUNCHEON.

THE SOURCES STATED THAT THE CHIEFS OF STAFF HAVE MADE SOME OBJECTIONS TO THE PROPOSAL AND DID NOT REACH ANY AGREEMENT. HOWEVER, SOURCES THAT PARTICIPATED IN THE RECENT MANEUVERS ON THE ISLAND HAD A DIFFERENT OPINION AND RATIFIED THAT ANOTHER MANEUVER WOULD BE HELD IN A PROVINCE OF THE LITTORAL IN JUNE.

ANYHOW, THE STATEMENT OF THE FOREIGN MINISTRY SPOKESMAN FALLS WITHIN THE DIPLOMATIC POLICY THAT MAY PARTLY DIFFER WITH THE MILITARY AND DEFENSE POLICIES, AS WAS POINTED OUT BY A SECTOR OF THE MEDIA YESTERDAY.

MOREOVER, GENERAL THURMAN WILL REMAIN IN SAN CARLOS DE BARILOCHE UNTIL SATURDAY, 19 MAY, AND THAT SAME DAY WILL FLY TO THE IGUAZU FALLS FROM WHERE HE WILL RETURN TO HIS MILITARY BASE IN PANAMA.

THE ONLY PURPOSE OF GENERAL THURMAN'S VISIT WAS TO OFFER THE DEFENSE MINISTRY ALL THE TECHNOLOGY, KNOW HOW, AND WEAPONS FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING WHICH, IN MANY CASES TURNS INTO NARCOTERRORISM, IN OTHER WORDS, THE USE OF DRUG TRAFFICKING TO FINANCE THE PURCHASE OF WEAPONS AND TERRORIST ACTIONS. THURMAN'S VISIT, WHICH TOOK THE UNITED STATES A WHOLE YEAR TO ARRANGE, WAS PREVIOUSLY APPROVED BY THE U.S. SENATE.

WITHIN THE SAME FRAMEWORK, THE BOLIVIAN POLICE HAVE JUST RECEIVED WEAPONS AND OTHER EQUIPMENT AMOUNTING TO $50 MILLION, WHICH IS ENOUGH TO EQUIP TWO COMPLETE BATTALIONS IN CHARGE OF FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

THEREFORE, THE ARGENTINE GOVERNMENT'S DECISION TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING LAUNCHED BY THE UNITED STATES IS PART OF A COMPREHENSIVE STRATEGY OF THE SOUTHERN CONE OF WHICH ARGENTINA -- ACCORDING TO EXPERTS -- MUST PARTICIPATE OUT OF FEAR OF A GROWING ISOLATION.

IT IS QUITE LIKELY THAT THE RESTRICTED AND GRADUAL -- BY NO MEANS MASSIVE -- PARTICIPATION OF THE ARMY AND PROBABLY THE NAVY IN MANEUVERS FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING MAY BE THE KEY THAT WILL FINALLY ALLOW THE ARMED FORCES TO ACQUIRE THE WAR MATERIEL, SPARE PARTS AND OTHER ELEMENTS IT NEEDS.

THE ANALYSTS HAVE RECALLED THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S DETERMINATION TO FIGHT CORRUPTION -- A PROBLEM THAT ALSO WORRIES PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM AND VICE PRESIDENT EDUARDO DUHALDE -- FALLS WITHIN THE SAME FRAMEWORK BECAUSE, IN THE EXPERTS' OPINION, IT IS THE EQUIVALENT TO DRUG TRAFFICKING.

HIGHLY RELIABLE SOURCES HAVE RECALLED THAT 30 DAYS AGO PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH SENT PRESIDENT MENEM TWO VOLUMES OF A U.S. EDITION ON TECHNIQUES TO FIGHT CORRUPTION.

TST1-MUC3-0033

BOGOTA, 9 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] THE PEACE PROCESS WITH M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] THAT WAS INTERRUPTED DUE TO THE MURDER OF TWO MEMBERS OF THAT SUBVERSIVE ORGANIZATION -- NOW OBSERVING A TRUCE -- WAS RESTORED FOLLOWING A VISIT BY PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER RAFAEL PARDO TO THE M-19 CAMP IN SANTO DOMINGO, CAUCA DEPARTMENT. OUR CORRESPONDENT MARIA ALEJANDRA GONZALEZ WAS THERE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GONZALEZ] THE PEACE PROCESS BETWEEN M-19 AND THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT WAS SERIOUSLY JEOPARDIZED THIS WEEK DUE TO THE MURDER OF TWO MEMBERS OF THAT GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION, WHICH OCCURRED AT THE BORDER BETWEEN CAUCA AND VALLE DEL CAUCA DEPARTMENTS. CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ EXPRESSED HIS CONCERN OVER THE SITUATION.

[PIZARRO] WE ARE LIVING A SLOW MOTION PEACE PROCESS. WE NEED A PEACE PROCESS THROUGH WHICH COLOMBIANS CAN FEEL THAT PEACE HAS ARRIVED, INSTEAD OF A PROCESS THAT IS SIMPLY A PERMANENT AND ENDLESS ACCOUNT OF PEACE TRAGEDIES.

[GONZALEZ] OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS, PRESIDENTIAL PEACE ADVISER RAFAEL PARDO AND DEPUTY GOVERNMENT MINISTER JOSE NOE RIOS MET WITH MEMBERS OF THE M-19 COMMAND. THE PARTICIPANTS REAFFIRMED THEIR DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE WITH THE PEACE EFFORTS.

A FORUM FOR LIFE, DEMOCRACY, AND PROGRESS WILL BE HELD IN SANTO DOMINGO THIS WEEKEND, WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF POLITICAL LEADERS AND REPRESENTATIVES FROM GRASSROOTS ORGANIZATIONS. THE EVENT WILL INCLUDE SPORTS AND CULTURAL ACTIVITIES. COMMISSIONS WILL WORK ON DEVELOPMENT PLANS. AT LEAST 2,000 PEOPLE ARE EXPECTED THIS WEEKEND AT THE PEACE CAMP.

TST1-MUC3-0034

SAN SALVADOR, 23 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] TODAY SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI REJECTED A REBEL PROPOSAL TO IMMEDIATELY NEGOTIATE A CEASE-FIRE WITH THE ARMY UNDER OAS AND UNITED NATIONS SUPERVISION; HOWEVER, HE DID EXPRESS HIS INTENTION TO SEEK A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY.

THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE ATTACKED THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR WITH MACHINEGUN FIRE AND ROCKETS JUST AS PRESIDENT CRISTIANI REJECTED THE DIALOGUE PROPOSAL MADE BY THE GUERRILLAS ON 22 NOVEMBER.

FOUR "PUSH AND PULL" PLANES AND TWO HELICOPTER GUNSHIPS OPENED FIRE ON ALLEGED FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] COLUMNS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

"THEIR PROPOSAL IS NOT SERIOUS, (THE REBELS) ARE ONCE AGAIN SAYING THAT THERE ARE TWO ARMED FORCES. IN EL SALVADOR THERE IS ONLY ONE ARMED FORCE," CRISTIANI SAID. HE ADDED THAT A POLITICAL SOLUTION ENTAILS THAT THE GUERRILLAS END THE VIOLENCE.

THE PRESIDENT, ACCOMPANIED BY COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES, SAID IN A NEWS CONFERENCE THAT THE FMLN PROPOSAL "IS NOT VERY SERIOUS" BECAUSE "IT IS NOT AIMED AT THE GOVERNMENT BUT AT THE ARMY, WHICH IS PART OF THE GOVERNMENT," HE SAID.

ACCORDING TO CRISTIANI, THE NEW FMLN PROPOSAL IS "PROPAGANDIST" AND IS ONLY MEANT TO GAIN SOME TIME IN VIEW OF THE "MILITARY DEFEAT SUFFERED IN THE LAST FEW DAYS."

CRISTIANI SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO SEEK A RATIONAL SOLUTION TO THE MILITARY CONFLICT IN THIS COUNTRY, BUT HE CATEGORICALLY EMPHASIZED THAT THIS MEANS THAT THE GUERRILLAS MUST LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND JOIN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

"WE WILL NOT ALLOW THE GUERRILLAS TO REGROUP AND BEGIN ATTACKING AGAIN. IF THEY WANT TO HOLD A DIALOGUE, THEY SHOULD LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND PEACEFULLY JOIN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS," CRISTIANI SAID.

THE PRESIDENT WARNED THAT "THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE WILLING TO FIGHT MILITARILY. IT ALL DEPENDS ON WHETHER THE FMLN CONTINUES TO BEHAVE THIS WAY, NOT LISTENING TO REASON, AND NOT ENDING THIS MADNESS," THE RIGHTIST PRESIDENT SAID.

THE NEWS CONFERENCE, HELD WITH SOME 50 JOURNALISTS, WAS ABRUPTLY INTERRUPTED BY THE HEAVY BOMBINGS CARRIED OUT BY THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE AGAINST ALLEGED GUERRILLA COLUMNS.

FOLLOWING THE FIRST BOMBINGS, WHICH ROCKED THE MILITARY OFFICES WHERE THE NEWS CONFERENCE WAS BEING HELD, CRISTIANI AND PONCE RESUMED CONTROL OF THE CONFERENCE AND EXPLAINED THAT THE ATTACK WAS THE RESULT OF AN OPERATION IN PURSUIT OF THE "GUERRILLAS FLEEING IN DISARRAY."

THE AIR FORCE BOMBING BEGAN SHORTLY BEFORE THE CURFEW, WHICH BEGAN AT 1800 (0000 GMT) UNTIL 0600 IN THE MORNING (1200 GMT), JUST WHEN THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS WERE RETURNING HOME.

THE HEAVY EXPLOSIONS CAUSED ALARM AMONG THE POPULATION IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR AND IT IS UNKNOWN WHETHER CIVILIANS HAVE BEEN HURT.

ACCORDING TO CRISTIANI, THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE "HAS BEEN A FAILURE" NOT ONLY MILITARILY, BUT POLITICALLY AS WELL BECAUSE THEY WERE UNABLE TO INCITE THE PEOPLE TO REBELLION, AS THEY PLANNED.

THE PROPOSAL SIGNED BY THE TOP FIVE FMLN COMMANDERS AND READ ON THE OFFICIAL REBEL STATION, CLANDESTINE RADIO VENCEREMOS, HAS BEEN RELEASED IN THE FRAMEWORK OF A REBEL MILITARY OFFENSIVE, WHICH BEGAN 12 DAYS AGO AND WHICH HAS LEFT MORE THAN 1,000 PEOPLE DEAD, HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE WOUNDED, AND TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE HOMELESS.

TST1-MUC3-0035

CLANDESTINE, 26 MAY 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] PLEASE PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. RADIO VENCEREMOS WILL NOW GIVE A PRELIMINARY BULLETIN ON VARIOUS ACTIONS THAT TOOK PLACE THURSDAY NIGHT IN SAN SALVADOR. EVERYONE AGAINST ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] -- WE WILL WIN!

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REPORTS THAT URBAN COMMANDO UNITS STAGED SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS ON THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS AND THE NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS AT 1830 ON THURSDAY, 25 MAY, IN THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. FURTHERMORE, ARMED UNITS DISTRIBUTED PROPAGANDA IN NEARBY AREAS. OUR UNITS ALSO SABOTAGED THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEM. WE REPORT THAT ARMED FORCES TROOPS REACTED BY SHOOTING INDISCRIMINATELY, SURROUNDING THE AREAS OF THE ATTACKS, AND CONDUCTING SEARCHES AND ARRESTS. THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY HAS BEEN SURROUNDED. TROOPS HAVE ENTERED THE UNIVERSITY AND OPENED FIRE INDISCRIMINATELY INSIDE UNIVERSITY BUILDINGS. IN FACE OF THE TERRORISM WAGED BY ARENA AND THE ARMED FORCES, EVERYONE SHOULD PREPARE TO FIGHT. EVERYONE AGAINST ARENA -- WE WILL WIN!

TST1-MUC3-0038

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 26 AUG 89 (BARRICADA) -- [ARTICLE] [MARTHA MARINA GONZALEZ] [TEXT] TEOTECACINTE -- MORE THAN 400 COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES HAVE DESERTED THE CAMPS IN YAMALES AND ARE ROAMING THE AREAS OF TROJES, CIFUENTES, JAMASTRAN, EL PARAISO, DANLI, SAN MARCOS, AND TEGUCIGALPA, DESPERATELY TRYING TO SLIP INTO THE REFUGEE GROUPS TO BE REPATRIATED -- HAD TIES WITH THE CONTRAS FOR 7 YEARS AND WAS FINALLY REPATRIATED ON WEDNESDAY 23 AUGUST.

AN INTERIOR MINISTRY SOURCE CONFIRMED TO BARRICADA THAT A CONTRA DESERTER PASSING HIMSELF OFF AS A REFUGEE ENTERED THE COUNTRY WITH A GROUP OF PEOPLE REPATRIATED BY THE ACNUR.

THE TELA AGREEMENTS HAVE CAUSED HAVOC NOT ONLY IN THE CONTRA RANKS, BUT ALSO IN THE REFUGEE CAMPS. THEIR DESPERATION TO RETURN TO NICARAGUA IS SUCH THAT MORE THAN 160 PERSONS TRIED TO ENTER THE COUNTRY ON 24 AUGUST THROUGH THE MURUPUCHI AND CERRO LA PIEDRA BORDER POSTS, BUT THE HONDURAN ARMY STOPPED THEM BECAUSE THEY LACKED THE NECESSARY DOCUMENTS.

ACCORDING TO JOSE TOMAS OSORIO, THE REFUGEES TRUST THE GUARANTEES OFFERED BY THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT. THIS WAS ASCERTAINED BY SEVERAL JOURNALISTS AT THE CERRO LA PIEDRA BORDER POST. SEVERAL PERSONS QUICKLY GOT OUT OF A VEHICLE BUT THE HONDURAN TROOPS' PRESENCE FRUSTRATED THEIR PLAN.

THE RED CROSS' BRANCH IN JALAPA HAS INSTALLED A RECEPTION POST IN CERRO LA PIEDRA, BEHIND THE TROJES CEMETERY, TO AVOID TRAGEDIES LIKE THE ONE WHICH OCCURRED LAST WEEK, WHEN A YOUTH FELL INTO A MINED FIELD. THE NICARAGUANS WILL NOW BE ABLE TO CROSS THE BORDER, IF THE HONDURAN ARMY ALLOWS THEM, WITHOUT FACING ANY DANGER.

RED CROSS PRESIDENT DENIS GUZMAN, WHO IS ALSO PRESIDENT OF THE PEACE COMMISSION, SPOKE ON 25 AUGUST WITH THE PERSON COMMANDING THE HONDURAN BORDER POST. HE SAID THAT THE RED CROSS WAS WILLING TO ACCEPT ALL THOSE WHO WANT TO RETURN TO NICARAGUA. THE HONDURAN OFFICER SAID: "WE HAVE NO INFORMATION BUT, IF MY COMMANDER AUTHORIZES IT, WE WILL NOT OBJECT AND WILL LET THEM PASS. HOWEVER, WE CANNOT LET ANYONE CROSS THROUGH HERE FOR THE TIME BEING."

SEVERAL REPATRIATED PERSONS RETURNING ON 23 AUGUST THROUGH LAS MANOS CONFIRMED THE PROBLEMS OF THE REFUGEES AT THE CAMPS: "THERE IS NO FREEDOM TO WORK, THE FOOD IS RATIONED, THE PEOPLE ARE ALWAYS HUNGRY, AND WE LIVED LIKE ANIMALS IN A CORRAL," IT WAS STATED BY ERNESTINA UMANZOR, WHO WAS KIDNAPPED AT THE CIFUENTES BORDER REGION AND LATER WAS REPATRIATED.

REFERRING TO THE CONTRAS, THE NICARAGUANS LIVING IN HONDURAN TERRITORY SAID THAT THE FORMER "ARE OUTSIDE THE LAW; THEY HAVE NOTHING TO DO; THEY MUST PUT DOWN THEIR WEAPONS; THEY MUST BE DEMOBILIZED; THEY HAVE NO BUSINESS GOING TO THIRD COUNTRIES; THEY MUST RETURN TO THEIR HOMELAND," IT WAS ASSERTED BY DOMINGO OROZCO.

THE REPATRIATED PEOPLE WHO ARRIVED AT TEOTECACINTE WERE WELCOMED BY LOCAL PEOPLE, WHO WERE SATISFIED WITH THEIR RETURN AND SAID THEY WOULD SUPPORT THOSE WHO WISH TO TILL IDLE AND ABANDONED LANDS.

TST1-MUC3-0039

SANTIAGO, 29 MAR 89 -- [TEXT] THE INVESTIGATIVE POLICE HAVE ADMITTED THAT THE INDIVIDUALS THAT FIRED THEIR GUNS DURING A DEMONSTRATION OF HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS AT BERNARDO O'HIGGINS AVENUE YESTERDAY ARE MEMBERS OF THE POLICE DEPARTMENT. THE CIVILIAN POLICE PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE RELEASED THE FOLLOWING COMMUNIQUE:

REGARDING THE PICTURE THAT APPEARS IN THE MORNING NEWSPAPERS LA EPOCA AND FORTIN MAPOCHO SHOWING CIVILIANS TRYING TO CONTROL THE DISORDERS PROVOKED BY YOUNG INDIVIDUALS AT BERNARDO O'HIGGINS AVENUE NEAR SAN IGNACIO AND NATANIEL STREETS, THE INVESTIGATIVE POLICE PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE STATES THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE CAR THAT APPEARS IN THE PICTURES OF BOTH NEWSPAPERS BELONGS TO THE INVESTIGATIVE POLICE. THE CAR WAS ON PATROL CARRYING OUT SURVEILLANCE FOR POSSIBLE CRIMINAL ACTIVITY.

2. THE BEHAVIOR OF THE AGENTS IN THE POLICE CAR IS NOT IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE NORMS OF CONDUCT ESTABLISHED BY THE INSTITUTION FOR SUCH CIRCUMSTANCES. THE INSTITUTION WILL THEREFORE DISCIPLINE THE AGENTS INVOLVED.

3. HOWEVER, THE INVESTIGATIVE POLICE WARN THAT ACCORDING TO LAW 2460, ARTICLE 5, ITS DUTY IS TO MAINTAIN PUBLIC ORDER AND COMBAT ALL CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES.

4. THE POPULATION MUST REST ASSURED THAT THE INSTITUTION WILL FULFILL ITS DUTY TO MAINTAIN ORDER WHILE MAINTAINING THE APPROPRIATE STANDARD OF CONDUCT WITHIN THE DETECTIVE DEPARTMENT.

SIGNED: JUAN DIAZ JARA, CHIEF PREFECT OF THE CIVILIAN POLICE PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE.

SEVERAL SHOTS WERE HEARD FOLLOWING THE INCIDENTS YESTERDAY AT THE CENTRAL WALKWAY OF BERNARDO O'HIGGINS AVENUE DURING A DEMONSTRATION STAGED BY STUDENTS FROM THE APPLICATIONS SCHOOL. THE STUDENTS WERE MARCHING TO HONOR THE TWO VERGARA TOLEDO BROTHERS WHO WERE KILLED 4 YEARS AGO DURING AN APPARENT CONFRONTATION AT VILLA FRANCIA.

AROUND 1400 YESTERDAY, SOME 100 STUDENTS FROM THE APPLICATIONS SCHOOL BUILT A ROADBLOCK AND MARCHED THROUGH THE CENTRAL WALKWAY OF O'HIGGINGS AVENUE. WHEN THE DEMONSTRATORS PASSED THE BRAZILIAN EMBASSY, A GUARD CAME OUT AND POINTED A GUN AT THEM. THE STUDENTS THEN PICKED UP STONES AND FORCES THE GUARD TO WITHDRAW.

LATER, TWO INDIVIDUALS IN A CHEVROLET OPALA AUTOMOBILE POINTED AK RIFLES AT THE STUDENTS, FIRED SOME SHOTS, AND QUICKLY DROVE AWAY. FINALLY A DETACHMENT OF CARABINEROS ARRIVED AT THE SCENE, ARRESTED SEVERAL STUDENTS, AND BROKE UP THE DEMONSTRATION.

TST1-MUC3-0040

BOGOTA, 4 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] TODAY "THE EXTRADITABLES," AN ORGANIZATION CONSIDERED TO BE THE ARMED SECTOR OF THE "MEDELLIN CARTEL," ORDERED "ITS LEADERS" IN LOW-INCOME NEIGHBORHOODS "TO TAKE HOSTAGES FROM TRADITIONAL BOURGEOISIE SECTORS TO FINANCE THE WAR" IT IS WAGING WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO.

"THE EXTRADITABLES" SENT A 7-POINT COMMUNIQUE TO SEVERAL MEDIA SOURCES IN MEDELLIN, CALLING ON THEIR MEN TO DEMAND LARGE SUMS OF MONEY FROM THE RELATIVES OF THE PERSONS THEY KIDNAP.

THEY ALSO RECOMMEND THAT THE PERSONS WHO ARE GOING TO CARRY OUT THE ABDUCTIONS SHOULD SELECT THE VICTIMS FROM AMONG POLITICIANS AND MEMBERS OF THE COLOMBIAN BOURGEOISIE "WHO HAVE NEVER DISTINGUISHED THEMSELVES BY MAKING SOCIAL CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE COMMUNITY."

THEY ADD THAT "50 PERCENT OF THE FUNDS OBTAINED FROM SUCH MILITARY ACTIONS ARE TO BE USED TO FINANCE THE WAR AGAINST THE POLITICAL OLIGARCHY AND THE OTHER 50 PERCENT TO RECONSTRUCT LOW-INCOME HOUSING FOR THE HOMELESS."

ANOTHER POINT NOTES THAT "THIS MEASURE HAS BEEN TAKEN AS A RESPONSE TO THE OFFICIAL PERSECUTION AGAINST OUR FAMILIES AND ORGANIZATIONS," AND IT CONCLUDES BY STATING THAT "WE ARE WILLING TO HOLD A DIALOGUE AS THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE ARE REQUESTING AND DESIRE."

ON 24 AUGUST 1989, "THE EXTRADITABLES" ANNOUNCED A COUNTEROFFENSIVE IN RESPONSE TO THE OFFICIAL ACTIONS OF PRESIDENT BARCO'S GOVERNMENT. THE GOVERNMENT INITIATED THE ATTACK ON THE DRUG-TRAFFICKING MAFIAS AFTER PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LUIS CARLOS GALAN WAS KILLED ON 18 AUGUST.

SINCE THEN, DRUG TRAFFICKERS BEGAN A SERIES OF ATTACKS WITH EXPLOSIVES AND CAR BOMBS MAINLY AGAINST BANKING ORGANIZATIONS, POLITICAL HEADQUARTERS, AND NEWSPAPERS.

ON 2 SEPTEMBER, A CAR BOMB DESTROYED THE INSTALLATIONS OF "EL ESPECTADOR" NEWSPAPER IN BOGOTA AND 5 WEEKS LATER ANOTHER CAR BOMB CAUSED SIMILAR DAMAGE TO THE "VANGUARDIA LIBERAL" NEWSPAPER IN BUCARAMANGA, IN NORTHEASTERN COLOMBIA.

SEVERAL SECURITY FORCES HEADQUARTERS HAVE ALSO BEEN HIT BY THESE ATTACKS AND AN AVIANCA AIRLINES PLANE BLEW UP IN MIDAIR ON 27 NOVEMBER KILLING ALL 107 PASSENGERS AND CREW.

A WEEK LATER, A BUS BOMB BLEW UP IN THE VICINITY OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS), IN THE CENTER OF BOGOTA, AND DESTROYED THE 11-FLOOR BUILDING, LEAVING 67 DEAD AND APPROXIMATELY 1,000 WOUNDED.

TST1-MUC3-0041

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, WE HAVE A LAST MINUTE REPORT. RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTS TO OUR PEOPLE ON THE FIGHTING THAT IS UNDER WAY IN SAN SALVADOR. WE ARE GOING TO GIVE YOU MILITARY INFORMATION FROM THE METROPOLITAN WAR FRONT, AS FOLLOWS:

THERE HAS BEEN FIGHTING AGAINST ATLACATL BATTALION ARMORED VEHICLES IN CUSCATANCINGO. AT 0700, THERE WAS AN EXTENSIVE AMBUSH IN WHICH SIX ARMORED VEHICLES WERE DESTROYED. THE AMBUSH WAS STAGED AGAINST ATLACATL BATTALION TROOPS IN CUSCATANCINGO WHO WERE ON THEIR WAY TO REINFORCE ENEMY POSITIONS UNDER ATTACK IN VARIOUS POINTS OF THE CAPITAL. OUR FORCES USED ROCKET LAUNCHERS AND SMALL ARMS FIRE, AS WELL AS EXPLOSIVES, TO AMBUSH THIS CONVOY, DESTROYING SIX ARMORED VEHICLES.

IN ADDITION, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION [FMLN] FIGHTERS ATTACKED BELLOSO BATTALION TROOPS IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE. THE BELLOSO BATTALION CALLED FOR AIR SUPPORT, WHICH IT RECEIVED, BUT THIS HAS RESULTED IN MORE CIVILIAN CASUALTIES BECAUSE THE HELICOPTERS USED HAVE BEEN BOMBING AND STRAFING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN THE AYUTUXTEPEQUE AREA. THE DESPERATE AIR SUPPORT HAS RESULTED IN MORE CIVILIAN VICTIMS.

MEANWHILE, FMLN FORCES BEGAN ATTACKING ENEMY POSITIONS IN LOS SANTOS, BOSQUES DEL RIO, AND UNICENTRO, IN SOYAPANGO.

IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT BARRICADES ARE CONSTANTLY BEING BUILT IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTIAL AREAS OF SAN SALVADOR'S NORTHERN AND SOUTHERN SECTORS. THESE ARE BARRICADES BUILT BY YOUTHS, STUDENTS, WORKERS, WOMEN, AND CHILDREN WHO HAVE TAKEN TO THE STREETS TO HELP WITH FOOD AND INFORMATION AND WHO, WITH THEIR OWN HANDS, ARE BUILDING BARRICADES AND ANSWERING THE CALL OF THE VANGUARD: THE FMLN.

WE ARE RECEIVING A REPORT WHICH INDICATES THAT THE FIGHTING WHICH HAD DECREASED IN THE UNIVERSITY AREA RESUMED AT 0600 THIS MORNING.

TST1-MUC3-0042

TEGUCIGALPA, 20 DEC 89 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] FOLLOWING THE U.S. INVASION OF GRENADA ISLAND, THE WORLD DISCARDED ANY FURTHER POSSIBILITY OF A U.S. ARMED OPERATION AGAINST ANOTHER NATION OF THE AMERICAN CONTINENT, DESPITE THE DETERIORATION OF ITS RELATIONS WITH OTHER GOVERNMENTS AND PROVOCATIONS AGAINST THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. IT WAS BELIEVED THAT THE U.S. WOULD CONFINE ITS PARTICIPATION TO SUPPORTING AND SPONSORING MOVEMENTS AIMED AT OUSTING GOVERNMENTS OR, AS IN THE CASE OF NICARAGUA, OF SUPPORTING REBEL FORCES TO ACHIEVE THE GOALS SET BY THE WHITE HOUSE.

THE EVENTS THAT OCCURRED EARLY THIS MORNING IN PANAMA HAVE SURPRISED THE WORLD BECAUSE, DESPITE GENERAL MANUEL ANTONIO NORIEGA'S CHALLENGING ATTITUDE, NO ONE THOUGHT THE U.S. WOULD INVADE PANAMA. NORIEGA WAS CERTAIN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WOULD NOT DO SO, AND SUPPOSED THAT U.S. ATTITUDES AGAINST HIM WOULD CONSIST OF SPONSORING REBELLION, SUCH AS THE RECENT 3-OCTOBER ATTEMPT, WHEN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ENCOURAGED MEMBERS OF THE PANAMANIAN DEFENSE FORCES TO REBEL AGAINST THEIR COMMANDER IN CHIEF. NORIEGA NEVER THOUGHT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WOULD EVER CONDUCT A MILITARY OPERATION AGAINST PANAMA, ALTHOUGH THERE WERE U.S. TROOPS BASED ON THE CANAL ZONE. HE CONTINUED UNDER THIS IMPRESSION BECAUSE NEVER BEFORE HAD THESE TROOPS CHANGED FROM THEIR ROLE OF SURVEILLANCE, NOT EVEN WHEN WASHINGTON PROMOTED THE REBELLION OF SOME YOUNG OFFICERS OF THE PANAMANIAN FORCES.

THIS EXCESSIVE SECURITY DISTRACTED NORIEGA AND ENCOURAGED HIM TO CHALLENGE THE U.S. POLICIES. NORIEGA DID NOT BELIEVE THE U.S. THREATS AND HE ADOPTED AN OMNIPOTENT STANCE, LIKE HIS RECENT DECISION TO APPOINT HIMSELF THE SUPREME LEADER OF PANAMA. NORIEGA BELIEVED THAT THE UNITED STATES WOULD CONTINUE TO SUPPORT SUBVERSION IN HIS COUNTRY, AND THAT THE U.S. DECISION TO SUPPORT THE OPPOSITION CURRENTLY IN EXILE WOULD PRODUCE MOVEMENTS AGAINST HIS REGIME, OR THAT A COMMANDO MIGHT ATTEMPT TO KIDNAP HIM. AS A RESULT OF THIS BELIEF, HE INCREASED THE STRENGTH OF THE MILITARY FORCES AND EQUIPPED MANY CIVILIANS WHO SUPPORTED HIM WITH WEAPONS TO BE READY TO DISMANTLE MOVEMENTS THAT TRIED TO DESTABILIZE HIS GOVERNMENT.

AS THE CLOCKS STRUCK MIDNIGHT IN PANAMA, THE U.S. FORCES BEGAN AN OPERATION AGAINST THE PANAMANIAN DEFENSE FORCE BARRACKS. THE TROOPS ALREADY BASED IN PANAMA, AND THOSE FLOWN IN FROM BASES IN CALIFORNIA AND IN OTHER CITIES NEAR PANAMA, STARTED A MASSIVE ATTACK TO OUST GEN NORIEGA.

THE INVASION, WHICH SEEMED POSSIBLE TO SOME AND TO OTHERS [WORDS INDISTINCT], WERE MAINLY CONDUCTED TO PUNISH SOMEONE WHO HAS BEEN DECLARED ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT LATIN AMERICAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS BY THE U.S. COURTS.

EARLY THIS MORNING, SOURCES CLOSE TO THE WHITE HOUSE ANNOUNCED THAT THE OPERATION WAS AIMED AT CAPTURING NORIEGA AND TAKING HIM TO THE UNITED STATES TO BE TRIED FOR THE CRIMES ATTRIBUTED TO HIM BY THE U.S. COURTS, AT ENSURING COMPLIANCE WITH THE TREATIES ON THE PANAMA CANAL, AND AT RESTORING DEMOCRACY IN THE COUNTRY FOLLOWING THE FARCICAL MAY-L989 ELECTIONS.

THESE ARE THE REASONS FOR THE U.S. ARMED INTERVENTION IN PANAMA, WHICH IS FILLING THE WORLD WITH TREPIDATION DUE TO THE DANGER HOVERING OVER THE CONTINENT AND THE FACT THAT PRESIDENT BUSH'S DECISION HAS GONE BEYOND THE LOGIC OF THE U.S. POLICY TOWARD LATIN AMERICA.

INTERNATIONAL OBSERVERS DID, HOWEVER, GUESS THAT SOMETHING WAS ABOUT TO OCCUR WHEN PRESIDENT BUSH SAID RECENTLY THAT WHILE THE U.S. GOVERNMENT COULD REACH AGREEMENT WITH NICARAGUA, WITH NORIEGA IT WAS IMPOSSIBLE TO REACH ANY AGREEMENT, AND THAT THE UNITED STATES HAD TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT THIS VEILED DANGER THAT THREATENED THE AMERICAN CONTINENT.

TODAY, PANAMA HAS BECOME A BATTLEFIELD. THE CAPITAL AND OTHER CITIES ARE BATTLEFIELDS ON WHICH THE GOVERNMENT FORCES ARE FIGHTING THE U.S. UNITS IN GROUND, AIR, AND MARITIME OPERATIONS THAT SEEK TO OUST MANUEL ANTONIO NORIEGA.

THE U.S. ACTION IS FOCUSSING THE WORLD'S ATTENTION ON WASHINGTON'S DECISION. MANY NATIONS WILL PROTEST AND REJECT THE U.S. INVASION WHICH WAS DISGUISED BY A SERIES OF PEACE-SEEKING ACTIONS.

FOUR DAYS BEFORE CHRISTMAS EVE, THE GHOST OF WAR IS HAUNTING OUR CONTINENT. WE MUST PONDER ON THE NEED TO KEEP HONDURAS ON THE DEMOCRATIC PATH, AND TO AVOID THE ANARCHY THAT DESTROYS NATIONS AND DECIMATES PEOPLES. THE EVENTS THAT HAVE KEPT THE WORLD IN VIGIL SINCE MIDNIGHT WILL CONTINUE FOR HOURS, DAYS, OR MAYBE WEEKS BECAUSE, SO FAR, THE NEWS IS VERY CONFUSING AND CIVILIAN VICTIMS ARE DYING ON THE STREETS OF THE PANAMANIAN TOWNS.

TST1-MUC3-0043

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN COMMANDER SANCHO BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] COMMANDER, DO THE RN LEADERS AGREE THAT THE FMLN SHOULD EVENTUALLY JOIN THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL [SI] AS HAS BEEN PROPOSED CONCERNING THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FSLN] IN NICARAGUA?

[SANCHO] WE THINK SO, BECAUSE SI HAS REPRESENTED, FOR THE PAST 30-40 YEARS, A EUROPEAN INTERNATIONAL POLITICAL BLOC THAT HAS SUPPORTED THE STRUGGLE....[CORRECTS HIMSELF] THAT HAS SHOWN INTEREST IN THE THIRD WORLD. IN OTHER WORDS, WE BELIEVE THAT EVERY INTERNATIONAL POLITICAL BLOC THAT TRULY WANTS TO ESTABLISH RELATIONS AND HELP -- WHILE STILL DEFENDING EUROPEAN INTERESTS -- IS VIABLE AND POSITIVE. THE FMLN MUST NECESSARILY JOIN THE SI.

[REPORTER] IN THE 1970'S [WORDS INDISTINCT] STRUGGLE IN OUR COUNTRY AND THE WAR RESULTED FROM A DECISION ADOPTED BY THE PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY [ERP]. VIRTUALLY NO ONE TALKS ABOUT THIS WITHIN THE FMLN NOW, YET THE RIGHT-WING SECTORS ALWAYS REMEMBER THE RESULTING SITUATIONS WITHIN THE LEFT-WING SECTORS. WHAT DOES THE RN THINK ABUT THE ERP IN 1990?

[SANCHO] WE HAVE STATED AND WE HAVE PUT IT IN WRITING -- IT IS GOOD TO HAVE IT IN WRITING -- THAT THE LEFT BECAME DIVIDED AND THE ERP BECAME DIVIDED BECAUSE WE WERE NOT FIRM ENOUGH, POLITICALLY AND IDEOLOGICALLY SPEAKING. WE BELIEVE THAT THE ERP LEADERSHIP ACTED CHILDISHLY [WORDS INDISTINCT], BUT WE CAN NOW SAY THAT WE HAVE ACHIEVED MATURITY IN EVERY SECTOR. THE OPTIONS WE HAVE CHOSEN WITHIN THE FMLN HAVE ALLOWED US TO CLEARLY SEE THE OUTCOME OF THE DECISIONS WE ADOPTED IN THE PAST.

THIS HAS OBVIOUSLY BEEN [WORD INDISTINCT] AND MISCONSTRUED BY THE ENEMY IN ITS PROPAGANDA AND PSYCHOLOGICAL WAR, BECAUSE IT LOVES TO SAY THAT REVOLUTIONARIES ALWAYS END UP KILLING EACH OTHER. [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE IDEOLOGICAL STRUGGLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] INDICATES THAT WE [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND UNITY HAS PREVAILED WITHIN THE FMLN. WE CONSIDER THE DIVISION A PROCESS THAT IS PART OF EL SALVADOR'S HISTORY AND WE SHOULD NOT CRY OVER SPILT MILK. NO ONE SHOULD DEPLORE.... [CHANGES THOUGHT] WE CANNOT SPECULATE ON WHAT MIGHT HAVE HAPPENED. IT WAS THE RESULT OF OUR IMMATURITY.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER, EVERYONE KNOWS THE NAMES OF THE FMLN LEADERS -- PARTICULARLY THE FIVE MEMBERS OF THE GENERAL COMMAND -- BUT THIS IS SOMETHING NEW. YOU WERE PREVIOUSLY KNOWN AS FERMAN CIENFUEGOS AND NOT EVERYONE KNEW THAT YOU WERE EDUARDO SANCHO COLOMBARI. THERE IS ALWAYS A CLANDESTINE ELEMENT INVOLVED. WHY IS THERE ALWAYS A TENDENCY TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS?

[SANCHO] I THINK THAT AFTER 10 OR 20 YEARS IN HIDING WE [WORDS INDISTINCT] POLITICAL CONDUCT THAT DOES NOT CORRESPOND TO MODERN TIMES AND OUR POLITICAL NEEDS. THEREFORE, THE GENERAL COMMAND NEEDS [WORDS INDISTINCT] SPECIFIC CONDITIONS, MEANING THE NEED FOR THE GENERAL COMMAND MEMBERS TO GO PUBLIC. WE BELIEVE THAT THE GENERAL COMMAND MEMBERS SHOULD GO PUBLIC AND STATE THEIR VIEWS SO THAT THEY PEOPLE CAN LEARN MORE ABOUT THEM, THEIR HUMAN SIDE, AND THEIR PERSONALITIES. IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THE PEOPLE AND THE WORLD TO KNOW ABOUT THE LEADERS' PERSONALITIES AS THEY ARE. THIS HAS BEEN -- LET US CALL IT A DEFECT OR LIMITATION. SECRECY IS A DEVIATION AND A PERSON CAN MAINTAIN.... [CORRECTS HIMSELF] COMBINE SECRECY WITH OUR POLITICAL ROLE. WE NOW WE HAVE TO OVERCOME THAT DEVIATION, MEANING SECRECY AND ANONYMITY.

[REPORTER] YES.

[SANCHO] I BELIEVE WE ARE TRYING TO OVERCOME THIS.

TST1-MUC3-0044

SAN SALVADOR, 2 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] WE NOW HAVE COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ ON THE TELEPHONE. THE ARMED FORCES, PARTICULARLY THE COMMANDERS OF THE VARIOUS ARMY BRANCHES AND GARRISONS WHO WERE CONVENED BY THE DEFENSE MINISTER, MADE A STATEMENT AGAINST THIS OFFICER, WHO IS A DEPUTY AND THE CURRENT CEL [LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION] PRESIDENT, AFTER HE DEMANDED JUSTICE IN THE CASE OF THE ASSASSINATED JESUIT PRIESTS. WE WILL NOW LISTEN TO COL OCHOA, WHO WILL MAKE KNOWN HIS STAND SINCE THE ARMED FORCES' STATEMENT WAS RELEASED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] GOOD MORNING, COLONEL.

[OCHOA] GOOD MORNING. THANKS, RAUL. THESE GENTLEMEN SEEM TO BE SPEAKING IN THE NAME OF THE ENTIRE ARMED FORCES. I KNOW WELL WHAT WAS DISCUSSED IN THE MEETING. SOMEONE EVEN SAID THAT THE BRIGHT IDEA OF DISCHARGING ME WAS CONSIDERED. THEY FAILED TO TAKE INTO ACCOUNT, HOWEVER, THAT I AM A DEPUTY AND THAT, AS A DEPUTY AND A CITIZEN, I AM ENTITLED TO EXPRESS WHAT I FEEL, JUST AS I HAVE DONE. I, WHO OWE EVERYTHING TO THE ARMED FORCES, WHO FOUGHT BESIDE THE SOLDIERS AS MONTERROSA, CARLITOS, AND VERY FEW OTHERS DID, NEVER GOT RICH WHEN IN THE ARMED FORCES, AS SOME OF THE COMMANDERS DID, ALTHOUGH NOT ALL OF THEM, OF COURSE. THIS UNDOUBTEDLY HAS IRRITATED THEM.

I HAVE SIMPLY EXPRESSED MY VIEWPOINT AS A SOLDIER CONCERNED ABOUT THE ARMED FORCES' SITUATION. I NEVER MENTIONED ANY NAMES. I SIMPLY DEMANDED JUSTICE BECAUSE, EVEN ACCORDING TO MILITARY THEORY, I CANNOT CONCEIVE THAT SUCH AN IMPORTANT DECISION COULD HAVE BEEN MADE BY A SINGLE PERSON. I STILL THINK THIS IS A PLOT BY SOME MEMBERS OF THE INSTITUTION, NOT BY THE ARMED FORCES AS SUCH. I ONLY HAVE RESPECT AND LOVE FOR THE ARMED FORCES. I AM CONCERNED OVER THE DELICATE SITUATION TO WHICH THE INSTITUTION COULD BE LED BECAUSE OF THE ACTIONS OF SOME NEFARIOUS MEMBERS. I HAVE DEEP RESPECT FOR THE OFFICERS IN THE FIELD, WHO FIGHT EVERY DAY. OF COURSE, I MUST CRITICIZE THOSE WHO HAVE PROFITED FROM THE INSTITUTION AND WHO TODAY HAVE RAISED THE ROOF, AS IF I WERE THE ONE TO BLAME AND AS IF I WERE UNDERMINING THE INSTITUTIONALITY OF THE STATE. QUITE THE OPPOSITE IS TRUE. MY CRITICISM IS POSITIVE AND INTENDS TO ENCOURAGE A DEEPER INVESTIGATION AND EXHAUST ALL RESOURCES IN THIS DIRECTION. I WOULD LIKE THEM TO STOP MAKING RIDICULOUS DEMANDS AND TO STOP SEEKING A CONFRONTATION. IT IS KNOWN THAT WHAT I AM DEMANDING IS WHAT IS BEING FELT AND SAID. I AM NOT ACCUSING ANYONE IN PARTICULAR. I AM ONLY DEMANDING JUSTICE. COMMANDERS' MEETINGS SHOULD NOT BE HELD TO MAKE SUCH A STATEMENT. THEY SHOULD HAVE INSTEAD SHOWN THEIR CONCERN OVER THE ARMED FORCES' SITUATION. I WOULD HAVE BEEN VERY INTERESTED IN SEEING THEM TAKE THE STAND TO CONTINUE THE INVESTIGATION TO THE LAST CONSEQUENCES. AS THE MILITARY MAN I AM, I ONLY ASSESSED THE SITUATION. I NEVER MENTIONED ANY NAMES, BUT INSISTED THAT A DEEPER INQUIRY SHOULD BE MADE TO CARRY OUT JUSTICE, BECAUSE OTHERWISE IT IS THE INSTITUTION THAT WILL SUFFER.

[REPORTER] COL OCHOA, AFTER THE "SIXTY MINUTES" PROGRAM ON CBS IN THE UNITED STATES, IT SEEMS THAT IN THIS CAPITAL AND IN THE COUNTRY YOUR REMARKS AND YOUR INTERPRETATION OF THE JESUITS' CASE WERE DISTORTED. TODAY THERE HAS BEEN AN ATTEMPT TO ACCUSE YOU. IT HAS BEEN SAID THAT THE CUT IN U.S. AID TO THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES IS THE RESULT OF YOUR REMARKS, RATHER THAN OF THE SLOWNESS IN THE INVESTIGATION OF THE JEUSIT PRIESTS' CASE. DO YOU THINK THERE HAS BEEN ILL INTENT IN THIS, OR THAT THERE HAS BEEN AN ATTEMPT TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF YOU TO TRY TO JUSTIFY AN ACTION?

[OCHOA] I THINK SO. THERE HAS BEEN AN ATTEMPT TO BLAME ME, AS IF I COULD INFLUENCE THE DECISION-MAKING OF THE U.S. CONGRESS. A REDUCTION IN MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR HAS BEEN UNDER CONSIDERATION FOR MONTHS BECAUSE THE EXPECTED RESULTS HAVE NOT BEEN OBTAINED. I THINK IT IS RIDICULOUS AND CHILDISH TO SAY THAT THE AID WILL BE CUT AS THE RESULT OF MY REMARKS. THE TRUTH IS THAT ALL CRIMES WITH WHICH SOME ARMED FORCES' MEMBERS HAVE JEOPARDIZED THE INSTITUTION SHOULD BE PUNISHED. MY UNDERSTANDING IS THAT SOLIDARITY SHOULD EXIST IN THE CONTEXT OF OPERATIONS AND THE FULFILLMENT OF THE ARMED FORCES' CONSTITUTIONAL MISSION. HOWEVER, THOSE WHO HARM THE INSTITUTION SHOULD NOT BE PROTECTED.

I THINK SOME ARE TRYING TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE SITUATION, AS IF TO SAY: COL OCHOA HAS ENDANGERED THE ARMED FORCES. WHAT HAS ENDANGERED THE INSTITUTION IS THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS AND THE SAN SEBASTIAN PEOPLE. I CANOT AGREE WITH THE PERPETRATION OF OUTRAGES. ONE THING IS TO FIGHT FAIRLY WITH THE ENEMY. THERE ARE DEAD IN EVERY WAR. I SAID THIS VERY CLEARLY WHEN I WAS 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE COMMANDER IN CABANAS. I AGREED WITH THE PENETRATION INTO THE POPULATION TO HELP THEM. I FEEL SATISFIED OVER MY PASSAGE THROUGH THE ARMED FORCES AS A COMMANDER, BECAUSE I IDENTIFIED MYSELF BOTH WITH MY MEN AND THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. AT NO TIME DID I TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE INSTITUTION TO ACQUIRE ILLEGAL RICHES. TO POINT THESE THINGS OUT IS NOT TO ATTACK THE ARMED FORCES. QUITE THE CONTRARY, IT IS BECAUSE I LOVE IT THAT I HAVE CRITICIZED THE NEGATIVE MEMBERS. THE ARMED FORCES CAN THUS BE SPARED GREATER DAMAGE BY THE POOR ACTIONS OF SOME OF ITS MEMBERS.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, IN THE PAST FEW HOURS WE HAVE HEARD REPORTS THAT YOU ARE TO BE SUPPORTED BY THE ARMY'S YOUNGER OFFICERS AND SOME UNIONS, EVEN THE CEL UNION. WHAT CAN YOU TELL US ABOUT THIS SITUATION? [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0046

SAN SALVADOR, 6 JUL 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE A FEW HOURS AGO DENYING THAT IT DIRECTED AN ATTACK AGAINST SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE PRESIDENT MAURICIO GUTIERREZ CASTRO.

THE REBEL COMMUNIQUE READS: ON THE AFTERNOON OF 2 JULY, FMLN GUERRILLAS CARRIED OUT PROPAGANDA ACTIVITY AND OCCUPIED 8 KM OF THE ROAD TO LA LIBERTAD PORT, BETWEEN THE 14- AND 21-KM MARKERS, WHERE THEY ERECTED A BARRICADE. THE GUERRILLAS ADDED THAT THEY STOPPED APPROXIMATELY 200 VEHICLES TO MEET AND EXCHANGE VIEWS WITH THE DRIVERS.

AT THE 14-KM MARKER, A VEHICLE IN WHICH (ROBERTO MATIS REGALADO'S) BODYGUARDS WERE RIDING ARRIVED, BUT THE DRIVER DID NOT OBEY THE ORDER TO STOP, WHICH PROVOKED A CLASH WITH OUR UNITS. TWO MEN WERE WOUNDED AND ONE WOMAN WAS KILLED AS A RESULT OF THAT INCIDENT.

OUR FORCES REPORTED THAT THEY SEIZED ONE M-16 RIFLE AND ONE .45 - CALIBER PISTOL. THE FMLN DOCUMENT ADDS THAT MINUTES LATER, AT THE 21-KM MARKER, THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE PRESIDENT'S BODYGUARDS TRIED TO SURPRISE OUR FIGHTERS AND ANOTHER CLASH OCCURRED. DURING THE CLASH, ONE BODYGUARD WAS KILLED AND THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] OFFICIAL WAS WOUNDED.

PARAGRAPH THREE OF THE COMMUNIQUE ADDS THAT THE ARMED PROPAGANDA ACTIVITIES ALONG THE LA LIBERTAD PORT - SAN SALVADOR ROUTE ARE AIMED AT DISTRIBUTING PROPAGANDA AND AT DESTABILIZING THIS VITAL ROUTE USED BY GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS AND MILITARY MEN TO TRAVEL TO THEIR PRIVATE CLUBS LOCATED ALONG THE COAST.

THE FMLN, THE DOCUMENT ADDS, REITERATES ITS DETERMINATION TO STOP THOSE WHO ARE INVOLVED IN THE GENOCIDAL WAR -- THOSE WHO EVERY DAY SHELL THE RURAL AREAS AND PERSECUTE AND MURDER PEASANTS, WORKERS, AND STUDENTS -- FROM TAKING IT EASY AND RELAXING AT THEIR CLUBS AND IN THEIR EXCLUSIVE NEIGHBORHOODS. THE ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL POLICE STATION AT THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE MILITARY NEIGHBORHOOD FOLLOWS THIS SAME LINE OF DESTABILIZATION. THEREFORE, WE CALL ON OUR PEOPLE TO PAY ATTENTION TO THE RECOMMENDATIONS AND ORDERS ISSUED BY OUR FIGHTERS AND TO THEREBY PREVENT REGRETTABLE LOSSES. WE WARN BODYGUARDS AND SECURITY GUARDS THAT WE WILL FIGHT THOSE WHO ARE ARMED AND WHO OFFER RESISTANCE.

IN CONCLUSION, THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE RELEASED A FEW HOURS AGO ADDS: WE REITERATE THAT WE WILL CONTINUE TO ABIDE BY OUR REVOLUTIONARY PRINCIPLES AND STICK TO THE TRUTH. WE DID NOT PARTICIPATE IN INCIDENTS SUCH AS THE ATTACK AGAINST [PRESIDENCY MINISTER] ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH AND EDGAR CHACON [IDEOLOGUE OF THE ORLANDO DE SOLA GROUP]. THESE INCIDENTS RESULTED FROM A WAR WITHIN ARENA RANKS, AND WE WARN THAT ACTS OF REPRESSION UNLEASHED BY THE GOVERNMENT AGAINST THE POPULAR AND DEMOCRATIC MOVEMENTS WILL NOT GO UNPUNISHED AND WILL RECEIVE A STRONG RESPONSE FROM OUR FORCES.

THIS WAS THE RECENT FMLN COMMUNIQUE ON THE INCIDENTS THAT OCCURRED ON 2 JULY ON THE ROAD TO LA LIBERTAD PORT, WHERE THE PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE WAS WOUNDED.

TST1-MUC3-0047

QUITO, 26 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] ECUADOR TODAY CONCEDED THE POSSIBILITY THAT THERE MAY BE COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN ECUADORAN TERRITORY, ALTHOUGH IT EMPHASIZED THAT BORDER CONTROLS HAVE BEEN REINFORCED "TO PREVENT THE SPREAD OF VIOLENCE AND TERROR."

ASKED ABOUT THE POSSIBLE PRESENCE OF MEMBERS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, INTERIOR MINISTER ANDRES VALLEJO SAID: "IT IS POSSIBLE. HOWEVER, THERE ARE QUITE RELIABLE REPORTS THAT THEY (THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS) HAVE MORE LIKELY FLED TO OTHER COUNTRIES."

THE MINISTER REVEALED THAT A FINANCING COMPANY, WHICH HE DID NOT IDENTIFY, WAS CLOSED BY THE GOVERNMENT BECAUSE IT WAS FOUND TO BE LAUNDERING DOLLARS OBTAINED FROM THE TRAFFICKING. "THERE WILL BE NO MERCY IN SUCH CASES," HE SAID.

OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS, PRESS REPORTS MENTIONED ECUADOR AS ONE OF THE COUNTRIES IN WHICH THE TOP LEADERS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL HAD REPORTEDLY TAKEN REFUGE TO ESCAPE THE ACTIONS LAUNCHED BY THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT FOLLOWING A SERIES OF ASSASSINATIONS COMMITTED BY THE DRUG MAFIAS. EARLY THIS WEEK, ECUADOR REINFORCED ITS EXTENSIVE BORDER WITH COLOMBIA TO KEEP THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS OUT.

ASSESSING THE STATUS OF DRUGS IN ECUADOR, THE MINISTER ADMITTED THAT "SEVERAL LARGE ESTATES HAVE BEEN PURCHASED BY PEOPLE WHO APPEAR TO BE LINKED TO THE DRUG TRAFFIC." HOWEVER, HE EXPRESSED THE OPINION THAT THESE PURCHASES WERE LINKED TO MONEY LAUNDERING RATHER THAN THE PRODUCTION OF DRUGS.

VALLEJO ALSO SAID THAT ECUADOR HAS "SEVERELY" RESTRICTED IMPORTS OF CHEMICAL SUBSTANCES USED IN THE PRELIMINARY PHASES OF THE REFINING OF NARCOTICS. FORMER FREE ACCESS TO THOSE SUBSTANCES HAD BEEN CONVERTING THE COUNTRY INTO AN ALTERNATIVE BASE FOR THE PRODUCTION AND SHIPMENT OF DRUGS TO THE UNITED STATES AND WESTERN EUROPE.

TST1-MUC3-0049

POPAYAN, 23 MAR 90 (BOGOTA RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] MEMBERS OF THE 8TH FRONT OF THE SELF-STYLED REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA [FARC] HAVE CARRIED OUT TERRORIST ATTACKS IN SOUTHERN CAUCA DEPARTMENT TO PROTEST PATRIOTIC UNION [UP] PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA'S MURDER.

THE FARC MEMBERS BLEW UP A POWER SUBSTATION AND A POWER PYLON IN SAJANDI, LA FONDA CORREGIMIENTO. THE GUERRILLAS ALSO BURNED THREE VEHICLES ON THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY-- A BALBOA HOSPITAL AMBULANCE, A FUEL TRUCK CARRYING 3,000 GALLONS OF GASOLINE, AND A STATION WAGON. A LARGE SECTION OF EL PATIA VALLEY WAS LEFT WITHOUT ELECTRICITY.

THROUGH SEVERAL TELEPHONE CALLS TO THE POPAYAN MEDIA, THE 8TH FARC FRONT DECLARED THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY A MILITARY TARGET DURING THE NEXT 48 HOURS IN ORDER TO DEMAND THAT THE GOVERNMENT INVESTIGATE AND ARREST THOSE WHO ARE TRULY RESPONSIBLE FOR JARAMILLO'S MURDER.

TRANSPORTATION SERVICES BETWEEN [WORD INDISTINCT] AND PASTO IN SOUTHERN COLOMBIA HAVE BEEN SUSPENDED AS A RESULT OF THE TERRORIST ATTACKS, WHICH BEGAN AT 0300 TODAY.

POLICE AND 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE MEMBERS WERE DEPLOYED TO THE AREAS WHERE THE 8TH FRONT OF THE SELF-STYLED REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA BLOCKED TRAFFIC. THE 8TH FARC FRONT MEMBERS SAID THEIR MILITARY ACTIONS ARE AIMED AT DEMANDING THE CLARIFICATION OF UP PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE BERNARDO JARAMILLO'S MURDER.

THE POPAYAN POLICE DEPARTMENT CONFIRMED THAT THE ATTACKS TOOK PLACE ON THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY AND AT LA FONDA CORREGIMIENTO, PATIA MUNICIPALITY.

GOVERNOR FERNANDO IRACONI SAID THAT THE REGIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL WILL MEET IN POPAYAN IN A FEW MINUTES TO ASSESS THE MOST RECENT TERRORIST ATTACKS AND TO ADOPT THE NECESSARY MEASURES.

TST1-MUC3-0052

BOGOTA, 4 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH NORTH SANTANDER GOVERNOR EDUARDO ASSAF ELCURE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [ASSAF] I BELIEVE THAT HERE IN THE DEPARTMENT, THE EXPERIENCE WITH MAYORS ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE, HAS BEEN SATISFACTORY. MOST OF THEM HAVE BEEN RESPONSIBLE TO THE COMMUNITIES THEY REPRESENT. THEY HAVE BEEN WORKING AND ALL HAVE A FAVORABLE BALANCE. WHY NOT ALLOW CITIZENS TO FREELY AND SPONTANEOUSLY EXCERCISE THE RIGHT TO VOTE AGAIN. THIS WOULD CONTINUE THE DEMOCRATIZATION AND DECENTRALIZATION PROCESS NEEDED BY THE COUNTRY TO PROGRESS AND FIND PEACE. I BELIEVE WE SHOULD TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE WONDERFUL SERVICES RENDERED BY DR. RAFAEL PARDO, THE NATIONAL REHABILITATION PLAN DIRECTOR, TO ATTEMPT TO FIND NEW ROADS TOWARD ACHIEVING DIALOGUE WITH THESE TWO SECTORS, ESPECIALLY WITH THE ELN. IT IS NOT EASY TO FIND PEACE, ESPECIALLY FOR THIS DEPARTMENT. WE MUST AT LEAST MAKE ATTEMPTS TO HOLD DIALOGUE WITH THIS GUERRILLA GROUP, WHICH HAS SHOWN IT CAN EASILY MOVE AROUND AND DISRUPT STABILITY AND PUBLIC ORDER IN THE DEPARTMENT OF NORTH SANTANDER.

[REPORTER] MR. GOVERNOR, UP TO NOW, HAVE ELN OR EPL SUBVERSIVES TRIED TO ATTAIN THIS DIALOGUE?

[ASSAF] WELL, NO. IT HAS NOT BEEN EASY, BESIDES WE BELIEVE THESE ARE INITIATIVES THAT SHOULD BE STARTED BY THE PEACE COMMISSIONERS, AS THEY HAVE EXPERIENCE IN SUCH CONVERSATIONS, CONTACTS, AND DIALOGUES. THAT IS WHY I MENTIONED THAT, PERHAPS, THROUGH DR. RAFAEL PARDO, WHO HAS BEEN THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT'S DELEGATE, ATTEMPTS WILL BE MADE TO SEARCH FOR SUCH POSSIBILITIES. I BELIEVE THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN MAKING EFFORTS TO ATTAIN PEACE IN THE COUNTRY, AND THE QUICKER WE ATTAIN THIS, THE BETTER IT WILL BE FOR THE SECURITY AND STABILITY OF COLOMBIA.

[REPORTER] HAVE YOU ALREADY SENT AN INVITATION OR ASKED DR. RAFAEL PARDO TO COME TO YOUR DEPARTMENT?

[ASSAF] WE HAVE TALKED TO HIM OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS ABOUT THE PUBLIC ORDER SITUATION AND OTHER SITUATIONS THAT REQUIRE SPECIAL ATTENTION. HOWEVER, THE ENTIRE COUNTRY KNOWS THAT DR. PARDO HAS BEEN WORKING VIRTUALLY FULL-TIME TO FURTHER THE PEACE CONVERSATIONS WITH M-19. THE ENTIRE COUNTRY HAS BEEN PLEASED AND VERY HAPPY WITH THESE CONVERSATIONS BECAUSE THEY HAVE BEEN AN IMPORTANT INITIATION FOR PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S PEACE PROCESS.

[REPORTER] BUT DR. RAFAEL PARDO RUEDA DOES NOT DISLIKE THE IDEA OF HOLDING SUCH CONVERSATIONS?

[ASSAF] I AM SURE HE DOES NOT DISLIKE THE IDEA BECAUSE HE HAS BEEN TRYING TO DO THIS FOR A LONG TIME.

[REPORTER] WHEN COULD THESE CONVERSATIONS TAKE PLACE? JUST GIVE US A TENTATIVE DATE. COULD IT BE WITHIN DAYS OR THIS WEEK?

[ASSAF] SURELY THIS WEEK WE WILL AGAIN HAVE TO STUDY THE PUBLIC ORDER SITUATION IN OUR DEPARTMENT AND SURELY WE WILL BE ABLE TO ANALYZE THIS PROPOSAL AGAIN AND I BELIEVE DR. PARDO WILL SERIOUSLY TAKE IT INTO ACCOUNT.

[REPORTER] SOME OF THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL LEADERS -- NOT ONLY IN NORTHERN SANTANDER, BUT IN SEVERAL AREAS OF THE COUNTRY -- ARE VERY CONCERNED ABOUT THE CONSTANT RAIDS BY SUBVERSIVE GROUPS, AND THEIR MURDERED MAYORS, OFFICIALS, AND POLITICAL LEADERS AND THE KIDNAPPING OF NATIONAL CIVIL REGISTRY OFFICE PERSONNEL. THEY INDICATE THAT WITH ACTIONS OF THIS TYPE IT WOULD BE VERY DIFFICULT FOR PEOPLE TO FREELY EXPRESS THEMSELVES BY VOTING IN THE NEXT ELECTIONS.

[ASSAF] YES, SURELY ALL THESE INCIDENTS CAN, IN A CERTAIN MANNER, WEAKEN THE ELECTORAL VOTE. HOWEVER, EVERYDAY WE ARE MORE CONVINCED THAT COLOMBIANS WANT TO EXCERCISE THIS RIGHT WITHOUT ANY TYPE OF LIMITATIONS AND MAKE EFFORTS -- INCLUDING HEROIC ACTIONS -- TO CONTINUE THIS CAMPAIGN SO THAT ELECTIONS CAN BE HELD THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY. VOTING IS THE REAL EXPRESSION OF DEMOCRACY AND WE WILL ALL FIGHT FOR IT. WE ARE SURE THAT THE GOVERNMENT, THROUGH THE ARMED FORCES, WILL DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE FOR THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS TO BE HELD WITHOUT PROBLEMS. HOWEVER, IT IS A HUGE EFFORT, AS IT HAS TO CONFRONT A SERIES OF APPREHENSIONS OR FEARS THAT HAVE BEEN INSTILLED IN SOME PEOPLE. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0053

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE -- [INTERVIEW WITH COMMANDER JORGE MELENDEZ] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [MELENDEZ] COL VARGAS' REACTION WAS TO BECOME DESPERATE BECAUSE 90-MM, 60-MM, AND 81-MM MORTARS, AND 85-MM FIELD GUNS HAVE BEEN INDISCRIMINATELY FIRED AGAINST THAT SECTOR OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD FOR 3 DAYS; ROCKETS HAVE BEEN FIRED FROM AIRPLANES. MANY CIVILIANS HAVE BEEN WOUNDED AND MANY HOUSES HAVE BEEN DESTROYED. IN OTHER WORDS, THERE HAS BEEN NO RESPECT WHATSOEVER -- PERHAPS BECAUSE THOSE NEIGHBORHOODS ARE LOCATED CLOSEST TO THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE, AND THAT SEEMS TO WORRY THIS MAN VERY MUCH. THIS COULD BE THE REASON FOR SUCH AN ATTITUDE AND FOR THAT GENOCIDAL SITUATION.

IN OTHER PLACES, CLASHES OCCURRED PRACTICALLY ALL DAY LONG ON 12 AND 13 NOVEMBER, AND DURING THE EARLY MORNING HOURS OF 14 NOVEMBER IN THE MILAGRO DE LA PAZ NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE WE CAUSED A CONSIDERABLE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES. IN ADDITION, OUR FORCES FOILED AND STOPPED THE ARCE BATTALION, PONCE BATTALION, LEON BATTALION, AND THE MONTERROSA FORCES [78-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] SURVEILLANCE AND SECURITY MEASURES, AND TO HANDLE ANY TYPE OF EMERGENCY, INCLUDING BOMBINGS, MORTAR ATTACKS, AND STRAFINGS. THIS MEANS THAT THE TERRAIN MUST BE PREPARED TO DEFEND THE POPULATION.

WE ALSO HAVE A NUMBER OF INSTRUCTION REGARDING THE TASKS TO BE DONE DURING TIMES OF COMBAT, BUT THIS IS GEARED TOWARD THE POPULATION WHO DECIDES TO PARTICIPATE BY DIRECTLY SUPPORTING THE FMLN. THIS INVOLVES MANY PEOPLE. THEY CAN JOIN NEW FORCES AND GROUPS IN CHARGE OF THE TRENCHES, SECURITY MEASURES, COURIERS, AND ALL KINDS OF TASKS TO SUPPORT THE WAR.

IN SUM, THE INSTRUCTIONS TO THE POPULATION ARE TO ORGANIZE THEMSELVES BECAUSE, ONCE ORGANIZED, THEY CAN GIVE [4-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] AND COUNTER IT. THE OTHER ISSUE IS THE CALLS TO THE POPULATION TO PARTICIPATE IN THE STRUGGLE AND ABOVE ALL [7-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] NOT TO LET ANYONE INTIMIDATE THEM. THEY SHOULD NOT LET ANYONE STOP THEM FROM GOING OUT TO PURCHASE THEIR FOOD AND WHATEVER ELSE THEY NEED.

GIVEN THE EMERGENCY SITUATION AND THE SHORTAGE OF MEDICINE AND FOOD, WE THINK IT IS NECESSARY FOR THE PEOPLE OF SAN MIGUEL TO OPEN THE STORES WHERE THEY CAN GET FOOD, MEDICINE, AND ANY OTHER ITEMS WHICH ARE URGENTLY NEEDED FOR THEIR [WORD INDISTINCT] AND SURVIVAL. THAT IS ALL FOR NOW. GREETINGS TO THE COMRADES WHO ARE LISTENING IN THE CAPITAL, ALL THE COMRADE FIGHTERS, AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE IN GENERAL. THEIR HIGH MORALE AND ACTIVE ROLE IN THE CAPITAL MAKES US FEEL PROUD. WE HAVE SEEN THAT THE VICTORY IS GUARANTEED. WE ARE PREPARED TO DO LIKEWISE AND WE SEND THEM THE COURAGEOUS, FRATERNAL, AND REVOLUTIONARY GREETINGS FROM ALL THE COMMANDERS AND FIGHTERS IN SAN MIGUEL.

TST1-MUC3-0054

LIMA, 15 AUG 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [SPEECH] [PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA] [TEXT] GOOD EVENING. THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN IS NOW UNDER WAY. TEN CANDIDATES ARE RUNNING FOR MAYOR OF LIMA. WE MUST PARTICIPATE IN THE ELECTIONS TO PRESERVE DEMOCRACY IN OUR COUNTRY.

HOWEVER, THE ELECTORAL ATMOSPHERE THAT PREVAILS SHOULD NOT MAKE US FORGET OUR MOST SERIOUS PROBLEM, THE GREATEST THREAT TO OUR FATHERLAND. THIS THREAT IS TERRORISM WHICH COSTS LIVES, INFLICTS ECONOMIC HARM, FOSTERS INSECURITY, AND CUTS OFF THE POWER THAT WE NEED FOR OUR HOMES AND OUR INDUSTRIES.

WE CONTINUE TO BATTLE TERRORISM. THE ARMED FORCES AND THE NATIONAL POLICE ARE TAKING DRASTIC ACTION IN THE HUALLAGA VALLEY AND IN THE MOUNTAIN RANGE. THEY ARE ALSO BREAKING UP URBAN TERRORIST CELLS. HOWEVER, WE MUST ALSO ATTACK TERRORISTS THROUGH LEGAL ACTIONS, THROUGH THE MOST DRASTIC AND SEVERE SENTENCES.

IRRESPECTIVE OF MILITARY ACTIONS, IF NO SWIFT AND DRASTIC LEGAL PUNISHMENT IS METED, THE TERRORISTS KNOW THAT THEY WILL GO UNPUNISHED. STIMULATED BY THIS THEY CONTINUE WITH THEIR CRIMES.

THE WHOLE COUNTRY IS AWARE OF THIS. MOST PERUVIANS WANT SEVERE, DRASTIC AND EFFECTIVE PUNISHMENT FOR TERRORISTS. THUS, ON 28 JULY I PROPOSED TO THE NATIONAL CONGRESS THAT THE MILITARY COURTS SHOULD TRY TERRORISTS. TONIGHT, I WOULD LIKE TO REMIND YOU OF THIS SUBJECT BECAUSE I AM CONCERNED THAT IT MAY REMAIN JUST THAT; A PROPOSAL. I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO ASK ALL PERUVIANS, ALL ORGANIZATIONS AND INSTITUTIONS, TO SUPPORT THIS REQUEST WHICH WILL BE DISCUSSED IN CONGRESS.

BY HAVING TERRORISTS TRIED BY MILITARY COURTS WE ARE NOT GIVING UP ANY CIVILIAN PREROGATIVES. WE ARE NOT GIVING UP ANY DEMOCRATIC RIGHTS. THIS HAS BEEN DONE BEFORE IN OTHER DEMOCRATIC COUNTRIES.

FURTHERMORE, THE ARMED FORCES ARE AN ESSENTIAL COMPONENT OF PERU'S DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM. THEY ARE ALSO THE ONES THAT ACTUALLY FIGHT THE BATTLE AGAINST SUBVERSION. NO ONE CAN SAY THAT SETTING UP MILITARY COURTS IS TANTAMOUNT TO MILITARIZING THE COUNTRY BECAUSE THAT WOULD IMPLY DISTRUSTING THE ARMED FORCES, OFFENDING THEM AND OVERLOOKING THE FACT THAT THEY ARE DEFENDING DEMOCRACY. MORE THAN 2 YEARS AGO WE ASKED FOR AND WERE ALLOWED TO ESTABLISH SPECIAL COURTS TO TERRORIST CASES. SO FAR THESE COURTS HAVE YIELDED NO POSITIVE RESULTS. THUS, AS PRESIDENT IT IS MY DUTY TO CALL FOR SEVERE SENTENCES, ISSUED WITHOUT DELAY OR ANY THEORETICAL OR ACADEMIC DISCUSSIONS.

FOLLOWING MY 28 JULY SPEECH I ASCERTAINED THAT THE VAST MAJORITY OF PERUVIANS ARE IN FAVOR OF DRASTIC PUNISHMENTS AND OF THE ESTABLISHMENT OF MILITARY COURTS. I HAVE ALSO HEARD SOME LEGAL OBJECTIONS AND THEORETICAL ARGUMENTS AGAINST THIS MEASURE.

THOSE WHO DO NOT WANT THE MILITARY COURTS TO TRY TERRORISTS SAY THAT ARTICLE 282 OF THE CONSTITUTION DOES NOT ALLOW IT. THIS IS HALF TRUE. ARTICLE 282 STATES: IN CASES OF CRIMES COMMITTED WHILE ON DUTY, POLICE AND ARMED FORCES MEMBERS ARE SUBJECT TO THE MILITARY JURISDICTION AND TO THE MILITARY CODE OF JUSTICE WHICH IS NOT APPLICABLE TO CIVILIANS EXCEPT IN THE CASE DESCRIBED BY ARTICLE 235, WHICH ESTABLISHES THE APPLICATION OF THE DEATH SENTENCE IN CASE OF BETRAYAL OF THE MOTHERLAND DURING WAR.

NOW, THOSE WHO DO NOT WANT MILITARY COURTS TO TRY TERRORISTS DO NOT WANT TO READ THE SECOND PART OF ARTICLE 282 WHICH STATES: THOSE WHO AVOID COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE ARE SUBJECT TO THE MILITARY CODE OF JUSTICE. THIS PARAGRAPH IS THE ONE THAT LEGALLY AND CONSTITUTIONALLY ALLOWS US TO TRY TERRORISTS UNDER THE MILITARY JURISDICTION, BECAUSE TERRORISTS ALSO VIOLATE THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE LAW WHEN THEY COMMIT CRIMES.

MANY PERUVIANS WRONGFULLY THINK THAT THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE ONLY AFFECTS MEN ON ACTIVE SERVICE, LIKE THOSE PERUVIANS WHO, AFTER A SELECTION ARE SENT TO SERVE IN A MILITARY GARRISON FOR 1 OR 2 YEARS. THIS IS ONLY ONE OF THE WAYS IN WHICH ONE COMPLIES WITH THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE.

THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE LAW STATES IN ARTICLE 2: THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE IN AN UNAVOIDABLE DUTY OF ALL PERUVIANS WHO MUST PARTICIPATE IN NATIONAL DEFENSE BY COMPLYING WITH THEIR MILITARY OBLIGATIONS. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0055

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] MOREOVER, THE CONSERVATIVE INTER-AMERICAN PRESS ASSOCIATION HAS CONDEMNED CRISTIANI BECAUSE OF THE CENSORSHIP, THE DISINFORMATION NETWORK, AND THE PERSECUTION AGAINST LOCAL AND FOREIGN JOURNALISTS AND THE FEDERATION OF LATIN AMERICAN JOURNALISTS HAS JUST DONE THE SAME. THE GROUP OF EIGHT, WHICH IS THE MOST INFLUENTIAL LATIN AMERICAN GROUP, HAS CRITICIZED CRISTIANI'S REJECTION OF A CEASE-FIRE, WHICH WAS REQUESTED BY THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND INCLUDED BY THE FMLN IN ITS LATEST POLITICAL PROPOSAL. IN ADDITION, THE GROUP OF EIGHT HAS DESCRIBED CRISTIANI'S REJECTION OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS MEETING, SCHEDULED FOR MANAGUA, AS A POLITICAL OUTBOURST.

CRISTIANI'S SITUATION IN THE UNITED STATES IS BECOMING DRAMATIC. THE BIPARTISAN CONSENSUS THAT SUPPORTED MILITARY AID HAS BOKEN UP. THE U.S. PRESS IS INCREASINGLY CRITICAL OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES. PROTEST DEMONSTRATIONS ARE MULTIPLYING. PERSONALITIES LIKE JESSE JACKSON ARE DEMANDING AND END TO AID FOR CRISTIANI. TO THIS MUST BE ADDED THE RECENT STATEMENT, IN SIMILAR TERMS, OF THE BISHOPS OF ALL U.S. CHURCHES. THE SCENES OF THE U.S. PERSONNEL'S DEPARTURE FROM SAN [13-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] $4 BILLION TO THAT COUNTRY'S TREASURY AND 70,000 DEATHS TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

SERIOUS QUESTIONS ARE BEING RAISED NOW ABOUT BUSH'S FOREIGN POLICY. THE IMAGE OF A TERRORIST, FANATICAL FMLN WHICH SOME POWERFUL U.S. SECTORS HAD [11-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] AND MOST RECENTLY IN ESCALON. THE U.S. PRESS HAS BEGUN TALKING ABOUT AN FMLN THAT SHOWS STATESMANSHIP IN ITS ACTIONS AND AS A RATIONAL AND SENSIBLE POLITICAL AND MILITARY FORCE WITH WHICH RELATIONS OF EQUALITY AND RESPECT CAN BE ESTABLISHED TO FIND POLITICAL SOLUTIONS AND TO AVOID A REGIONALIZATION AND DEEPENING OF THE CONFLICT.

TO ACHIEVE DEMOCRATIZATION, TO ENFORCE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, THERE HAD TO BE [5-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] AND WE HAVE SUCCEEDED. THIS IS THE FIRST IMPORTANT ACHIEVEMENT, WHICH ADDS TO THE MANY GAINS DURING THE NATIONWIDE OFFENSIVE FOR PEACE AGAINST THOSE WHO HAVE TURNED WAR INTO A BUSINESS.

WE ACHIEVED IN 10 DAYS WHAT THE WORLD TOOK 10 DAYS TO UNDERSTAND. SALVADORANS, WE ARE STRONGER NOW THAN EVER. THE OFFENSIVE CONTINUES BUILDING VICTORY.

TST1-MUC3-0056

SAN SALVADOR, 2 MAY 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] AT LEAST 18 CASUALTIES, AMONG BOTH SOLDIERS AND CIVILIANS, RESULTED FROM SEVERAL GUERRILLA ATTACKS ON THE PRESIDENT'S RESIDENCE, THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL, AND OTHER MILITARY INSTALLATIONS IN SAN SALVADOR AND SEVERAL DEPARTMENTS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) REPORTED THAT FOUR ARMY MEMBERS, INCLUDING TWO OFFICERS, WERE KILLED AND SIX SOLDIERS WERE WOUNDED IN CLASHES IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

THE TWO DEAD OFFICERS WERE IDENTIFIED AS CAPTAIN JOSE ALFONSO CHAVEZ AND LIEUTENANT BOLANOS OF THE TREASURY POLICE.

A TREASURY POLICE MEMBER WAS KILLED IN A REBEL ATTACK IN SAN MIGUEL, THE COUNTRY'S THIRD LARGEST CITY, EARLY THIS MORNING.

THE ATTACKS BEGAN AT 2100 (0300 GMT) ON 1 MAY AND CONTINUED AFTER MIDNIGHT, ALARMING CITIZENS IN SAN SALVADOR AND CAUSING BLACKOUTS.

FURTHERMORE, THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS REPORTED THAT EIGHT MINORS WERE WOUNDED IN TWO CLASHES BETWEEN GUERRILLA FORCES AND SOLDIERS IN ILOBASCO, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, AND USULUTAN, LOCATED IN THE SOUTHEAST AREA OF THE COUNTRY.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN SAID THAT THE GUERRILLA FORCES ATTACKED THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE, THE SHERATON HOTEL'S SECURITY CORPS, PUBLIC WORKS MINISTER MAURICIO STUBIG'S RESIDENCE, AND THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL.

THE COPREFA REPORTED THAT THERE WAS PROPERTY DAMAGE BUT NO CASUALTIES IN THESE PLACES.

MILITARY REPORTS ADDED THAT A CIVIL DEFENSE MEMBER WAS WOUNDED IN A REBEL HARASSMENT OF THE CIVIL DEFENSE GROUP IN THE TOWN OF YUCUAYQUIN, EASTERN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT.

ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY SOURCES, THE TOWNS OF JOCORO AND GUADALUPE WERE ALSO ATTACKED BY THE REBELS, BUT THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES REPORTED IN THESE ATTACKS.

TST1-MUC3-0058

SAN SALVADOR, 15 OCT 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, THE GOVERNMENT HAS RECEIVED REPORTS, WHICH HE DESCRIBED AS DISTURBING, THAT THE REBELS ARE PLANNING TO UNLEASH AN OFFENSIVE IN THE CAPITAL CITY ON THE VERY DAY WHEN PEACE TALKS ARE SCHEDULED TO BEGIN IN COSTA RICA. GOVERNMENT REPORTS SUGGEST THAT THE INSURGENTS WILL NOT ONLY STEP UP THEIR ACTIONS TO DESTROY THE ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURE AND MURDER GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, BUT ALSO THREATEN TO USE GROUND-TO-AIR MISSILES AGAINST THE CITY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] ALTHOUGH THE PEACE PROCESS IS UNDER WAY, WE HAVE RECEIVED REPORTS THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] COMMAND HAS AUTHORIZED A PLAN TO STEP UP VIOLENCE IN SAN SALVADOR THROUGH THE USE OF GROUND-TO-AIR MISSILES.

WE BELIEVE THAT THIS SHOWS ABSOLUTELY NO WILLINGNESS TO BRING ABOUT PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY. THE MEDIA SHOULD REVEAL TO ALL SALVADORANS AND THE ENTIRE WORLD WHAT THE FMLN IS PLANNING TO DO. [END RECORDING]

ACCORDING TO THE PRESIDENT, THESE FMLN PLANS DO NOT CONTRIBUTE TO THE PEACE PROCESS THAT BEGAN IN SEPTEMBER IN MEXICO. WHEN ASKED WHETHER THESE ACTIONS PLANNED BY THE FMLN COULD HARM THE TALKS IN COSTA RICA, CRISTIANI SAID THAT THIS WILL DEPEND ON THE SITUATION THAT PREVAILS AT THE MEETING. HE ADDED THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT OPPOSES THE USE OF THE TALKS FOR TACTICAL PURPOSES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] IF THE FMLN WANTS TO USE THE PROCESS FOR TACTICAL PURPOSES, WE WILL NOT LEND OURSELVES TO THEIR GAME. OUR OBJECTIVE HAS BEEN TO SEEK PEACE IN GOOD WILL. HOWEVER, I REPEAT, WE WILL NOT LEND OURSELVES TO A FMLN TACTICAL GAME. I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT WE CAN MAKE ANY PREDICTIONS AT THIS MOMENT. THE OUTCOME WILL DEPEND ON THESE ALLEGED PLANS AND DEVELOPMENTS IN COSTA RICA. [END RECORDING]

AN END TO THE HOSTILITIES WILL BE DISCUSSED IN THIS ROUND OF TALKS. THUS, THIS MEETING COULD BE CRUCIAL FOR ACHIEVING NATIONAL PEACE. CRISTIANI MAINTAINED THAT THIS MEETING WILL BE USEFUL TO GAUGE THE INTENTIONS OF THE GUERRILLA FRONT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE WILL PRESENT A GOVERNMENT PROPOSAL. IT IS AN BROAD PROPOSAL BECAUSE IT DEALS WITH VARIOUS ISSUES, EVEN THE POSSIBLE INCORPORATION OF THE FMLN TO CIVILIAN AND DEMOCRATIC LIFE. IT SPECIFICALLY DEALS WITH AN END TO THE HOSTILITIES, A TOPIC THAT WE HAD AGREED TO ADDRESS IN COSTA RICA DURING OUR MEETING IN MEXICO. WE ARE WILLING TO DISCUSS ANY TOPIC THAT IS WITHIN OUR CONSTITUTIONAL FRAMEWORK FOR THE SAKE OF DEMOCRACY. [END RECORDING]

THE PRESIDENT DESCRIBED AS BENEFICIAL THE UN AND OAS PRESENCE AT THE TALKS, BECAUSE THEY WILL GUARANTEE COMPLIANCE WITH THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED IN COSTA RICA.

ONLY A DAY BEFORE THE BEGINNING OF THE TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN, THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT DESPITE AN INCREASE IN WAR ACTIONS, THE MEETING IN COSTA RICA WILL NOT FACE OBSTACLES.

TST1-MUC3-0059

SAN SALVADOR, 9 JUN 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [ERNESTO RIVAS] [TEXT] PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HOLDS THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF DR JOSE ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH AND CALLED THE ATTACK AN ATTEMPT TO HINDER DIALOGUE. THE PRESIDENT HAS ORDERED 3 DAYS OF NATIONAL MOURNING IN HONOR OF THE SLAIN MINISTER.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE ARE GOING TO RESPOND LEGALLY. WE WILL IMMEDIATELY BEGIN THE REQUISITE EXHAUSTIVE INVESTIGATIONS TO FIND AND PUNISH THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR A CRIME AGAINST THE LIFE OF AN EXEMPLARY CITIZEN. [END RECORDING]

PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BLAMED THE FMLN FOR MINISTER RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S DEATH. HE SAID THIS ATTACK IS PART OF A SERIES OF ACTIONS AIMED AT DESTABILIZING THE NEW GOVERNMENT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE ARE VIRTUALLY CONVINCED THAT THIS WAS AN FMLN EFFORT, AN FMLN INCIDENT, TO TRY AND PROVOKE A REACTION FROM OUR GOVERNMENT. WE FEEL THAT THE INVESTIGATIONS WILL UNDOUBTEDLY SHOW US WHO IS TO BLAME FOR THIS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT; HOWEVER, I REPEAT WE ARE ALMOST SURE THAT THIS WAS DONE BY THE FMLN.

WE HAD HOPED THE FMLN WOULD REFRAIN FROM THIS TYPE OF BARBARIC ACTION; HOWEVER, IT IS THE DUTY OF THE ARMED FORCES AND THE SECURITY CORPS TO OFFER PROTECTION. THIS IS WHY THEY HAVE BEEN DEPLOYED: TO OFFER GREATER SAFETY AND PROTECTION TO THE PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

DURING THIS EVENING'S RADIO VENCEREMOS NEWSCAST, HOWEVER, THE REBELS NEITHER CLAIMED NOR DENIED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK. NEVERTHELESS, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID THE ASSASSINATION MAY HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT BY THE FMLN IN AN ATTEMPT TO HINDER THE DIALOGUE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE HAD LEARNED, EVEN BEFORE THE INAUGURATION, THAT THE FMLN WOULD TRY TO HINDER THE TRANSITION FROM ONE GOVERNMENT TO ANOTHER AND LATER CREATE ANARCHIC SITUATIONS FOR THE NEW GOVERNMENT. THIS COULD BE PART OF THAT PLAN.

I ALSO FEEL THAT THIS COULD BE THE FMLN'S WAY TO FORCE US TO SIT DOWN AND TALK. IT WOULD BE REGRETTABLE THAT AFTER RECEIVING A FORMAL OFFER TO SIT DOWN TO TALK -- FIRST ABOUT THE MECHANISMS TO BE USED AS GUIDELINES DURING THE TALKS AND LATER TO BROACH THE MAIN ISSUES IN AN ATTEMPT TO REACH A LASTING PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY -- THE FMLN SHOULD STILL THINK THAT SUCH ACTIONS ARE NECESSARY. I THINK THEY ARE ONLY TRYING TO DISRUPT THE NEW GOVERNMENT'S WORK. [END RECORDING]

DURING THIS EVENING'S NEWS CONFERENCE, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID THAT DURING TODAY'S CABINET MEETING IT WAS DECIDED TO ASK THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY TO DECREE 3 DAYS OF MOURNING FOR DR RODRIGUEZ PORTH.

TST1-MUC3-0060

BOGOTA, 27 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [SPEECH] [CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO, LIBERAL PARTY PRESIDENT-ELECT] [TEXT] THIS IS A NIGHT OF HAPPINESS FOR ALL OF MY FAMILY, FOR ALL OF THOSE WHO WITH THEIR DEDICATION AND THEIR WORK HAVE ACCOMPANIED ME IN THIS DIFFICULT MOMENT OF COLOMBIAN LIFE. I HAVE, DEEP IN MY THOUGHTS, MY CAMPAIGN COMPANIONS, MY DEBATE LEADERS, ALL THOSE WHO FILLED EVERY MOMENT WITH DEDICATION AND ENTHUSIASM, WHICH I HOPE TO DESERVE. I HAVE PRESENT THE UNIVERSITY YOUTH, STAUNCH STANDARD-BEARERS OF THE CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY [APPLAUSE]; ALL OF MY PARTY LEADERS, SERVANTS OF THE LIBERAL CAUSE WHO SHOWED STEADFAST LOYALTY; GRASSROOTS LEADERS FROM ALL PARTS OF COLOMBIA; AND THE PEOPLE, WHOSE DECISION COMMITS ME BEYOND ANY DOUBT.

I WANT TO OFFER THIS VICTORY TO GLORIA, JUAN MANUEL, AND HIS BROTHERS [APPLAUSE], AND TO LUIS CARLOS GALAN'S PARENTS -- MARIO AND CECILIA -- WHO ACCOMPANIED HIM IN HIS LONG HEROIC JOURNEY THROUGH COLOMBIAN LIFE. THIS IS HIS VICTORY, A VICTORY FOR HIS CHILDREN, HIS IDEALS, HIS FAITH IN COLOMBIA, AND THE LIBERAL PRINCIPLES THAT INSPIRED HIS LIFE.

I ALSO THINK OF MY MOTHER; MY BROTHERS; ANA MILENA [APPLAUSE], MY WIFE AND COMPANION AT ALL TIMES AND DURING SLEEPLESS NIGHTS; AND MY CHILDREN SIMON AND MARIA PAZ. [APPLAUSE]

TODAY COLOMBIA HAS COMPLETED THE MOST DIFFICULT AND RUGGED POLITICAL CAMPAIGN IN ALL ITS HISTORY. ITS VALUES, ITS DEMOCRACY, AND ITS LIBERTY WERE AT STAKE AS NEVER BEFORE. AS NEVER BEFORE, THE PROMOTERS OF VIOLENCE FROM ALL SIDES TRIED TO DESTABILIZE OUR INSTITUTIONS. HOWEVER, COLOMBIANS, ALSO AS NEVER BEFORE, STOOD UP TO THE HISTORIC MOMENT WE FACED. THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE'S POWERFUL DEMOCRATIC DETERMINATION WAS STRONGER. CONVINCED OF THE IMPORTANCE OF THE CURRENT HOUR, THEY WENT OUT TO SUPPORT WITH MILLIONS OF VOTES DEMOCRACY THAT HAS HAD TO FACE BOMBS, NARCOTERRORISM, AND HATEFUL PRACTICES.

ALL THOSE WHO HAVE WANTED TO THREATEN OUR DEMOCRACY MUST LISTEN: OUR PEOPLE HAVE SPOKEN TODAY WITH COURAGE AND CLARITY. WE SHALL PREVAIL. IT HAS BEEN A CONSCIENTIOUS, BOLD MOBILIZATION BY MILLIONS OF COLOMBIANS WHO HAVE EXPRESSED THEIR POLITICAL WILL FOR THE FIRST TIME THROUGH A SYSTEM WITHOUT PRESSURE OR INTIMIDATION. ONCE AGAIN, TODAY, AS ON 11 MARCH, CITIZENS VOTED AS THEY WISHED.

THIS DIFFICULT AND RUGGED CAMPAIGN HAS NOT BEEN CHARACTERIZED BY A CRUDE CONFRONTATION AMONG CANDIDATES, WHO ACTED WITH DECENCY AND LOYALTY. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0061

BOGOTA, 25 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA ALIAS "THE MEXICAN," A WELL-KNOWN COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKER WHO IS ONE OF THE DRUG LORDS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL HAS ADMITTED THAT HE IS IN FAVOR OF "CEASING OFFENSIVE ACTIONS AGAINST THE MILITARY FORCES."

IN A LETTER TO THE OPPOSITION'S DAILY LA PRENSA EDITED IN BOGOTA, HE STRESSED THAT "THE MISSION EACH ONE OF US HAS AS COLOMBIAN CITIZENS IS TRYING TO RESTORE PEACE IN COLOMBIA."

RODRIGUEZ GACHA, WHO ALONG WITH PABLO ESCOBAR HAVE BECOME THE COUNTRY'S MOST WANTED MEN, DENIED HAVING PROPOSED AN ALLIANCE WITH THE COMMUNIST GUERRILLAS OF THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC).

ONLY 1 WEEK AGO, LA PRENSA REPORTED THAT RODRIGUEZ GACHA HAD PROPOSED AN ALLIANCE WITH THE FARC IN ORDER TO FACE THE WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING DECLARED BY LIBERAL PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO IN MID-AUGUST.

"THE TRUTH IS THAT THERE IS NO SUCH LETTER," SAID THE "CAPO" FOR WHOSE HEAD -- ALONG WITH PABLO ESCOBAR -- COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES HAVE OFFERED A REWARD OF 100 MILLION PESOS (APPROXIMATELY $250,000).

RODRIGUEZ GACHA ALSO RECALLED HIS STRUGGLE AGAINST THE FARC.

TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE OCCASION, THE DRUG TRAFFICKER REJECTED ALL INFORMATION THAT STATING THAT HE IS THE "ACKNOWLEDGED PERPETRATOR OF ALL CRIMES AGAINST PATRIOTIC UNION LEADERS (UP)." HE ADDED THAT ALTHOUGH HE WAS CHARGED WITH THE MURDER OF JAIME PARDO LEAL "THE COURT'S VERDICT WAS FAVORABLE TO ME."

PARDO LEAL WAS THE FOUNDER AND FIRST PRESIDENT OF UP. UP WAS FORMED IN 1984, DURING A TRUCE SIGNED BETWEEN FARC AND THE THEN SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PRESIDENT BELISARIO BETANCUR. ACCORDING TO GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, PARDO LEAL WAS MURDERED BY TWO PAID ASSASSINS WHO RECEIVED ORDERS FROM "EL MEXICANO" ON 11 OCTOBER 1987.

RODRIGUEZ GACHA ARGUED: "NOBODY HAS BEEN CHASED WITH SUCH FIERCENESS IN COLOMBIA BEFORE AS I HAVE." HE ADDED: "IT SEEMS THAT ALL THE ARTICLES OF THE PENAL CODE HAVE BEEN THROWN AT ME AND MY DETRACTORS ARE NOT BINDED BY ANY OF THESE NORMS."

AFTER HE INSISTED THAT OFFENSIVES AGAINST THE COLOMBIAN ARMED FORCES SHOULD STOP, RODRIGUEZ GACHA NOTED THAT THOSE WHO DISTURB PUBLIC ORDER "SHOULD DEFINITELY STOP USING WEAPONS."

"THESE ARE THE FIRST STEPS THAT ARE NEEDED TO GET COLOMBIANS TO SIT AT A NEGOTIATING TABLE WITHOUT EXCLUDING ANYONE," HE CONCLUDED.

VIRGILIO BARCO'S GOVERNMENT HAS REJECTED ALL POSSIBILITY OF DIALOGUE WITH THE DRUG MAFIAS.

TST1-MUC3-0062

BOGOTA, 1 FEB 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) HAS ANNOUNCED IN A COMMUNIQUE SENT TO ANTONIO ROLDAN BETANCUR, GOVERNOR OF THE NORTHWESTERN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, THAT IT REJECTS THE PEACE PLAN PROPOSED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THAT IT WILL CONTINUE ARMED ATTACKS, IT WAS LEARNED A FEW HOURS AGO.

ACCORDING TO INITIAL REPORTS, THE ARMED MOVEMENT--THE MOST RADICAL OF THE GUERRILLA GROUPS IN THE COUNTRY--SENT THE MESSAGE THROUGH LUIS MESA PUERTA, A POLICE INSPECTOR OF EL TIGRE, WHO WAS KIDNAPED LAST FRIDAY FOR THIS PURPOSE.

ROLDAN BETANCUR DID NOT DISCLOSE ANY MORE DETAILS AND MERELY CONFIRMED THAT THE CASTROITE ELN, WHICH HAS STAGED SEVERAL DYNAMITE ATTACKS AGAINST OIL INSTALLATIONS, DID NOT ACCEPT THE PROPOSAL MADE BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS' GOVERNMENT.

MEANWHILE, THE M-19 SENT A LETTER A FEW HOURS AGO TO MISAEL PASTRANA BORRERO, A FORMER PRESIDENT AND MEMBER OF THE OPPOSITION SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PARTY (PSC), REQUESTING THAT HIS PARTY ACTIVELY PARTICIPATE IN A NEW PEACE INITIATIVE THAT FORMALLY BEGAN THE 2D WEEK OF JANUARY.

AT THAT TIME, ON BEHALF OF THE GOVERNMENT, RAFAEL PARDO RUEDA--THE PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER FOR PEACE--AND THE TOP M-19 COMMANDER, CARLOS PIZARRO LEON GOMEZ, SIGNED A PRELIMINARY AGREEMENT THAT CONTEMPLATES THE BEGINNING OF A DIRECT DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GUERRILLA GROUPS AND SPOKESMEN OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES REPRESENTED IN PARLIAMENT.

HOWEVER, THE FARC, WHICH DECLARED A UNILATERAL TRUCE TO FACILIATE THE BEGINNING OF THE CONVERSATIONS, SAID THAT THESE AGREEMENTS WERE "EXCLUSIVE," AS THEY WERE SIGNED BY ONLY ONE OF THE COUNTRY'S REBEL MOVEMENTS.

THE DOCUMENT SIGNED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE M-19 SPECIFIES THAT THE TASKS WITH ALL THE REBEL ORGANIZATIONS ARE CONDUCTED THROUGH THE SIMON BOLIVAR NATIONAL GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD (CNGSB). HOWEVER, WITH THE ELN ANNOUNCEMENT, A JOINT AGREEMENT HAS BEEN RULED OUT.

MEANWHILE, PRIOR TO LEAVING TODAY FOR CARACAS WHERE HE WILL ATTEND THE INAUGURATION OF CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, THE PRESIDENT HELD A MEETING WITH THE CHIEFS OF THE TWO TRADITIONAL PARTIES, FORMER PRESIDENTS JULIO CESAR TURBAY OF THE RULING LIBERAL PARTY, AND PASTRANA BORRERO, OF THE PSC.

THE MEETING HELD AT THE NARINO PALACE (SEAT OF THE GOVERNMENT) WAS CALLED SO THAT BARCO VARGAS COULD REPORT TO THE PSC ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE MOST RECENT EVENTS CONCERNING THE NEW PEACE PROCESS THAT BEGAN WITH THE M-19.

ACCORDING TO SOME POLITICAL CIRCLES, IN THIS MANNER THE PATH TOWARD PEACE MIGHT BE CLEARED, INASMUCH AS ONE OF THE "RESERVATIONS" THE PSC HAD WAS THAT THE BARCO VARGAS GOVERNMENT DID NOT CONSULT WITH THE PARTIES ON THE NEGOTIATIONS.

TST1-MUC3-0064

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] IN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT THERE ARE ALSO CRIMINALS LIKE VICE PRESIDENT MERINO, A MAN WHO HAS PERSONALLY PARTICIPATED IN CRIMES AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AGAINST THE SALVADORAN [WORD INDISTINCT]. THERE IS ALSO D'AUBUISSON, WHO IS ANOTHER ASSASSIN WHO HAS PARTICIPATED IN CRIMES AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

NICARAGUA IS GOING TO DEMAND PUNISHMENT FOR THE ASSASSINS OF PRIESTS AND OF SALVADORAN PEOPLE FROM THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. IT WILL DEMAND THAT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY BREAK RELATIONS WITH EL SALVADOR AND THAT IT TAKE MEASURES AGAINST THAT CRIMINAL GOVERNMENT UNTIL IT STOPS THE BOMBINGS AND THE CRIMES AND IT PUNISHES THE CRIMINALS.

WHAT WE ARE INTERESTED IN IS PEACE AND DEMOCRACY, BUT NOT THE PEACE OF GRAVEYARDS. THERE IS PEACE IN CEMETERIES [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THAT IS THE PEACE THEY WANT FOR EL SALVADOR, THE PEACE OF GRAVEYARDS. THEY WANT TO TURN EL SALVADOR INTO A CEMETERY. IN OTHER WORDS, [WORDS INDISTINCT]. HOWEVER, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE COURAGEOUS. THEY ARE HEROIC PEOPLE WHO KNOW HOW TO FIGHT. THEY HAVE BEEN SHOWING THIS. THEY HAVE GREAT [WORDS INDISTINCT].

WE ARE GOING TO CONTINUE STRUGGLING IN THE INTERNATIONAL SPHERE TO ACHIEVE PEACE. IT IS NOT WE NICARAGUANS, IT IS NOT I BREAKING THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENTS. I WILL CONTINUE TO DEFEND THEM SO THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT WILL ABIDE BY THEM, BECAUSE HUMAN RIGHTS MUST BE RESPECTED. ON 7 AUGUST 1987, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SIGNED AN AGREEMENT SAYING THAT IT WAS GOING TO RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, AND IT IS NOT ABIDING BY THAT AGREEMENT. IT HAS TO COMPLY WITH THAT AGREEMENT EVEN IF IT WITHDRAWS FROM THE PEACE TALKS, EVEN IF IT DOES NOT WANT TO PARTICIPATE IN THE MEETINGS OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS.

WE ARE ALSO GOING TO CONTINUE STRUGGLING IN THE INTERNATIONAL SPHERE, IN THE UNITED NATIONS, SO THAT AN AGREEMENT WILL BE REACHED TO COMPLY WITH THE REMOVAL OF THE CONTRAS FROM HONDURAS. IF THE CONTRAS DO NOT WANT TO LEAVE HONDURAS, WELL, WHAT HAS BEEN SHOWN ON THIS BORDER, IN THESE HEROIC TOWNS OF [NAME INDISTINCT], VILLANUEVA, SOMOTILLO, [NAME INDISTINCT], SAN PEDRO, SAN BENITO, SAN FRANCISCO, AND SANTO TOMAS? ALL THOSE NAMES ARE KNOWN IN THE WORLD FOR THE HEROIC BATTLES WHICH HAVE BEEN WAGED THERE TO REJECT THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES WHO HAVE RECEIVED ALL TYPES OF SUPPORT FROM THE YANKEES. THE YANKEES HAVE GIVEN THE CONTRAS ALL TYPES OF ARMAMENTS, INCLUDING MORE THAN 300 SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES.

WE ARE GOING TO ACHIEVE PEACE BECAUSE THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE WANT PEACE. THE TOWNS IN NORTHERN NICARAGUA WANT PEACE. THEY WANT PEACE. DO YOU WANT PEACE? [CROWD SHOUTS: "YES!"] OR DO YOU WANT WAR? [CROWD SHOUTS: "NO!"] DO YOU WANT PEACE? [CROWD SHOUTS: "YES!"] [QUESTION AND ANSWER REPEATED TWO MORE TIMES] WE ARE GOING TO ACHIEVE PEACE. WE ARE GOING TO ACHIEVE TOTAL PEACE BY ALWAYS VIGOROUSLY FIGHTING THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES AND DEFEATING THE YANKEES IN THE ELECTIONS ON 25 FEBRUARY 1990. [APPLAUSE] WE ARE GOING TO THROW SHOVELFULS OF DIRT AT THE CONTRAS AND THE YANKEES ON 25 FEBRUARY 1990, BECAUSE THE YANKEES HAVE CREATED WHAT IS CALLED THE UNO. IT IS A MIXTURE OF PEOPLE WHO ARE [WORDS INDISTINCT]. IT IS A SALAD BUT WITH ROTTEN FRUIT. [APPLAUSE, LAUGHTER] IT IS A SALAD WITH ROTTEN FRUIT. WHO CAN EAT A SALAD WITH ROTTEN FRUIT? CAN YOU BE DECEIVED [WORDS INDISTINCT]? THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE ARE GOING TO SHOW ON 25 FEBRUARY THEIR DESIRE FOR PEACE AND DEMOCRACY AND THEIR SUPPORT FOR THE PLANS OF THE REVOLUTION. THESE ARE GOING TO BE ELECTIONS BETWEEN NICARAGUA AND THE YANKEES. THE CANDIDATES ARE GOING TO BE BUSH ON THE ONE SIDE AND DANIEL ON THE OTHER. THOSE ARE THE CANDIDATES. WHO ARE THE PEOPLE GOING TO VOTE FOR? [INDISTINCT SHOUTS] ARE YOU GOING TO VOTE FOR BUSH? [CROWD SHOUTS: "NO!"] THOSE OTHER ONES, THE ONES GOING AROUND THERE, THEY DO NOT REPRESENT ANYTHING. BUSH IS PAYING THOSE PEOPLE TO BE PRETENDING [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE REAL ENEMY HERE IS THE YANKEES WHO HAVE ORGANIZED AND FINANCED THE UNO. THE YANKEES CANNOT SOLVE THE NICARAGUAN PROBLEMS, BECAUSE THEY CANNOT EVEN SOLVE HONDURAS' PROBLEM. THEY CANNOT SOLVE ITS ECONOMIC PROBLEM, EVEN THOUGH THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT HAS LENT ITSELF FOR THE YANKEE MANEUVERING. I AM NOT TALKING ABOUT THE HONDURAN PEOPLE. YOU KNOW THAT THE HONDURAN PEOPLE ARE COMBATIVE AND BRAVE. WHAT IS THE ARMY USED FOR IN HONDURAS? WHAT IS IT USED FOR? TO MASSACRE THE PEOPLE [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]. THE CONTRAS ARE IN HONDURAN TERRITORY. WHO IS RESPONSIBLE FOR GETTING THOSE CONTRAS OUT? IT IS UP TO THE HONDURANS, IT IS UP TO THE HONDURAN ARMY. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0066

MAPUTO (MOZAMBIQUE), NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [REPORT] [FRELIMO CENTRAL COMMITTEE] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE FRELIMO PARTY APPRECIATES AND SUPPORTS EFFORTS MOUNTED BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT AND OTHER STATES OF CENTRAL AMERICA TO RESTORE PEACE, AND CALLS ON ALL THE INTERESTED FORCES TO CREATE CONDITIONS TO APPLY THE PEACE PLAN AS AGREED UPON. WE VALUE OUR RELATIONS OF FRIENDSHIP AND COOPERATION WITH THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT.

IN THE REPUBLIC OF CUBA, THE PEOPLE'S POWER HAS CONSOLIDATED AND THE REVOLUTION CAN NOW FUNDAMENTALLY CONCENTRATE ITS EFFORTS ON THE TECHNICAL AND SCIENTIFIC DEVELOPMENT OF THE COUNTRY AND THE IMPROVEMENT OF THE QUALITY OF LIFE OF THE PEOPLE. THE [FRELIMO] PARTY SALUTES THE RELATIONS OF FRIENDSHIP AND COOPERATION BETWEEN OUR PARTIES, STATES, AND PEOPLES, AND EXPRESSES THE HOPE THAT THESE RELATIONS WILL CONTINUE TO DEVELOP FURTHER. THE [FRELIMO] PARTY HOPES THAT THE WINDS OF PEACE NOW BLOWING WILL CONTRIBUTE TO ELIMINATING THE HOTBEDS OF TENSION THROUGHOUT ALL OF CENTRAL AMERICA AND LATIN AMERICA IN GENERAL SO THAT THE PEOPLE OF THAT ZONE MAY BENEFIT FROM PEACE AND TRANQUILITY TO UNDERTAKE THE NECESSARY FIGHT AGAINST MISERY AND BACKWARDNESS.

IN EUROPE, DURING THE PERIOD UNDER EXAMINATION, THE RELATIONS OF FRIENDSHIP AND SOLIDARITY WITH OUR PEOPLE WERE DEEPENED, WHILE THE COOPERATION OF THE MOZAMBICAN STATE WITH THE EUROPEAN COUNTRIES WAS BROADENED. IN GENERAL TERMS, WE HAVE BEEN CLOSELY FOLLOWING THE PROCESS TO ESTABLISH THE EUROPE OF 12 AND THE TRANSFORMATIONS BEGUN IN VARIOUS SOCIALIST COUNTRIES.

THE [FRELIMO] PARTY VIEWS POSITIVELY THE CONTINUATION OF THE PROCESS OF CONSOLIDATION OF THE EUROPE OF 12 AND HOPES THAT THIS PROCESS WILL POSITIVELY CONTRIBUTE TO BALANCED RELATIONS BETWEEN NORTH AND SOUTH.

THE [FRELIMO] PARTY SALUTES THE COURAGE DEMONSTRATED BY THE CPSU LEADERSHIP, PARTICULARLY COMRADE MIKHAIL GORBACHEV, BY FACING THE GREAT CHALLENGE OF CRITICAL REFLECTION AND FOR THE RECTIFICATIONS NOW IN PROGRESS IN THE USSR.

THE TRANSFORMATIONS TAKING PLACE IN VARIOUS SOCIALIST COUNTRIES OPEN AN ENCOURAGING AND PROFITABLE THEORETICAL DEBATE ON THE CONSTRUCTION OF SOCIALISM THAT WE WOULD LIKE TO SEE CONTINUE IN A CLIMATE OF UNITY AND SOLIDARITY. THE [FRELIMO] PARTY IS FOLLOWING THIS PERIOD OF REFLECTION ON THE PROCESS OF THE BUILDING OF SOCIALISM IN EUROPEAN COUNTRIES AND IT IS OVERJOYED BY THE FACT THAT THIS PROCESS CONTINUES TO SAFEGUARD COOPERATION WITH OUR COUNTRY. WE ARE AWARE THAT THESE CHANGES TAKING PLACE IN SOCIALIST COUNTRIES, PARTICULARLY THE CHANGES THAT ARE OBSERVED IN THE USSR WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF PERESTROYKA AND GLASNOST, HAVE AN IMPORTANT IMPACT AT THE LEVEL OF THE [MARXIST-LENINIST] PARTIES AND THE PROGRESSIVE FORCES, AS WELL AS IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS IN GENERAL. THIS IMPACT HAS BEEN VERY POSITIVE AND HAS DECISIVELY CONTRIBUTED TO CREATE A NEW ATMOSPHERE IN RELATIONS AMONG THE SUPERPOWERS AND IN THE PROCESS OF DETENTE THAT CURRENTLY CHARACTERIZES THE INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0067

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 20 OCT 89 -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] AND WHAT DO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS MEAN WITH THAT VERY CATEGORICAL PASSAGE? THEY WANT TO SAY THAT IT IS THE FMLN THAT MUST STOP ITS HOSTILITIES, AND DO SO AT ONCE, IMMEDIATELY, AND EFFECTIVELY IN ORDER TO HOLD A DIALOGUE. WHAT THIS MEANS IS THAT THE PRESIDENTS, AS ANY RATIONAL PEOPLE, FEEL IT IS MORE ADVANTAGEOUS TO CONDUCT A PROCESS OF DIALOGUE WITHOUT BOMBS AND BULLETS. WHAT ELSE DOES THE AGREEMENT SAY? IT SAYS THE END OF HOSTILITIES WILL PERMIT A DIALOGUE SO THAT THE FMLN WILL LATER ABANDON THE ARMED STRUGGLE, DISBAND AS AN ARMED GROUP, SURRENDER ITS WEAPONS, AND JOIN DEMOCRATIC AND INSTITUTIONAL LIFE.

BY THIS, THEY -- EVEN NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA WHO SIGNED THE AGREEMENT -- MEAN THERE IS INSTITUTIONAL LIFE IN EL SALVADOR AND DEMOCRACY, WHICH THEY ARE ASKING THE FMLN TO JOIN. THIS IS THE SPIRIT OF THE PROPOSAL THE GOVERNMENT TOOK TO SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA. BECAUSE THE PROPOSAL WE ADOPTED IS SO LONG, IT WOULD BE IMPOSSIBLE FOR ME TO READ IT TO YOU, SO THAT YOU CAN BE INFORMED.

HOWEVER, YOU WILL BE ABLE TO SEE FOR YOURSELVES TOMORROW WHAT I AM SAYING TO YOU TONIGHT, BECAUSE THE PROPOSAL WILL BE PUBLISHED IN ALL OF OUR COUNTRY'S NEWSPAPERS. THERE, YOU WILL SEE THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS FAITHFULLY COMPLYING WITH WHAT THE FIVE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SIGNED IN THE TELA ACCORD, AND THAT WE ARE FOLLOWING UP ON THE TERMS OF THE FIRST DIALOGUE IN MEXICO.

WHAT DOES THE FMLN DO IN SAN JOSE? FIRST, DRAWING AWAY FROM THE AGREEMENT MADE IN MEXICO, IT DOES NOT WANT TO TALK ABOUT CEASING HOSTILITIES. IT INTRODUCES SEVERAL PROPOSALS, WHICH THE FMLN CLAIMS ARE AN EXPANSION ON THE MEXICO PROPOSAL, AND PRESENTS SEVERAL DOCUMENTS TO THE SALVADORAN DELEGATION. BY THE WAY, THE FMLN ALSO VIOLATES THE MEXICO PACT BY NOT RESPECTING THE DISCRETION OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. ONCE AGAIN IT PRESENTS THESE DOCUMENTS TO THE NEWS MEDIA BEFORE PRESENTING THEM TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DELEGATION. AS YOU WILL SEE, THE DELEGATION RECEIVED QUITE A FEW DOCUMENTS FROM THE FMLN THERE. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0069

HAVANA (CUBA), 10 JAN 90 (RADIO REBELDE NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] DESPITE AMPLE EVIDENCE, NO SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAD BLAMED THE ARMED FORCES OF KILLING DEFENSELESS CIVILIANS SINCE THE CIVIL WAR WORSENED IN 1979. THE ANNOUNCEMENT MADE BY PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI OF THE ARREST OF 45 SOLDIERS AND 2 OFFICERS FOR KILLING 6 CLERGYMEN, A MAID, AND HER DAUGHTER, ON 16 NOVEMBER IS IN ITSELF A SMALL AND PARTIAL MILESTONE.

CRISTIANI, WHOSE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE PARTY WAS FOUNDED AT THE BEGINNING OF THE EIGHTIES BY INDIVIDUALS LINKED TO PARAMILITARY BANDS, THE ARMY, AND SECURITY CORPS, ASSERTED THAT THE NAMES OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRIMES WILL BE RELEASED IN THE NEXT 48 HOURS.

JESUIST FRANCISCO ESTRADA, WHO REPLACED FATHER JOSE IGNACIO ELLACURIA -- ONE OF THOSE MASSACRED -- AT THE RECTORSHIP OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN SAN SALVADOR, WARNED THAT IT IS NOT ENOUGH TO KNOW WHICH SARGENT PULLED THE TRIGGER BUT WHO GAVE HIM ORDERS TO DO SO NEEDS TO BE REVEALED. CRISTIANI WILL NOT GO THAT FAR.

COSMETIC SACRIFICES ARE MADE IN ORDER TO NEUTRALIZE THE THREAT OF U.S. CONGRESS INTERRUPTING THE $1.5 MILLION IT SENDS A DAY FOR THE WAR AGAINST THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] AND THE REPRESSION OF THE PEOPLE.

THE DISMISSAL OF GENERAL JUAN RAFAEL BUSTILLO AS CHIEF OF THE AIR FORCES AND THE POSSIBLE PUNISHMENT OF SOME OF THE COUNTERINSURGENT ATLACATL BATTALION FULFILL THESE REQUIREMENTS. HOWEVER, CRISTIANI WILL ATTEND THE NEXT INFORMAL SUMMIT OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS IN TEGUCIGALPA, HONDURAS ON 28 JANUARY UNDER ADVERSE CONDITIONS.

THE MOBILIZATION OF THE LATIN AMERICAN PUBLIC OPINION AGAINST THE U.S. INTERVENTION IN PANAMA AND ITS AIM OF EXTENDING THE INTERVENTION TO OTHER NATIONS OF THE AREA HAVE WEAKENED WASHINGTON'S DIPLOMATIC SPACE. THIS COULD HAVE AN EFFECT ON ITS POLITICAL ALLY OF EL SALVADOR WHICH, IN THE PREVIOUS SUMMIT HELD IN DECEMBER, PRESENTED NICARAGUA AND THE FMLN AS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE WORSENING OF THE CRISIS IN CENTRAL AMERICA.

THE FACTS ARE CONCLUSIVE. WHAT WILL NOW BE THE EXCUSE OF SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND HIS PROTECTOR GEORGE BUSH?

TST1-MUC3-0070

BUENOS AIRES, 25 JAN 90 (NA) -- [TEXT] THE GROUP THAT STORMED THE 3D INFANTRY REGIMENT IN LA TABLADA INTENDED TO OVERTHROW THE CONSTITUTIONAL AUTHORITIES AND TO IMPLEMENT "A PLAN OF GOVERNMENT" WITH ARMY FUNDS. THE GROUP ALSO SOUGHT TO DISSOLVE THE ARMED FORCES.

ACCORDING TO DOCUMENTS THAT WERE SEIZED FROM THE TERRORISTS BY INTELLIGENCE SERVICES, THE ATTACKERS PLANNED TO ISSUE A PROCLAMATION. THE PROCLAMATION STATES THAT THE SO-CALLED "PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENT," ALLEGEDLY TO HAVE BEEN INSTALLED BY THEM, WOULD ADOPT THE FOLLOWING MEASURES:

1. TO DECREE A 150-PERCENT SALARY INCREASE FOR ALL PEOPLE EARNING 2,000 AUSTRALES OR LESS;

2. TO DECREE A 100-PERCENT SALARY INCREASE FOR ALL PEOPLE EARNING 3,000 AUSTRALES;

3. TO DECREE A 40-PERCENT SALARY INCREASE FOR PEOPLE WHO EARN UP TO 6,000 AUSTRALES;

4. TO INCREASE MINIMUM PENSIONS TO 4,000 AUSTRALES;

5. TO ELIMINATE ALL PRIVILEGED PENSIONS FOR THE MILITARY, DEPUTIES, SENATORS, COUNCILMEN, CABINET MEMBERS, AND SECRETARIES OF STATE;

6. TO DECREE A PRICE FREEZE AND TO DECREE THAT ALL THOSE WHO VIOLATE THE ESTABLISHED PRICE FREEZE, AS WELL AS SPECULATORS AND HOARDERS, WILL BE PUNISHED WITH SENTENCES OF UP TO 20 YEARS; IT WIL BE UP TO THE PEOPLE TO CONTROL THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THIS PRICE FREEZE;

7. TO DECREE THE IMMEDIATE SUSPENSION OF EVICTIONS AND DECREE A FREEZE ON HOUSE RENTS;

8. TO DECREASE INTEREST RATES AND NEGATIVE RATES, EVEN ON PREVIOUSLY ESTABLISHED CREDITS;

9. TO CANCEL IMMEDIATELY DEBTS CONTRACTED WITH THE FINANCIAL MARKET;

10. TO CANCEL DEBTS CONTRACTED BY SMALL- AND MEDIUM-SIZED FARMERS WITH THE BANKING SECTOR;

11. TO IMPLEMENT UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE OF 2,000 AUSTRALES PER CHILD;

12. TO IMPLEMENT A SUBSIDY FOR UNWED MOTHERS OF 3,000 AUSTRALES;

13. THE PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENT HEREBY NATIONALIZES THE BANKING SECTOR; THE IAPI, ARGENTINE INSTITUTE FOR PROMOTION OF FOREIGN TRADE, [INSTITUTO ARGENTINO DE PROMOCION DEL INTERCAMBIO] IS REESTABLISHED;

14. ARTICLE NO 40 OF THE 1949 CONSTITUTION IS HEREBY ESTABLISHED: "ENERGY SOURCES ARE THE INALIENABLE PROPERTY OF THE NATION."

THE REST OF THE TERRORIST PROCLAMATION STATES:

THIS IS A NATIONAL EMERGENCY AND SOLIDARITY PLAN THAT WILL BE IMPLEMENTED FOR 120 DAYS. IT SEEKS TO PROMOTE INVESTMENTS FOR PRODUCTION, AND CONSUMPTION. WITHIN THIS 120-DAY PERIOD, THE PROPER NATIONAL SECTORS WILL HELP IN THE DRAFTING OF A SHORT-, MEDIUM-, AND LONG-TERM ECONOMIC PLAN THAT WILL PROTECT THE INTERESTS OF THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY.

THE FUNDS TO FINANCE THIS NATIONAL EMERGENCY AND SOLIDARITY PLAN WILL DERIVE FROM:

1. THE ELIMINATION OF THE MILITARY BUDGET, SINCE THE ARMY HAS BEEN REPLACED BY THE POPULAR MILITIAS OF THE PEOPLE'S RESISTANCE FRONT;

2. THE EXPRESSION OF ALL THE PROPERTIES OF JOSE ALFREDO MARTINEZ DE HOZ AND OF ALL MILITARY OFFICERS WHO HAVE MORE THAN ONE HOUSE AND ONE CAR; THE SAME WILL APPLY TO ALL UNION LEADERS;

3. THE EXPROPRIATION OF THE FINANCIAL MARKET;

4. THE SUSPENSION OF INTEREST PAYMENTS ON THE FOREIGN DEBT.

THIS PLAN IS BASED ON THE SOLIDARITY OF MILLIONS OF ARGENTINES, THE IMMENSE MAJORITY OF WORKERS, PRODUCERS, AND UNEMPLOYED. WE HAVE THE ABSOLUTE RIGHT TO LIVE IN A FATHERLAND WITH LIBERTY AND SOCIAL JUSTICE, WHERE ALL MEN ARE BROTHERS, AND WHERE THE WEALTH OF THE COUNTRY MAY BE ENJOYED BY EVERYONE IN KEEPING WITH HIS WORK, HIS CREATIVITY, AND HIS HONESTY.

TST1-MUC3-0071

LA PAZ, 25 MAY 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] TWO U.S. MORMON MISSIONARIES -- AGED 19 AND 21 -- WERE SHOT TO DEATH LAST NIGHT BY A GROUP OF TERRORISTS FROM THE ZARATE WILKA ARMED FORCES OF LIBERATION [FAL].

THIS IS THE SAME TERRORIST GROUP THAT CLAIMED CREDIT FOR THE FOILED ATTACK AGAINST FORMER U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE GEORGE SHULTZ IN AUGUST 1988. IN OCTOBER, THE GROUP BLEW UP THE LINES PROVIDING POWER TO LA PAZ, RESULTING IN A POWER OUTAGE THERE. THE GROUP ALSO CLAIMED CREDIT FOR THE JANUARY DYNAMITE BOMBING IN THE CONGRESS.

THE MURDER TOOK PLACE AT 2220 LAST NIGHT AND, 30 MINUTES LATER, THE TERRORISTS LEFT MESSAGES WITH LOCAL NEWSPAPERS CLAIMING TO BE THE ASSAILANTS.

THE MESSAGE, WHICH WAS HANDRITTEN, SAID: "THE VIOLATION OF OUR NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY CANNOT REMAIN UNPUNISHED. THIS IS A WARNING TO THE YANKEE INVADERS WHO COME HERE TO MASSACRE OUR PEASANT BROTHERS AND TO THEIR LACKEYS. WE POOR HAVE NO OTHER OPTION BUT TO TAKE UP ARMS. OUR HATRED IS IMPLACABLE, AND OUR WAR IS TO THE DEATH. FAL, ZARATE WILKA."

THE U.S. CITIZENS -- TODD RAY WILSON BURDENSON AND JEFFREY BRENT BALL -- WERE MISSIONARIES OF THE CHRISTIAN CHURCH OF LATTER DAY SAINTS (HEADQUARTERED IN UTAH), WHICH, IN RECENT YEARS, HAS EXTENDED ITS ACTIVITIES IN BOLIVIA BY BUILDING DOZENS OF TEMPLES. BOTH MISSIONARIES HAD LIVED IN THE VICINITY OF THE GENERAL CEMETERY LOCATED IN A DENSELY POPULATED LA PAZ DISTRICT. THEY WERE KILLED WITH TWO BURSTS OF MACHINEGUN FIRE.

A MORMON CHURCH SPOKESMAN SAID THAT THIS WAS AN ATTACK AGAINST "TWO INNOCENT PEOPLE" AND CALLED ON THE POLICE TO SOLVE THE MURDER. HE SAID THAT LAST YEAR DYNAMITE WAS PLACED AT A TEMPLE IN THE SAME AREA BUT THAT THE CULPRITS WERE NEVER IDENTIFIED.

THE BOLIVIAN GOVERNMENT HAS CONDEMNED THE ATTACK AND ORDERED AN IMMEDIATE INVESTIGATION. DEPUTY INTERIOR MINISTER WALTER COSTAS ANNOUNCED THAT THE TRAFFIC AND POLICE DEPARTMENTS WILL CARRY OUT DRAGNETS IN LA PAZ.

THE KILLING OF THE U.S. MISSIONARIES HAS COINCIDED WITH THE ARRIVAL IN BOLIVIA OF THE FIRST CONTINGENT OF U.S. MILITARY ENGINEERS, TECHNICIANS, AND TROOPS, WHO WILL BE IN CHARGE OF THE TASK OF LEVELING PATTI-PATTI HILL TO BUILD AN AIRPORT FOR THE CITY OF POTOSI.

TST1-MUC3-0073

SANTIAGO, 29 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] POLICE TODAY REPORTED THAT DURING THE LAST FEW HOURS TERRORISTS STAGED THREE BOMB ATTACKS AGAINST U.S. PROPERTIES.

NO ONE HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACKS SO FAR. THEY AFFECTED THE U.S.-CHILEAN CULTURAL INSTITUTE, A MORMON CHURCH IN THE CAPITAL, AND A BRANCH OF THE "CITICORP" FINANCIAL FIRM IN VINA DEL MAR, 125 KM NORTHEAST OF SANTIAGO.

CARABINEROS HAVE REPORTED THAT A BOMB, WHICH WAS PLACED ON THE 5TH FLOOR OF THE CHILEAN-U.S. CULTURAL INSTITUTE, 150 METERS FROM THE GOVERNMENT PALACE, WENT OFF LAST NIGHT CAUSING DAMAGE BUT NO VICTIMS.

THE BOMB HAD BEEN MANUFACTURED WITH L KILO OF AMMONIUM GELAGNITE AND WAS ACTIVATED WITH A FUSE, POLICE SOURCES SAID.

AT 0LL5 THIS MORNING (0415 GMT) INCENDIARY BOMBS WERE HURLED AT A MORMON TEMPLE AT NUNOA DISTRICT, IN SANTIAGO. THE BOMBS CAUSED MINOR DAMAGE. AT THE TIME OF THE ATTACK THE BUILDING WAS EMPTY, ACCORDING TO THE SOURCES.

THE ATTACKERS PAINTED THE WALLS AND LEFT PAMPHLETS WITH ULTRA-LEFTIST MESSAGES OF THE LAUTARO YOUTH FRONT.

A BOMB, WHICH SHATTERED THE GLASSES AND DESTROYED THE MASONRY OF THE "CITICORP" FINANCIAL COMPANY OFFICES IN DOWNTOWN VINA DEL MAR, EXPLODED TODAY SHORTLY AFTER 0200 (0500 GMT).

THE POLICE REPORTED THAT ANOTHER BOMB WAS DISCOVERED AND DEFUSED BEFORE IT EXPLODED AT A CATHOLIC SCHOOL IN VINA DEL MAR.

A FEW DAYS AGO, THE CHILEAN-U.S. CULTURAL INSTITUTES IN VINA DEL MAR, TALCA, AND TEMUCO WERE THE TARGET OF BOMB ATTACKS.

THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT (FPMR), WHICH THE PINOCHET REGIME CONSIDERS TO BE THE COMMUNIST PARTY'S ARMED BRANCH, ANNOUNCED FOLLOWING THE U.S. INVASION OF PANAMA THAT IT WOULD ATTACK "U.S. INTERESTS IN CHILE."

TST1-MUC3-0074

BOGOTA, 2 NOV 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] JOSE ALEJANDRO BONIVENTO, FORMER PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE AND CURRENT MEMBER OF THE COURT OF APPEALS, RESIGNED HIS POST TODAY, CLAIMING THAT HE HAD BEEN SUBJECTED TO UNDUE PRESSURE BY THE GOVERNMENT.

BONIVENTO MAINTAINS THAT IN APPLYING WHAT IS TANTAMOUNT TO A STATE OF SIEGE, THE GOVERNMENT IS ISSUING MEASURES AND WANTS THEM TO BE DECLARED CONSTITUTIONAL FOR ITS CONVENIENCE AND TO SATISFY FOREIGN INTERESTS.

IT WAS ANNOUNCED THAT 40 JUDGES MIGHT RESIGN NEXT WEEK TO PROTEST THE ASSASSINATION OF THEIR COLLEAGUE MARIELA ESPINOSA ARANGO.

COLOMBIAN JUDGES TODAY BEGAN A NUMBER OF STAGGERED STOPPAGES TO PROTEST THE ASSASSINATION OF JUDGE MARIELA ESPINOSA ARANGO THE EVENING OF 1 NOVEMBER IN MEDELLIN. A TOTAL OF 17,000 JUDGES PARTICIPATED IN A 2-HOUR STOPPAGE. THERE WILL BE TWO SIMILAR ACTIONS THE MORNING AND AFTERNOON OF 3 NOVEMBER. MEDELLIN'S SUPERIOR COURT WILL BE IN RECESS FOR 1 WEEK.

MEANWHILE, THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE COMPLAINED THAT FIVE JUDGES HAVE BEEN KILLED IN 2 MONTHS, AND IT REQUESTED A MEETING WITH PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO. JUDGE ESPINOSA WAS BURIED THIS AFTERNOON.

TST1-MUC3-0075

BOGOTA, 28 JUL 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [MARIBEL OSORIO] [TEXT] A COLOMBIAN JUDGE HAS PAID THE HIGHEST PRICE FOR DOING HER DUTY. MARIA ELENA DIAZ PEREZ, THIRD JUDGE OF PUBLIC ORDER, AND TWO OF HER BODYGUARDS FROM THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY], WERE ASSASSINATED IN MEDELLIN TODAY BY A GROUP OF 10 PAID ASSASSINS IN TWO CARS, A MAZDA AND WHAT WAS THOUGHT TO BE A MERCURY.

SHE WAS TRAVELING HOME IN HER CAR TODAY AT NOON. ABOUT HALF A BLOCK FROM HER HOME, HER CAR, A TOYOTA WITH LICENSE PLATE NO. A-3037, WAS INTERCEPTED BY A WHITE MAZDA AND POSSIBLY A MERCURY. DIAZ' DRIVER HAD TO HIT THE BRAKES, AS THE MOTORCYCLE OF ONE OF HER BODYGUARDS SLAMMED INTO THE REAR OF HER CAR. IN A MATTER OF SECONDS, THE 10 PAID ASSASSINS OPENED FIRE ON THE JUDGE'S CAR. A TOTAL OF 55 9-MM SUBMACHINE GUN ROUNDS HIT THE LEFT SIDE OF THE CAR. THE JUDGE, WHO WAS SITTING IN THE BACK SEAT, WAS ABLE TO LEAVE THE CAR AND RUN, BUT SHE WAS ONLY ABLE TO TAKE A FEW STEPS BEFORE BEING GUNNED DOWN BY 19 BULLETS. TWO OF HER DAS BODYGUARDS, DAGOBERTO RODRIGUEZ AND ALFONSO DE LIMA, WHO WERE INSIDE THE CAR, WERE KILLED INSTANTLY.

NO ONE HAS BEEN ARRESTED YET IN CONNECTION WITH THIS INCIDENT. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE MANY THREATS MADE AGAINST HER BECAME A REALITY TODAY.

MARIA ELENA DIAZ, 34, WILL BE BURIED IN MEDELLIN TOMORROW.

TST1-MUC3-0077

BOGOTA, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [BARCO] ACTUALLY, THAT IS NOT SO, BECAUSE WHILE WE ARE GATHERED HERE THE TENTACLES OF THE DRUG TRADE ARE CLOSING IN ON EUROPE AND THE MIDDLE EAST. THE AGGGRESSIVE SEARCH FOR NEW MARKETS DOES NOT RESPECT OCEANS, JUST AS IT HAS NOT RESPECTED BORDERS. ANYWHERE THERE ARE CONSUMERS, THERE WILL BE SUPPLIERS. IN FACT, COCAINE IS BUT ONE OF THE PERNICIOUS MANIFESTATIONS OF THE CRISIS OF DRUG ABUSE, WHICH IS MUCH BROADER. WE MUST NOT DELUDE OURSELVES. THIS SCOURGE AFFECTS US ALL.

ACTING IN SOLIDARITY, AS A COMMUNITY OF NATIONS, WE MUST FOLLOW THIS PLAN OF ACTION:

FIRST, IT IS INDISPENSABLE TO EFFECTIVELY CURB THE DEMAND FOR ILLEGAL DRUGS. DRUG ABUSE IS THE FUEL THAT PROPELS NARCOTERRORISM. TODAY IT IS ONE OF THE MOST SERIOUS THREATS TO LATIN AMERICAN DEMOCRACIES. COCAINE USERS ARE CONTRIBUTING TO THE KILLING OF MY PEOPLE BY THE CRIMINAL INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION. WITHOUT ANY DOUBT, IN ANY OF THE DISTINGUISHED RESIDENTIAL DISTRICTS OF THIS CITY, A HABITUAL COCAINE USER MAY REGARD MY ASSERTION AS AN EXAGGERATION. NEVERTHELESS, HIS VICE MAKES HIM A COLLABORATOR OF THE MURDERERS WHO HAVE KILLED MANY COLOMBIAN JUDGES AND POLICEMEN, WHO HAVE SACRIFICED THEIR LIVES TO DEFEND DEMOCRACY AND LAW. [APPLAUSE]

NO WEAPON OR TACTIC USED IN THIS STRUGGLE WILL BE EFFECTIVE ENOUGH IF IT IS NOT COMBINED WITH RESOLUTE EFFORTS TO REDUCE THE DEMAND. THE ILLEGAL PROFITS ARE EXTREMELY LARGE. I AM CERTAIN THAT WE WILL DEFEAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN COLOMBIA, BUT SOMEONE IN SOME OTHER COUNTRY, SOMEWHERE, WILL TAKE OVER THIS BUSINESS AS LONG AS IT REMAINS SO PROFITABLE. THIS HAPPENED WITH MARIJUANA. WHEN IT BECAME TOO COSTLY FOR THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO OPERATE IN COLOMBIA BECAUSE OF THE EFFECTIVENESS OF THE PUBLIC FORCES, THE TRADERS IN VICE MOVED THEIR PLANTATIONS TO CALIFORNIA, TO HAWAII, AND TO MANY OTHER REGIONS. THE ONLY LAW THE DRUG RUNNERS DO NOT VIOLATE IS THE LAW OF SUPPLY AND DEMAND. [APPLAUSE]

NO SOCIETY, REGARDLESS OF HOW WEALTHY IT IS, CAN AFFORD THE LUXURY OF ALLOWING ITS SONS OR DAUGHTERS TO POISON THEMSELVES WITH COCAINE, HEROIN, MARIJUANA, OR ANY OTHER SUCH DEADLY DRUGS. IN THIS CONTEXT, I WISH TO ASSERT THAT PRESIDENT BUSH'S PLAN TO CURB THE DEMAND IS A FIRST STEP IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION. WE MUST INSIST ON THE MESSAGE THAT ILLEGAL DRUGS ARE NOT ACCEPTABLE OR HARMLESS, WHETHER THEY ARE CONSUMED IN THE GLITTERING PARTIES OF THE RICH OR IN THE SLUMS. [CONTINUED]

TST1-MUC3-0078

BOGOTA, 15 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] MONTERIA -- BLOODY CLASHES HAVE BEEN TAKING PLACE IN THE RURAL AREA OF PUERTO LIBERTADOR MUNICIPALITY, SOUTH OF CORDOBA, SINCE 11 NOVEMBER. THE NUMBER OF GUERRILLAS KILLED BY 11TH BRIGADE TROOPS HAS RISEN TO 26.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS GIVEN JUST A FEW MINUTES AGO BY MILITARY SOURCES, THREE MORE MEMBERS OF THE SELF-STYLED POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY, EPL, WERE KILLED IN MUTATA, TRES PLAYITAS HAMLET, JUAN JOSE CORREGIMIENTO, IN THE CLASHES THAT TOOK PLACE ON 14 NOVEMBER. THIS BRINGS TO 21 THE NUMBER OF GUERRILLAS KILLED IN THIS AREA OF PUERTO LIBERTADOR MUNICIPALITY. IN ADDITION, FIVE MEMBERS OF THE FARC [REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA] WERE KILLED IN LA RICA, WHERE COMBAT BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER. IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT THE THE ARMY SUFFERED NO CASUALTIES. SOLDIER LUIS EDUARDO GONZALEZ ANAYA, WHO WAS WOUNDED IN COMBAT, HAS BEEN TAKEN TO THE BOGOTA MILITARY HOSPITAL. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

IN THE MEANTIME, COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE PERSONNEL ARE REPAIRING THE HELICOPTER THAT MADE AN EMERGENCY LANDING IN THE AREA AFTER BEING DAMAGED, APPARENTLY BY THE REBELS. MILITARY OPERATIONS CONTINUE IN THE RURAL AREA OF PUERTO LIBERTADOR MUNICIPALITY LED AND COORDINATED BY 11TH BRIGADE COMMANDER COLONEL IVAN RAMIREZ QUINTERO.

TST1-MUC3-0079

BOGOTA, 6 MAR 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] ...NOT ONLY OF THE PROVISIONS OF THE ANDEAN PACT, BUT ALSO OF THE VAST HORIZONS OF THE CARIBBEAN AND THE CENTRAL AMERICAN REGION. AS WE JOIN EFFORTS, AS WE STRENGTHEN OUR CAPABILITIES, AND WITH THE LONG TRADITION OF DEMOCRACY THAT WE SHARE, WE CAN OFFER OUR CONTRIBUTION TO STRENGTHENING OUR DEMOCRACY. ALL THE DEMOCRATS OF THE AMERICAS WHO SEE IN YOU, MR. PRESIDENT PEREZ, A GREAT FIGHTER, ARE NOW CELEBRATING A POSITIVE WAVE OF LEGITIMATE ELECTIONS, FOR EXAMPLE IN URUGUAY, CHILE, BRAZIL, COSTA RICA, AND NICARAGUA. VERY SHORTLY COLOMBIA AND LATER PERU WILL HOLD ELECTIONS. PANAMA, IN TURN, HAS CALLED FOR POPULAR CONSULTATION IN THE FORM OF A REFERENDUM SO THAT THE PEOPLE WILL DECIDE ON IMPORTANT CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS.

THROUGHOUT THE AMERICAS, DEMOCRACY IS THE PATH AND THAT IS WHY IT WILL BE THE ADEQUATE MEANS FOR STRENGTHENING THE OAS AS A REGIONAL ORGANIZATION IN WHICH THE VARIOUS TRENDS AND IDEOLOGIES WITHIN A COMMON OBJECTIVE OF SEARCHING FOR PEACE, FREEDOM, LIBERTY, AND JUSTICE MAY AND SHOULD BE EXPRESSED AND CONSULTED ON. THERE, THE MEMBERS WILL BE ABLE TO DISCUSS TOPICS THAT AFFECT US IN A DIRECT MANNER, SUCH AS INTERNATIONAL TRADE, FOREIGN DEBT, AND TECHNICAL COOPERATION, AS WELL AS HOW TO INCREASE THE SCOPE OF ACTION WITH VARIOUS INTERLOCUTORS, SUCH AS THE CASE OF CANADA, THE ENTRY IF WHICH INTO THE OAS WE WARMLY WELCOME.

THEREFORE, LET US CONSIDER THE REASONS FOR THIS MEETING WHICH WE DO NOT HESITATE IN TERMING HISTORIC. THE DOCUMENTS ARE EVIDENCE OF HOW MUCH WE HAVE ADVANCED IN SPECIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS IN THE FIELDS OF ENERGY, COMMUNICATIONS, TRANSPORTATION, AND BORDER TRANSIT; IN JOINT PROGRAMS IN CITY PLANNING SUCH AS THE CUCUTA-VILLA EL ROSARIO-SAN ANTONIO-URENA; IN THE AGRO-INDUSTRIAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL SECTORS, AND IN INDIAN ETHNIC GROUPS, CUSTOMS, AND EDUCATION. ALL OF THESE ARE TOPICS WE HAVE DISCUSSED OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS WITH OUR RESPECTIVE TEAMS. HOWEVER, THERE IS ONE TOPIC THAT I WISH TO EMPHASIZE.

THERE IS AN ENEMY WHO SEEKS TO DESTROY THE INTEGRATIONIST AND DEMOCRATIC PROJECT. THERE ARE ANACHRONISTIC REDOUBTS OF A SUBVERSIVE NATURE THAT ARE TODAY ENFENCED BY OUR MILITARY FORCES AND OUR HARD WORKING PEOPLE. THE ENEMY FEELS HIS DAYS ARE NUMBERED AND HE EXPRESSES HIMSELF THOUGH VIOLENT ACTIONS WITH KIDNAPPINGS, EXTORTION, AND INDISCRIMINATE TERRORISM; BY DESTROYING OIL PIPELINES AND CONTAMINATING RIVERS, WATER BASINS, AND LAGOONS. OUR COMMISSIONS HAVE SUGGESTED POSITIVE MEANS FOR WORKING JOINTLY ON THESE RIVERS, WATER BASINS, AND LAGOONS, AND HAVE SIGNED AN AGREEMENT THAT IS ALREADY BEING IMPLEMENTED ON OIL SPILLS AND ACCIDENTS.

COLOMBIAN DEMOCRACY WILL PREVAIL OVER THIS INTERNAL ENEMY, AND UNDOUBTEDLY THE INTEGRATION PROGRAMS WILL CONTINUE WITH RENEWED VIGOR. THE TECHNICAL MANAGEMENT OF THE WATER RESOUCES, THE ELECTRICITY AND TELEPHONE INTERCONNECTIONS, THE FEASIBILITY STUDIES FOR THE VARIOUS ALTERNATE ROUTES THAT WILL CONNECT US, THE REOPENING OF THE BRIDGES THAT WERE CLOSED 30 YEARS AGO, THE UTILIZATION OF THE CAMILO DAZA AIRPORT IN CUCUTA AS AN ALTERNATE AIRPORT FOR SAN ANTONIO, THE AGREEMENT ON FISHING POLICIES, THE PLANS TO INCREASE CROPS RANGING FROM SUGARCANE AND COTTON TO CHIQUI-CHIQUI FIBER ARE POSITIVE ANSWERS TO THOSE WHO INSIST ON DISRUPTING THINGS.

THE INTERNATIONAL POLICY TODAY NOT ONLY UNDERSTANDS THE TRADITIONAL CONCEPT AND THE PRESERVATION OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY, BUT ABOVE ALL, IT POINTS TO PEOPLE'S WELL-BEING AND INCREASES THEIR CAPABILITIES FOR CONSUMPTION. IT IS NOT BY BLOWING UP OIL PIPELINES OR PREVENTING THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE ALONG THE RIVER BANKS OF BOTH COUNTRIES FROM FISHING OR BY POISONING THEIR CROPS THAT PEOPLE'S WELL-BEING WILL BE ACHIEVED.

I AM SURE THAT THE SAN PEDRO ALEJANDRINO DOCUMENT WE SIGNED TODAY IS A GRADUAL, BUT DECISIVE STEP TOWARD AUTHENTIC LATIN AMERICAN INTEGRATION. BY THE DECISION OF THEIR PEOPLE AND PROMOTED BY THEIR RULERS IN THIS SIMPLE ROOM WHERE THE LIBERATOR DIED, WE ARE TODAY CONSOLIDATING THESE BASES THAT WILL NOT BE DESTROYED AND WILL PREVENT IN THE FUTURE ANY FURTHER FRUSTRATIONS OF THE DREAMS OF THE LIBERATOR, BOLIVAR.

MIXED COMMISSIONS WILL BE APPOINTED SHORTLY AND WILL GET DOWN TO WORK IN WHAT WE STILL HAVE YET TO DO. THEY WILL CONTINUE WITH A TRULY LIBERATING TASK, THAT TODAY -- AS FROM THE TIMES OF THE CONGRESS OF ANGOSTURA -- IS UNITING OUR TWO NATIONS. THANK YOU. [APPLAUSE]

TST1-MUC3-0083

SAN SALVADOR, 26 APR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] A SALVADORAN COURT YESTERDAY PRESENTED A SWORN DECLARATION BY PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE IN WHICH HE LINKS RIGHTIST LEADER ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON TO THE MARCH 1980 ASSASSINATION OF ARCHBISHOP OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO.

THE DECLARATION, WHICH THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE REQUESTED FROM THE FOURTH PENAL COURT, DID NOT PROVIDE DETAILS REGARDING EVIDENCE THAT COULD BE USED TO SOLVE THE CASE OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO, WHO WAS A STAUNCH CRITIC OF THE GOVERNMENT BECAUSE OF ITS ALLEGED HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS.

THE DOCUMENT CONTAINS A LIST OF THE NAMES OF 12 ARMY OFFICERS AND 12 CIVILIANS WHO WERE ALLEGEDLY INVOLVED IN PLOTTING TO OUST THE REVOLUTIONARY GOVERNMENT JUNTA THAT TOOK OVER IN OCTOBER 1979 AFTER OVERTHROWING GENERAL HUMBERTO ROMERO.

THE LIST OF PLOTTERS INCLUDES RIGHTIST DEPUTY D'AUBUISSON, FOUNDER OF THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) -- THE WINNER IN THE RECENT ELECTIONS -- AND CAPTAIN ALVARO SARAVIA, WHOM THE PRESIDENT ACCUSED OF BEING THE MASTERMINDS OF THE ASSASSINATION OF THE CLERGYMAN.

THE LIST ALSO INCLUDES THE NAMES OF CIVILIANS INVOLVED IN THE KIDNAPPING OF SEVERAL SALVADORAN BUSINESSMEN EARLY IN THE DECADE.

ACCORDING TO DUARTE'S DECLARATION, 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE SOLDIERS ARRESTED THE 24 COUP PLOTTERS IN 1980, AND SEVERAL DOCUMENTS WERE SEIZED FROM THEM, INCLUDING A NOTEBOOK WITH PLANS FOR KILLING ROMERO.

THE U.S. SENATE HAS A NOTEBOOK OWNED BY CAPT SARAVIA, AND SALVADORAN JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES ARE INVESTIGATING HOW THE U.S. SENATE ENDED UP WITH IT.

ACCORDING TO DUARTE, "COLONEL ADOLFO ARNULFO MAJANO, A MEMBER OF THE REVOLUTIONARY JUNTA THAT OUSTED GEN ROMERO, HAD THE DOCUMENTS."

THE SALVADORAN SUPREME COURT RECENTLY REVOKED A SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT EXTRADITION REQUEST FOR SARAVIA, WHOM THE GOVERNMENT WANTED TO QUESTION TO HELP SOLVE THE ROMERO CASE.

THE ARCHBISHOP WAS KILLED BY A SNIPER WHILE SAYING MASS AT A HOSPITAL FOR CANCER PATIENTS.

TST1-MUC3-0084

SAN SALVADOR, 13 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [STATEMENT] [JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, COMMANDER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] WE BELIEVE WE HAVE MADE A GREAT EFFORT TO INCREASE THE POSSIBILITIES OF REACHING AN AGREEMENT. AS A RESULT, WE BELIEVE THIS MEETING AND OTHERS THAT MAY COME CAN BE DESCRIBED AS SERIOUS DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION. WE HAVE MADE AN EFFORT SO THAT THE DELEGATIONS CAN HOLD ENOUGH DECISION-MAKING POWER FOR AGREEMENTS TO BE REACHED AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. I SAID EARLIER THAT OUR PROPOSAL IS AIMED AT ACHIEVING THE COUNTRY'S REAL DEMOCRATIZATION. WE HAVE MADE AN EFFORT TO ACHIEVE THAT GOAL. WE ARE NOT ASKING THE GOVERNMENT TO GIVE UP THE LEGITIMACY IT SAYS IT HAS OBTAINED IN THE ELECTIONS. WE ARE ASKING THE GOVERNMENT TO SUBMIT IT TO A TEST FOR THE SAKE OF PEACE. IF IT PASSES THE TEST, THEN IT WOULD REAFFIRM ITS POWER. OTHERWISE, WE WERE ALWAYS RIGHT TO DEMAND A NEW CONSENSUS FOR ACHIEVING PEACE IN THE COUNTRY.

ON PREVIOUS OCCASIONS THEY SAID THAT OUR PROPOSALS VIOLATED THE CONSTITUTION. WE HAVE MADE A GREAT EFFORT, IN SPITE OF THE FACT THAT WE DO NOT RECOGNIZE THE CONSTITUTION BECAUSE IT WAS MADE TO PROMOTE THE WAR. THE CONSTITUTION WAS DRAFTED BASED ON THE KILLING OF OVER 70,000 SALVADORANS. THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY DOES NOT REPRESENT A LARGE PART OF SALVADORAN SOCIETY, BUT WE HAVE MADE AN EFFORT SO THAT THERE ARE NO OBSTACLES TO REACHING AN AGREEMENT. WE HOPE A NEW CONSTITUTION FOR PEACE CAN BE DRAFTED.

THAT IS WHY WE ARE HERE, IN SPITE OF THE FACT THAT AT THE BEGINNING THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION INSISTED ON PERFORMING CERTAIN TASKS WHICH WE THOUGHT SHOULD NOT HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT. WE ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THE FACT THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS THE WRONG IDEA OF WHAT A DIALOGUE IS. WE BELIEVE THAT TO EXTEND THE DIALOGUE IN THE CURRENT CONTEXT, IN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE EXISTING PRESSURE IN THE COUNTRY, IS TO EXTEND THE WAR. TO HOLD A DIALOGUE FULL OF DETAILS AND AGREEMENTS OF LITTLE IMPORTANCE IS TO EXTEND THE WAR.

TST1-MUC3-0085

SAN SALVADOR, 2 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO, ALIAS FERMAN CIENFUEGOS, BY RENE ALVARENGAS] [EXCERPT] [PASSAGE OMITTED] [ALVARENGAS] COMMANDER FERMAN CIENFUEGOS, WHEN WILL THE DIALOGUE RESUME?

[SANCHO] WE BELIEVE THAT FOR THE DIALOGUE TO BE RESUMED THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES, MAINLY COLONELS PONCE AND ELENA, AND CRISTIANI MUST SPECIFICALLY ACCEPT THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES. WE BELIEVE THAT ONCE THIS SITUATION AND ALL THE POLITICAL ACTIONS FOR WHICH THEY ARE RESPONSIBLE HAVE BEEN CLARIFIED.... [CHANGES THOUGHT] THEY HAVE TO EXPLAIN THINGS VERY CLEARLY BECAUSE WE ARE REALLY TIRED OF HEARING THE FAMOUS PHRASE THAT THEY ALWAYS USE; THAT IS, THAT THEY ARE GOING TO INVESTIGATE. THAT IS NO LONGER POSSIBLE; THEREFORE, WE ARE DEMANDING THAT THE SITUATION BE CLARIFIED.

MEANWHILE, WE ARE GOING TO TALK TO THE OBSERVERS AND MEDIATORS TO CHECK ON HOW THE SITUATION IS DEVELOPING AND AT THE SAME TIME TO STUDY THE CONDITIONS FOR THE DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION. I BELIEVE THAT THE NATURE OF THE SUSPENSION HAS BEEN WELL EXPLAINED. THESE CONDITIONS MUST BE MET BEFORE WE CAN, LET US SAY, RESUME THE MEETING. IT MUST BE MADE VERY CLEAR THAT THE AGREEMENT TO HOLD A DIALOGUE, THE CONTINUITY OF THE DIALOGUE, HAS NOT BEEN BROKEN. THIS WAS AGREED ON BY THE TWO PARTIES, AND THIS IS NOT WHAT WE ARE TALKING ABOUT. WHAT WE DID WAS SUSPEND THE MEETING THAT HAS CREATED SO MANY EXPECTATIONS. THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT STATED THAT THERE WOULD BE A CEASE-FIRE AND A GRADUAL PROCESS TO PUT AN END TO HOSTILITIES THAT WOULD LEAD TO THE END OF THE WAR; HOWEVER, WE BELIEVE THAT IN ORDER FOR THIS TO BE DONE, WE MUST FIRST HAVE SPECIFIC DEMOCRATIC CONDITIONS. THAT IS WHAT CRISTIANI SIGNED IN TELA, HONDURAS. WHAT WE ARE SEEING HERE IS THE UNMASKING OF A FASCIST DICTATORSHIP. WE ARE SEEING A FASCIST AND TERRORIST CLIQUE. THE MEMBERS OF THE DEATH SQUADS ARE PRACTICALLY LEGAL IN EL SALVADOR. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

TST1-MUC3-0086

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE FMLN FAILED EVEN BEFORE IT TRIED TO ENTER OUR COUN.... [CORRECTS HIMSELF] OUR CAPITAL, AND THIS WAS STATED BY TERRORISTS WHO HAVE SURRENDERED AND TERRORISTS WHO HAVE BEEN APPREHENDED. THEY SAID THAT THEY WERE BROUGHT TO THE CAPITAL UNDER FALSE PRETENSES. THEY WERE LED TO BELIEVE THAT THEY WERE GOING ALONG FOR A RIDE AND THAT ALL THE PEOPLE WOULD SUPPORT THEM, AND THAT THE ARMED FORCES WOULD NOT PUT UP A FIGHT. THIS, MORE THAN ANYTHING ELSE, HAS BEEN THE HARSHEST BLOW FOR THE FMLN BECAUSE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE REJECTED AND SPURNED THEM WHEN THEY TRIED TO EXPOSE THE PEOPLE TO SO MUCH DANGER AND HARM.

IT WAS ALSO SATISFACTORY TO HEAR THE MANY STATEMENTS OF SUPPORT AND SOLIDARITY GIVEN BY SO MANY SALVADORANS. THEY HAVE TALKED THROUGH THE NATIONAL NETWORK AND EVERY OTHER MEANS OF COMMUNICATION, AND HAVE REJECTED AND SPURNED THE FMLN AND ITS TERRORIST ACTIONS. FURTHERMORE, THE MINISTRY OF INTERIOR AND THE MINISTRIES OF AGRICULTURE AND ECONOMY ARE DRAFTING A PROGRAM TO HELP THE NEIGHBORHOODS WHICH HAVE BEEN AFFECTED BY THE FMLN'S ACTIONS--ONCE EVERYTHING IS CALM--AND TO RESUPPLY THE SUPERMARKETS AND STORES AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE. WE KNOW THE PEOPLE HAVE HAD PROBLEMS GETTING FOOD FOR THE LAST 2 AND 1/2 DAYS AND THE SUPPLIES SHOULD BE BROUGHT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE DO NOT WANT TO END THIS ADDRESS WITHOUT STATING OUR DEEP GRATITUDE FOR YOUR--AND THE OTHER SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S--COURAGEOUS ATTITUDE IN THE FACE OF THE FMLN AGGRESSION. WE CAN ONLY FEEL PROUD ABOUT THE MESSAGES OF SUPPORT--NOT FOR US ON A PERSONAL BASIS BUT FOR THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM, THE RIGHTS THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE DEMAND--AND FOR THE SUPPORT GIVEN TO THE ARMED FORCES, WHOSE MORALE IS HIGH AND WHO TAKE PRIDE IN THE PROFESSIONALISM WHICH THEY HAVE ACQUIRED THROUGHOUT THE YEARS TO COUNTER THE SITUATION IN THE SHORTEST TIME POSSIBLE.

WE KNOW THAT THE FMLN HAS FAILED, AND NOW IT IS A MATTER OF TIME BEFORE THE ARMED FORCES MANAGE TO TURN THE SITUATION AROUND COMPLETELY. ALSO, WE WANT TO STATE OUR DEEP GRATITUDE TO THE FRIENDLY COUNTRIES THAT HAVE SHOWN THEIR SUPPORT AND SOLIDARITY-- MOST OF ALL THEIR SOLIDARITY WITH YOU, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE-- BECAUSE THERE HAVE BEEN STATEMENTS WHICH, FRANKLY, HAVE FILLED US WITH EMOTION. FOR EXAMPLE, THOSE OF COSTA RICA, THE UNITED STAES, GUATEMALA, AND, IN SHORT, ALL THE OTHER COUNTRIES THAT KNOW PERFECTLY WELL HOW IRRATIONAL THE FMLN'S AGGRESSION IS. THEY HAVE REALIZED THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REPUBLIC, WHICH ARE THE RESULT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S WILL, HAVE BEGUN A RATIONAL, PEACEFUL, AND DEMOCRATIC PROCESS TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY.

TO CONCLUDE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE REQUEST YOUR SUPPORT AND UNDERSTANDING; BUT ALSO YOUR TRUST AND SERENITY. YOU CAN REST ASSURED THAT THE ARMED FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT WILL EMERGE VICTORIOUS FROM THE AGGRESSION WHICH THE FMLN TERRORISTS HAVE LAUNCHED. IT IS A DESPERATE ACTION AND, IN COUNTERING THE SITUATION, WE WILL BE MUCH CLOSER TO THE PEACE WE WANT SO MUCH. MAY GOD BLESS YOU ALL AND THANK YOU.

TST1-MUC3-0088

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] SAN SALVADOR DOMESTIC SERVICE IN SPANISH AT 1245 GMT ON 28 NOVEMBER BEGINS BROADCASTING A NUMBER OF REPORTS ON CLASHES BETWEEN SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES TROOPS AND FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REBELS ON 27 AND 28 NOVEMBER.

THE FIRST REPORT STATES THAT THE SALVADORAN TREASURY POLICE THWARTED AN FMLN ATTEMPT TO OCCUPY THE SAN SEBASTIAN NEIGHBORHOOD, CIUDAD DELGADO MUNICIPALITY. THE REPORT ADDS THAT APPROXIMATELY 50 "TERRORISTS" TRIED TO ENTER CIUDAD DELGADO AT 0500 ON 28 NOVEMBER AND THAT THEY CLASHED WITH TREASURY POLICE MEMBERS SUSTAINING TWO CASUALTIES. THE REPORT CONCLUDES SAYING THAT THE AUTHORITIES CONFISCATED ONE AK-47 RIFLE, ONE M-16 RIFLE, AMMUNITION FOR BOTH WEAPONS, AND SEVERAL STICKS OF DYNAMITE.

THE SECOND REPORT INDICATES THAT 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS CLASHED WITH FMLN FORCES AT NORTHERN LOS GUEVARAS HAMLET, LA LAGUNA JURISDICTION, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT. THE REPORT GOES ON TO SAY THAT AS A RESULT OF THE CLASHES, ONE REBEL WAS KILLED AND ONE M-16 RIFLE AND A COMMUNICATION RADIO WERE CONFISCATED.

THE NEXT REPORT SAYS THAT MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 1 REPORTED THAT TWO OF ITS MEMBERS WERE WOUNDED AFTER A GUERRILLA HARASSMENT OPERATION CONDUCTED IN CHIAPAS CANTON AND TEPEYAC HAMLET, CHALATENANGO CITY. THE SAME REPORT ADDS THAT MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 3 MEMBERS STATIONED IN LA UNION DEPARTMENT REPORTED THAT TWO FMLN REBELS WERE KILLED AND FIVE OTHERS WOUNDED DURING CLASHES NEAR EL REFUGIO FARM, SAN MIGUEL JURISDICTION IN THE AFTERNOON OF 27 NOVEMBER. THE REPORT ADDS THAT ONE SOLDIER WAS KILLED AND THREE OTHERS WERE WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACK.

THE NEXT REPORT SAYS THAT ARMED FORCES MILITARY TRAINING CENTER MEMBERS CONFISCATED 13 AR-15 RIFLES, 10 M-16 RIFLES, 1 HEAVY-CALIBER MORTAR, 2 GRENADES, AND EXPLOSIVES DURING A COMBING OPERATION IN ZAMORAN CANTON, SAN MIGUEL JURISDICTION. THE SAME REPORT ADDS THAT 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS CONFISCATED 3 M-60 MACHINEGUNS, 5 M-16 RIFLES, 1 RPG-18 ROCKET LAUNCHER, 150 CARTRIDGES AND EXPLOSIVES AT LAS LOMITAS CANTON AND EL MOLINO NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN MIGUEL CITY.

THE LAST REPORT INDICATES THAT THE NATIONAL POLICE DESTROYED AN FMLN SECURITY HOUSE IN NUEVA SAN SALVADOR, SANTA TECLA CITY, LA LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT. THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE ARMY TROOPS ARRESTED ONE FMLN "TERRORIST." THE REPORT SAYS THAT "DURING THIS SEARCH OPERATION, THE ARMY TROOPS CONFISCATED 3 SUBMACHINEGUNS, 1 SOVIET-MADE RPK AUTOMATIC RIFLE, 4 AKM RIFLES, 1 DRAGUNOV RIFLE, 1 AK-47 RIFLE, OVER 40,000 CARTRIDGES, 3,800 DETONATING PLUGS, 200 BENGAL LIGHTS, 6 GRENADES FOR RPG-2 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, 112 MANUALS FOR TERRORISTS, AND OTHER WAR MATERIEL."

THE REPORT CONCLUDES SAYING THAT DURING ANOTHER SEARCH OPERATION IN VALLE NUEVO NEIGHBORHOOD, ILOPANGO, NATIONAL POLICE MEMBERS DISCOVERED ANOTHER FMLN SECURITY HOUSE AND CONFISCATED 2 SUBMACHINEGUNS, 2 RIFLES, 650 CARTRIDGES, 6 STICKS OF DYNAMITE, 58 DETONATING PLUGS, AND OTHER EXPLOSIVES.

TST1-MUC3-0089

SAN SALVADOR, 9 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] YESTERDAY MORNING AT 0730, APPROXIMATELY 20 OR 30 TERRORISTS MACHINEGUNNED A ROUTE 302 BUS COVERING THE SAN SALVADOR - USULUTAN AND USULUTAN - SAN SALVADOR ROUTE. ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL REPORT, THIS CRIMINAL ACTION WAS CARRIED OUT BY THE ENEMIES OF THE PEOPLE. THE BUS, WITH LICENSE PLATE 76231, WAS ATTACKED ON THE COASTAL HIGHWAY NEAR LA TIENDITA CANTON, FUENTE RIO GUALEYO, TECOLUCA JURISDICTION, SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT. FIVE PASSENGERS TRAVELING ON THE BUS TO USULUTAN WERE INJURED DURING THIS AGGRESSIVE ACTION CARRIED OUT BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE INJURED PASSENGERS WERE IMMEDIATELY TAKEN TO THE SANTA TERESA HOSPITAL IN ZACATECOLUCA WHERE THEY ARE BEING TREATED.

LATER, AT APPROXIMATELY 0900 IN THE SAME AREA, CRIMINAL TERRORISTS BURNED NINE VEHICLES. INFORMATION CONCERNING THE BURNED VEHICLES HAS NOT BEEN PROVIDED.

MEANWHILE, FOUR REBELS WERE KILLED DURING AN ARMED CLASH WITH ENGINEERS MILITARY DETACHMENT TROOPS. THE FMLN TERRORISTS WERE ATTEMPTING TO ENTER THE CHINCHONTEPEQUE NEIGHBORHOOD IN ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT. THE SOLDIERS ALSO SEIZED THE FOLLOWING MATERIEL: 700 ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION FOR AK-47 RIFLES, 536 ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION FOR M-16 RIFLES, 3 KNAPSACKS WITH CIVILIAN CLOTHING, 6 AK-47 GRENADES, AND A G-3 RIFLE WITH A SERIAL NUMBER THAT CANNOT BE READ. THE ARMED FORCES ARE SHOWING THEIR PROFESSIONALISM BY FIGHTING AGAINST THE ENEMIES OF THE PEOPLE.

LIKEWISE, AN UNKNOWN NUMBER OF FMLN TERRORISTS ATTACKED THE EL TRIUNFO CIVIL DEFENSE POST, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT. THE FMLN REBELS BURNED THE MUNICIPAL MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THE ANTEL [NATIONAL ADMINISTRATION FOR TELECOMMUNICATIONS] OFFICES. THEY ALSO BURNED A GAS STATION OWNED BY VALENTIN VILLATORO AND DESTROYED A PYLON IN SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOOD. THE ATTACK ON THE DEFENSELESS RESIDENTS RESULTED IN ONE TERRORIST DEAD AND ONE WOUNDED. THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE RESIDENTS OF THE TOWN PRAISED THE ATTITUDE OF THE CIVIL DEFENSE MEMBERS AND REPUDIATED THE FMLN ASSASSINS FOR THEIR CONSTANT ATTACKS ON THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

TST1-MUC3-0091

CLANDESTINE, 28 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WHEN NAPOLEON DUARTE WAS PROCLAIMED PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR IN 1984, THE WHITE HOUSE, STATE DEPARTMENT, PENTAGON, AND ALL THE POWERFUL CIRCLES IN THE UNITED STATES WERE STRICKEN WITH EUPHORIA AND OPTIMISM. DUARTE PROMISED A SOCIAL PACT, A TOLERANT REGIME, ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL REFORMS, AND, MOST IMPORTANT OF ALL, HE PROMISED PEACE.

ALL OF THESE PROMISES WERE ONLY A MEANS OF ACHIEVING WASHINGTON'S GREAT OBJECTIVE: TO CONTROL THE REVOLUTION IN EL SALVADOR OR, IN OTHER WORDS, COUNTERINSURGENCY. FIVE YEARS HAVE PASSED SINCE THEN. IN REALITY 8 YEARS HAVE PASSED SINCE EL SALVADOR BECAME THE PLACE WHERE THE REAGAN ERA'S MODELS OF COUNTERINSURGENCY, NEODICTATORSHIP, AND LOW-INTENSITY WARFARE WERE IMPLEMENTED.

WASHINGTON'S EUPHORIA AND OPTIMISM HAVE COMPLETELY VANISHED. THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS SEALED THE COLLAPSE OF THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION'S SALVADORAN STRATEGY. TWO BASIC FACTORS ARE AT THE ROOT OF THE U.S. FAILURE: FIRST, THE UNITED STATES SOUGHT DEMAGOGIC AND POLITICALLY UNSOUND REFORMS. DUARTE DID NOT IN ANY WAY IMPROVE THE MASSES' EXTREME POVERTY AND ISOLATION. SECOND, THE REVOLUTIONARY, POPULAR, AND DEMOCRATIC FORCES' QUALITATIVE AND QUANTITATIVE PROGRESS WAS POSSIBLE BECAUSE THE PROBLEMS THAT LED TO THE CONFLICT ARE--TODAY MORE THAN EVER--STILL UNRESOLVED.

THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS RESULTED IN AN ARENA VICTORY, AND ARENA IS THE PARTY THAT REPRESENTS THE MOST ULTRACONSERVATIVE OLIGARCHIC SECTORS. WASHINGTON HAS RETURNED TO ITS STARTING POINT. THE $3 BILLION SPENT ON MILITARY ADVICE AND THE GENOCIDE OF TENS OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS SERVED NO PURPOSE WHATSOEVER. IT IS ALL OVER. ARENA REPRESENTS A RETURN TO THE SYSTEM USED PRIOR TO 15 OCTOBER 1979. IN OTHER WORDS, IT IS A RETURN TO DICTATORIAL CONTROL OF ALL POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND MILITARY POWER. THIS IS THE END, THE SAD END OF THE LOW-INTENSITY WAR EXERCISE.

U.S. GENERAL HARRY GORDON SUMMER, A MEMBER OF THE SANTA FE GROUP, IN HIS BOOK ON THE MISTAKES THE UNITED STATES MADE IN VIETNAM, SAID THE UNITED STATES' CONCEPT OF VICTORY AFTER ITS DEFEAT IN VIETNAM CAN NO LONGER BE TO ACHIEVE ITS ENEMY'S UNCONDITIONAL SURRENDER, AS IN WORLD WAR II, BUT TO ACHIEVE THE POLITICAL OBJECTIVES FOR WHICH IT STARTED THE WAR. THIS IS PRECISELY THE CONCEPT OF VICTORY USED IN LOW-INTENSITY WARFARE. ARENA'S VICTORY, AND THE SUBSEQUENT RETURN TO THE OLD SYSTEM, IS OBVIOUSLY CONTRARY TO THE OBJECTIVE OF LOW-INTENSITY WARFARE.

FOR WASHINGTON, OF COURSE, THIS DEFEAT MEANS THAT $3 BILLION WAS SQUANDERED. FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND CENTRAL AMERICANS, IT MEANS RAZED TOWNS, DEVASTATED ECONOMIES, AND THE DEATH OF 70,000 PEOPLE. THE NEW U.S. ADMINISTRATION DOES NOT HAVE A DEFINITE PLAN FOR EL SALVADOR. WHAT IT HAS IS AN UNCOMFORTABLE ALLY, ARENA, AND A SOCIAL TIME BOMB ABOUT TO EXPLODE.

THE FMLN BELIEVES THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION SHOULD STUDY THE NEW SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR AND THE ENTIRE WORLD IN A REALISTIC AND PRAGMATIC MANNER. THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR CONTINUES AND WILL CONTINUE AS LONG AS THERE IS NO CHANGE, NO REAL CHANGE, TO BENEFIT THE MASSES THAT ARE STRUGGLING FOR THAT CHANGE. THIS IS OUR NEW REALITY, AND IF THE NEW U.S. ADMINISTRATION WANTS PEACE AND STABILITY IN THE REGION, IT MUST ESTABLISH A FOREIGN POLICY THAT REFLECTS THAT REALITY.

TST1-MUC3-0092

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] 4. AT 0640 AN FMLN GUERRILLA UNIT LAUNCHED AN ATTACK ON CONCHAGUA BATTALION AND 3D MILITARY DETACHMENT SOLDIERS WHO WERE TRAVELING ON THE ROAD BETWEEN ANAMOROS AND LISLIQUE, 1 KM FROM LISLIQUE, LA UNION DEPARTMENT. THE CLASH, CARRIED OUT IN BROAD DAYLIGHT, ENDED AT 0930. WE KILLED THREE AND WOUNDED FIVE, AND TOOK FOUR PRISONERS OF WAR IN THAT AREA OF LA UNION DEPARTMENT. A CHIEF OF SECTION, A SERGEANT, IS AMONG THE DEAD. WE SEIZED SIX RIFLES, AN M-79 GRENADE LAUNCHER, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. MEANWHILE, ANOTHER FMLN UNIT ENTERED LISLIQUE, WHERE THEY CARRIED OUT POLITICAL ACTIVITIES FOR 3 HOURS.

5. AT 0300 FMLN UNITS ATTACKED AN INFANTRY COMPANY AT THE MOUTH OF THE LEMPA RIVER, AND 30 MINUTES LATER OUR FORCES HAD TAKEN OVER THE POST. WE KILLED ONE AND WOUNDED FOUR, AND SEIZED A RIFLE, A LAW ROCKET LAUNCHER, THREE BACKPACKS, AND WAR MATERIEL.

6. URBAN GUERRILLAS SABOTAGED PYLONS AND TRANSFORMERS IN SAN MIGUEL CITY.

7. A NATIONAL POLICE POST IN BERLIN WAS RAIDED AND ATTACKED.

ATTENTION: DURING THIS OPERATION LAUNCHED THROUGHOUT THE FOUR EASTERN DEPARTMENTS, WE INFLICTED A TOTAL OF 67 CASUALTIES. AMONG THESE CASUALTIES ARE: THE CHIEF OF THE CACAHUATIQUE BATTALION, A CAPTAIN, A LIEUTENANT, AND A SERGEANT. WE CAPTURED SIX PRISONERS OF WAR DURING THIS OPERATION. WE ALSO SEIZED 37 RIFLES, A 90-MM CANNON, 2 M-70 MACHINE GUNS, 3 LAW ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 3 M-79 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, 5 MILITARY RADIOS, 38 BACKPACKS, AND 6,800 ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION, AND WE DAMAGED A HELICOPTER. THIS IS THE RESULT OF OUR OPERATION: THE EASTERN SECTOR IS COURAGEOUS; EVERYONE AGAINST ARENA.

TST1-MUC3-0093

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE WILL ORGANIZE A PLURALIST GOVERNMENT WHICH INCLUDES REPRESENTATIVES OF ALL THE PATRIOTIC GROUPS OF THE NATION. LET US SAVE OUR CAPITAL, WHICH IS BEING BOMBED DUE TO A FOREIGN MENTALITY. IT IS BEING BOMBED AND DESTROYED BY AN OCCUPATION ARMY. THE AIRPLANES ARE NOW BEING FLOWN BY U.S. PILOTS AT NIGHT, AND THEY HAVE THE MENTALITY OF AN OCCUPATION ARMY.

SALVADORANS, LET US UNITE AND ORGANIZE OURSELVES. LET US NOT REMAIN IDLE. WE MUST MOBILIZE OURSELVES RIGHT NOW AND ORGANIZE A COMMITTEE IN EACH NEIGHBORHOOD, RESIDENTIAL AREA, AND TOWN. THE PEOPLE MUST ORGANIZE. THE FMLN HAS BEGUN ITS 7TH DAY IN THE CAPITAL, AND WE ARE SURE THAT WE ARE ADVANCING TOWARD VICTORY. VICTORY WILL BE OURS AND COLONEL PONCE HAS GIVEN PROOF OF HIS DESPERATION WITH THE JESUIT PRIESTS' ASSASSINATION IN SAN SALVADOR. HE HAS OVERSTEPPED HIS MARK AND THE PEOPLE'S PATIENCE IS EXHAUSTED. WE URGE ALL OUR PEOPLE TO JOIN THE GENERAL UPRISING, STRUGGLE, TAKE UP WEAPONS, AND ORGANIZE EVERYTHING NECESSARY TO OUST THIS CORRUPT AND MURDEROUS REGIME. WE URGE THE PEOPLE TO MOBILIZE,TO TAKE UP WEAPONS, AND TO STAY IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTIAL AREAS TO STRUGGLE FOR THE LIBERATION OF OUR HOMELAND. WE MUST ACHIEVE PROGRESS.

INFORMATION HAS JUST ARRIVED FROM THE UNITED STATES, INDICATING THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS BEGUN TO WITHDRAW ITS UNCONDITIONAL SUPPORT FOR THE DEATH SQUADS IN EL SALVADOR. INFORMATION RECEIVED FROM THE UNITED STATES INDICATES THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS BEGUN TO RECANT ITS IRRESPONSIBLE AND GENOCIDAL ATTITUDE OF SENDING U.S. PILOTS TO BOMB OUR CAPITAL BY NIGHT. THAT IS THE PROFESSIONAL TRAINING THAT U.S. IMPERIALISM IS CURRENTLY GIVING THE ARMED FORCES, MEANING TO BOMB THE CAPITAL BY NIGHT, AS ALL THE PEOPLE IN THE CAPITAL HAVE WITNESSED IN RECENT HOURS.

THUS, WE ISSUE AN APPEAL TO THE PEOPLE: ORGANIZE YOURSELVES. WE WILL ACHIEVE VICTORY. WE SURE OF THIS. THE BLOOD OF IGNACIO ELLACURIA, THE BLOOD OF THE JESUITS, THE BLOOD OF MONSIGNOR [ARNULFO] ROMERO, THE BLOOD OF THE FOUR U.S. NUNS, THE BLOOD OF THE 11 PRIESTS ASSASSINATED [WORDS INDISTINCT], THE BLOOD OF [WORDS INDISTINCT] SEMINARIANS, YOUTHS [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND FOR ALL THE BLOOD SHED. WE MUST WIN, WE MUST ACHIEVE VICTORY, WE MUST ATTAIN A TRUE DEMOCRACY FOR OUR HOMELAND -- A DEMOCRACY WITH FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION, FOOD, EDUCATION, AND JUSTICE.

TST1-MUC3-0096

GUATEMALA CITY, 28 MAR 89 (CADENA DE EMISORAS UNIDAS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT] [TEXT] THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT REPORTS THAT ON SUNDAY, 26 MARCH, AS RELATIVES WERE VISITING THE PAVON REHABILITATION FARM, A PRISON REVOLT ERUPTED. THE REVOLT WAS STARTED BY 28 PRISONERS -- ALL CONSIDERED VERY DANGEROUS -- ORGANIZED INTO SEVEN GROUPS.

THE MUTINIOUS PRISONERS WORKED OUT A DETAILED PLAN AND ATTACKED VARIOUS IMPORTANT OFFICES, SUCH AS THE ARMORY, WHERE THEY SEIZED ABOUT 90 CARBINES AND MUCH AMMUNITION, WHICH THEY IMMEDIATELY USED TO ATTACK THE SECURITY GUARDS. AT THE TIME, THERE WERE 107 MEN, 366 WOMEN, AND 154 CHILDREN -- A TOTAL OF 627 PEOPLE -- VISITING THE DETAINEES. THEY HAVE BEEN HELD HOSTAGE SINCE THE UPRISING BEGAN.

THE PRISONERS' ESCAPE ATTEMPT WAS THWARTED BY THE SECURITY GUARDS, WHO WERE ABLE TO CARRY OUT THEIR ASSIGNED MISSION. THE GUARDS WERE ABLE TO REPEL THE SURPISE ATTACK; HOWEVER, CORRECTIONAL OFFICERS BUENAVENTURA MARTINEZ, 47, AND GERONIMO ALVARADO, 21, WERE KILLED IN THE CLASH.

THE GOVERNMENT STATES THAT ACCORDING TO ITS INVESTIGATION, THE LEADERS OF THE RIOT WERE JULIO ENRIQUE REYES GRANADOS, MARCO ANTONIO SANTIZO LINARES, AND VICTOR MANUEL VELIZ DUARTE, WHO ARE DOING TIME FOR KIDNAPPING CHILDREN, EXTORTION, MURDER, ROBBERY, ASSAULT AND BATTERY, AND OTHER CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES. VELIZ DUARTE WAS KILLED IN THE CLASH BY GUNSHOTS TO HIS JAW AND STOMACH. HE HAD BEEN SENTENCED TO 30 YEARS IN PRISON FOR DOUBLE MURDER.

FOLLOWING THE UNSUCCESSFUL UPRISING IN THE PAVON MODEL REHABILITATION FARM, A COMMISSION OF PRISONERS HAS PRESENTED A HUMANITARIAN PETITION TO THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT, WHICH IS BEING CONSIDERED. OTHER LEGAL PETITIONS WILL BE DEALT WITH BY THE APPROPRIATE ORGANIZATIONS.

TST1-MUC3-0097

TEGUCIGALPA, 6 FEB 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE HONDURAN POLICE TODAY PRESENTED TO REPORTERS TWO OF THE PRESUMED KILLERS OF CONTRA COMMANDER MANUEL RUGAMA ACEVEDO, ALIAS "AURELIANO." ONE OF THE MEN ACCUSED AN OFFICIAL OF THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA OF INVOLVEMENT IN THE CRIME.

"AURELIANO," CONSIDERED TO BE THE SECOND IN COMMAND OF THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS, WAS GUNNED DOWN BY AN UNIDENTIFIED GROUP IN TEGUCIGALPA'S NORTHERN OUTSKIRTS ON 7 JANUARY AFTER ATTENDING A WORKING MEETING WITH OTHER REBEL LEADERS.

THE POLICE DETAINED HONDURANS JUAN BAUTISTA AND RIGOBERTO MATUTE AND NICARAGUAN LUIS ORDONEZ, WHO ARE BEING HELD AS SUSPECTS IN AURELIANO'S MURDER. OTHER SUSPECTS ARE STILL BEING PURSUED.

ONLY BAUTISTA AND ORDONEZ WERE PRESENTED TO REPORTERS. MATUTE IS BEING HELD OUTSIDE TEGUCIGALPA AS A WITNESS IN THE CASE.

ORDONEZ SAID HE "PARTICIPATED ONLY AS A GO-BETWEEN" SO JOSE DE JESUS PENA, THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY OFFICIAL, COULD MEET MATUTE, WHO WORKED AS A MESSENGER FOR ORDONEZ AT THE EXCHANGE OFFICE HE RUNS IN TEGUCIGALPA.

ORDONEZ ADDED: "I WAS AWARE THAT PENA WANTED TO GET RID OF SOMEBODY, BUT I NEVER LEARNED WHO THEY WERE GOING TO KILL UNTIL 'AURELIANO' WAS ELIMINATED."

ORDONEZ ALSO SAID HE WORKED FOR THE SOMOZA REGIME, THAT HE LATER AIDED THE CONTRAS FINANCIALLY IN HONDURAS, PARTICULARLY THE REBEL INDIAN ORGANIZATION MISURASATA [MISKITO, SUMU, AND RAMA SANDINIST UNITY], AND THAT WIDCLIFE DIEGO, A MISURASATA LEADER, OWES HIM $25,000.

ORDONEZ SAID FURTHER THAT HE PROVIDED INFORMATION ON THE CONTRAS SEVERAL TIMES TO THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY THROUGH PENA, WHO GAVE HIM $1,000 ALMOST EVERY MONTH.

ORDONEZ DENIED THAT HE PARTICIPATED DIRECTLY IN THE CRIME: "ON SATURDAY, 7 JANUARY, WHEN 'AURELIANO' WAS KILLED, I WAS AT A COCK FIGHT IN EL PROGRESO" ON HONDURAS' NORTHERN COAST.

ORDONEZ SAID: "I ALSO WAS IN TOUCH WITH THE HONDURAN SECRET POLICE, ONE OF WHOSE LIEUTENANTS, WORKING FOR INTERPOL, CALLED ME UP A FEW DAYS AGO. HE TOLD ME LATER, HOWEVER, THAT OTHER OFFICERS WANTED TO SEE ME. THAT IS HOW I WAS DETAINED."

IN ADDITION, BAUTISTA CLAIMED THAT HE WAS HIRED BY MATUTE DURING TWO MEETINGS THEY HELD AND THAT MATUTE OFFERED TO PAY HIM $10,000 TO KILL SOMEBODY, PRESUMABLY A CONTRA COMMANDER WHO ALSO INTENDED TO KILL MATUTE.

BAUTISTA SAID THAT A FEW DAYS PRIOR TO THE CRIME, MATUTE INTRODUCED TO HIM ANOTHER PERSON, CANO ARTEAGA, WHO IS STILL AT LARGE AND WHO TOLD BAUTISTA THAT IT WAS ORDONEZ WHO WANTED THE MAN DEAD.

BAUTISTA SAID THAT, ON THE DAY OF THE CRIME, HE MET WITH MATUTE AND CANO. THEY DROVE AROUND THE PLACE SEVERAL TIMES UNTIL THEY INTERCEPTED THE CONTRA COMMANDER'S CAR.

"I OPENED FIRE WITH A .38 CALIBER REVOLVER. AURELIANO GOT OUT OF THE CAR AND WAS HIT BY MATUTE'S SHOTS. CANO FINISHED HIM OFF."

BAUTISTA SAID HIS TWO COMPANIONS WERE ARMED WITH .45 CALIBER PISTOLS. AFTER THE CRIME, THEY WENT THEIR SEPARATE WAYS TO WAIT TO RECEIVE THE PROMISED MONEY IN A TEGUCIGALPA PARK ON 15 FEBRUARY.

POLICE SOURCES AND COLONEL MANUEL ENRIQUE SUAREZ, HEAD OF THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES' PUBLIC RELATIONS DEPARTMENT, WHO PRESENTED THE CRIMINALS TO THE REPORTERS, DECLINED TO COMMENT ON THE INVOLVEMENT OF A NICARAGUAN EMBASSY OFFICIAL IN THE CRIME.

SUAREZ SAID: "IT IS UP TO THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT TO COMMENT ON THIS CASE OR TO TRY TO ESTABLISH WHETHER A DIPLOMAT PARTICIPATED. THE POLICE HAVE ALREADY DONE THEIR DUTY."

THERE WAS NOBODY AVAILABLE AT THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA TO COMMENT ON THE ALLEDGED INVOLVEMENT OF ONE OF THE EMBASSY OFFICIALS IN THE ASSASSINATION. THE EMBASSY WOULD NEITHER CONFIRM NOR DENY THAT SOMEONE NAMED JOSE DE JESUS PENA WORKED THERE.

TST1-MUC3-0099

LIMA, 25 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT TERRORISTS TONIGHT BOMBED THE EMBASSIES OF THE PRC AND THE SOVIET UNION. THE BOMBS CAUSED DAMAGE BUT NO INJURIES.

A CAR-BOMB EXPLODED IN FRONT OF THE PRC EMBASSY, WHICH IS IN THE LIMA RESIDENTIAL DISTRICT OF SAN ISIDRO. MEANWHILE, TWO BOMBS WERE THROWN AT A USSR EMBASSY VEHICLE THAT WAS PARKED IN FRONT OF THE EMBASSY LOCATED IN ORRANTIA DISTRICT, NEAR SAN ISIDRO.

POLICE SAID THE ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY AND THAT THE BOMBS BROKE WINDOWS AND DESTROYED THE TWO VEHICLES.

NO ONE HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACKS SO FAR. POLICE SOURCES, HOWEVER, HAVE SAID THE ATTACKS COULD HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT BY THE MAOIST "SHINING PATH" GROUP OR THE GUEVARIST "TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT" (MRTA) GROUP. THE SOURCES ALSO SAID THAT THE SHINING PATH HAS ATTACKED SOVIET INTERESTS IN PERU IN THE PAST.

IN JULY 1989 THE SHINING PATH BOMBED A BUS CARRYING NEARLY 50 SOVIET MARINES INTO THE PORT OF EL CALLAO. FIFTEEN SOVIET MARINES WERE WOUNDED.

SOME 3 YEARS AGO TWO MARINES DIED FOLLOWING A SHINING PATH BOMBING OF A MARKET USED BY SOVIET MARINES.

IN ANOTHER INCIDENT 3 YEARS AGO, A SHINING PATH MILITANT WAS KILLED BY SOVIET EMBASSY GUARDS INSIDE THE EMBASSY COMPOUND. THE TERRORIST WAS CARRYING DYNAMITE.

THE ATTACKS TODAY COME AFTER SHINING PATH ATTACKS DURING WHICH LEAST 10 BUSES WERE BURNED THROUGHOUT LIMA ON 24 OCT.

TST1-MUC3-0100

LIMA, 1 APR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN TODAY ENTERED ITS FINAL STRETCH, WITH ONLY ONE WEEK TO GO IN AN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN THAT HAS BEEN THE MOST DISPUTED AND DANGEROUS ONE IN THE HISTORY OF THAT ANDEAN COUNTRY, PRIMARILY BECAUSE OF TERRORIST THREATS.

THE SPREADING WAVE OF TERRORISM, AIMED AT STOPPING THE ELECTIONS FROM TAKING PLACE, FORCED PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA'S ADMINISTRATION TO TAKE DRASTIC SECURITY MEASURES TO PROTECT THE NEARLY 3,500 CANDIDATES [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] ARE DEPLOYED, ESPECIALLY IN AREAS UNDER STATE OF EMERGENCY AND WHERE THE ACTIVITIES OF SHINING PATH'S TERRORIST GANGS ARE MORE WIDESPREAD, SUCH AS LIMA AND THE DEPARTMENTS OF AYACUCHO, HUANCAVELICA, APURIMAC, AND JUNIN.

THE GOVERNMENT HAS APPOINTED FOUR MEMBERS OF THE SECURITY FORCES TO PROTECT EACH CANDIDATE AND HAS TAKEN OUT LIFE INSURANCE ON ALMOST 250,000 PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN SELECTED BY LOTTERY TO WORK AT OVER 52,000 POLLING STATIONS. IN LIMA ALONE, HUNDREDS OF MEMBERS OF POLLING STATION TEAMS HAVE ASKED TO BE RELIEVED OF THIS DUTY, PETITIONS WHICH FOR THE MOST PART HAVE BEEN REFUSED BY THE THE ELECTORAL COURT.

IN LIMA, THE MAIN OBSTACLE TO NORMAL ELECTIONS ON SUNDAY COULD BE THE STRIKE OF PRIVATE BUS OWNERS WHO ARE AFRAID OF TERRORIST REPRISALS. THE "MINI-BUS-OWNERS" (INDIVIDUAL OWNERS OF URBAN BUSES) HAVE ASKED THAT FOUR POLICEMEN BE ASSIGNED TO EACH BUS, A REQUEST THAT DEPARTMENTAL PREFECT (GOVERNOR) JACOBO MISHKIN HAS DEEMED "IMPOSSIBLE."

"IF THERE IS NO TRANSPORTATION, THE PEOPLE WILL WALK," PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA HAS SAID, REAFFIRMING HIS "ABSOLUTE CONFIDENCE" THAT THE PERUVIAN PEOPLE WILL VOTE EN MASSE -- DESPITE THE TERRORIST THREATS -- TO "STRENGTHEN DEMOCRACY," RECOVERED IN 1980 AFTER 12 YEARS OF MILITARY GOVERNMENTS. PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, NATIONAL ELECTION BOARD PRESIDENT CARLOS CASTANEDA, AND THE CANDIDATES HAVE BEEN URGING THE NEARLY 10 MILLION VOTERS TO COMPLY WITH THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY BY CASTING THEIR VOTES.

THE GOVERNMENT CLAIMS THAT A LARGE TURNOUT WILL AMOUNT TO "THE MOST EFFECTIVE REJECTION OF SUBVERSION" AND THAT IT WILL "STRENGTHEN DEMOCRACY" IN PERU, WHICH HAS ALMOST 22 MILLION INHABITANTS.

OUT OF THE NINE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES, FOUR HAVE THE BEST CHANCES, ALTHOUGH ONLY THE CANDIDATE OF THE CENTER RIGHT, MARIO VARGAS LLOSA, IS THE CLEAR-CUT FAVORITE. HE WILL GET AN ESTIMATED 45 PERCENT OF THE VOTES, ACCORDING TO THE LATEST SURVEYS.

ACCORDING TO PERUVIAN LAW, IF VARGAS LLOSA DOES NOT GET ABSOLUTE MAJORITY HE WILL HAVE TO PARTICIPATE IN A RUNOFF ELECTION WITH THE SECOND-PLACE CANDIDATE. SINCE IT IS QUITE CERTAIN THAT VARGAS LLOSA, THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE DEMOCRATIC FRONT (FREDEMO), WILL WIN THE FIRST ROUND, THE QUESTION NOW IS WHO WILL BE HIS RIVAL FOR THE PRESIDENCY IN THE SECOND ROUND. ACCORDING TO THE SURVEYS, THE CANDIDATES WITH THE BEST CHANCE ARE LUIS ALVA CASTRO OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA), WITH 19 PERCENT OF THE VOTES; ALFONSO BARRANTES LINGAN OF THE SOCIALIST LEFT (IS), WITH 12 PERCENT; AND HENRY PEASE OF THE COMMUNIST LEFT WING COALITION UNITED LEFT (IU), WITH 8 PERCENT.

DURING THE LAST FIVE DAYS OF THEIR CAMPAIGNS THE CANDIDATES WILL STEP UP THEIR TRIPS TO VARIOUS POINTS OF THE COUNTRY TRYING TO GAIN THE VOTES OF A LARGE UNDECIDED SECTOR OF THE POPULATION. ACCORDING TO THE SURVEYS, THIS SECTOR REPRESENTS BETWEEN 18 AND 20 PERCENT OF THE VOTES.

MEANWHILE THE TERRORISTS CONTINUE ON THEIR PATH OF DEATH AND DESTRUCTION. IN THE LAST 24 HOURS THE SHINING PATH MURDERED TWO STATE OFFICIALS OF THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] ON A ROAD LINKING CHAVIN AND HUARI, TWO TOWNS IN ANCASH DEPARTMENT. IN HUARAZ, THE CAPITAL OF ANCASH DEPARTMENT, THE TERRORISTS SET FIRE TO THE OFFICES OF THE LOCAL DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION BUT INJURED NO ONE. ONE PERSON DIED WHEN AN ORE TRAIN WAS DERAILED NEAR OROYA, A KEY MINING TOWN IN THE PERUVIAN CENTRAL JUNGLE AREA, WHERE AN ELECTORAL REGISTRATION OFFICE WAS LOCATED. SEVEN PRIVATE BANK BRANCHES WERE ALSO ATTACKED AND SERIOUSLY DAMAGED IN LIMA. IN BARRANCA, A SMALL VILLAGE 180 KM FROM LIMA, TERRORISTS BOMBED A RADIO STATION AND A DRUGSTORE, BOTH OF THEM BELONGING TO SANTIAGO JAO, A FREDEMO CANDIDATE FOR DEPUTY.